<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/why-seen/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2025-08-26T22:05:27+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/why-seen/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">SEEN | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Sex Equality and Equity Network</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">SEEN in Northern Ireland</title>
      <link href="/posts/2024-11-18-seen-in-northern-ireland/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="SEEN in Northern Ireland" />
      <published>2024-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2024-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/seen-in-northern-ireland</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2024-11-18-seen-in-northern-ireland/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A member of SEEN based in Northern Ireland provides some reflections on the setting up of a SEEN in Northern Ireland group, and meeting other members of SEEN based in Northern Ireland for the first time.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was towards the end of last year that I first learned about SEEN. And, as the kids say, I finally felt “seen”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with many civil servants, I was increasingly concerned about the promotion of policies based on the concept of gender identity, rather than the protected characteristic of sex, across staff networks. Not to mention the proliferation of practices in relation to identity politics, such as pronouns in email signatures, and the general sense that “diversity and inclusion” meant submission to a strict set of beliefs which I did not share. Bring my “whole self” to work? How could I do that when social media told the horrid tale of what happened to those who were vocal about their belief in the importance of basic biology? It seemed that, wherever you looked, people were bullied – and worse – for raising concerns about the impact of ideas based on gender identity on the sex-based rights of women, as well as on gay rights and the safeguarding of children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet at the time I felt that there was no choice but to suck it up - friends and family warned me against putting my head above the parapet for fear of repercussions, both social and professional. I had resigned myself to biting my tongue and tolerating the avalanche of material promoting ideas based on gender identity politics, until one night on X I saw a post about SEEN.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not an exaggeration to say that SEEN has been a revelation for me. The very fact of knowing that there were hundreds of colleagues out there who share my beliefs and concerns was comfort in itself. But when I dug into the articles on the SEEN website, and got a sense of how genuinely tolerant, civil and professional the network is, I knew I wanted to get involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The journey to establishing a SEEN NI Chapter has been a fulfilling one. I began by speaking with SEEN leaders in other departments, who put me in touch with other NI-based civil servants who had come across the network in a similar manner to me. I met with them one by one, formed connections, and we now have a thriving band of gender critical folk who keep each other sane via coffees and lively chats. What started as a tentative exercise - we joked about creeping around like members of the French resistance - has evolved into a forum in which we can share views, highlight successes, and encourage each other to stand up for what we believe in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without the support of the SEEN NI cohort, for example, I wouldn’t have had the courage to hold a meeting with HR and D&amp;amp;I seniors to raise concerns about our department’s adherence to the Civil Service Code in the context of Pride Month. Or to challenge the views of a stakeholder who was dismissive of gender critical beliefs. In the SEEN NI group, despite our different backgrounds, experiences and politics, we have each other’s backs when it comes to combating overreach and disinformation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there is no doubt that our voices are being heard. As other bloggers have noted, progress can be slow and frustrating at times, but SEEN has taught me what can be achieved when rational, reasonable and tolerant people get together. So I would encourage any civil servant in Northern Ireland who shares our beliefs to get in touch. You’ll have a warm welcome in SEEN NI - to adopt a term that has been weaponised elsewhere, it truly is a “safe space”!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you are a member of SEEN and interested in finding more about the SEEN in Northern Ireland group, or if you would like to find out more about Chapters of SEEN in general, keep an eye out for email correspondence via the SEEN mailing list for contact details.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you are a civil servant and would like to join SEEN please submit your membership request via &lt;a href=&quot;https://seen-network.uk/join/&quot;&gt;our ‘join us’ page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover photo&lt;/strong&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@wwarby?utm_content=creditCopyText&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_source=unsplash&quot;&gt;William Warby&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/photos/a-black-and-white-photo-of-a-rocky-beach-_K1qXCM8yKg?utm_content=creditCopyText&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_source=unsplash&quot;&gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>UNSEEN</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="personal experience" />
      
        <category term="why seen" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">A member of SEEN based in Northern Ireland provides some reflections on the setting up of a SEEN in Northern Ireland group, and meeting other members of SEEN based in Northern Ireland for the first time.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">SEEN in Scotland</title>
      <link href="/posts/2024-11-07-seen-in-scotland/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="SEEN in Scotland" />
      <published>2024-11-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2024-11-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/seen-in-scotland</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2024-11-07-seen-in-scotland/">&lt;p&gt;A member of SEEN based in Scotland provides some reflections on the setting up of a SEEN in Scotland Group, and meeting other members of SEEN based in Scotland for the first time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chilling, silencing, fear and hurt were common themes at the first meeting to establish a Scotland Group of members of SEEN, along with frustration that such emotions are provoked for holding what are in reality widely held and evidence-based beliefs – that biological sex is real, immutable and in many cases important. The group was also surprisingly diverse, containing a mixture of ages, both sexes, and a wide range of perspectives and routes which had drawn them first to this issue and then to get involved in SEEN.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it was this backdrop which made the meeting a little odd – like a reluctantly clandestine and random group blind date. However, it is also what made the meeting feel so positive and productive. An active step to find a voice, connect with others, and make a difference.  Our discussions focussed on ways that the culture of “no debate” is impacting colleagues both in a personal sense and on the performance of the civil service as a whole. From a personal perspective it is clear that the “bring your whole self to work” ethos does not apply if that includes having concerns around the impact of implementing policies based on belief in the concept of gender identity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The group shared their experiences of feeling unable to talk about family issues at work or expressing honest concerns around mixed sex facilities which made them feel vulnerable. This was all compounded by a feeling that unions would not support them in upholding the lawful provision of single-sex facilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More widely, there was significant concern around the impact on quality of work and professional standards in the workplace, such as the ability to freely interrogate policy, taking a balanced approach to consultation on the collection and recording of data, and taking a truly evidence-based approach to decision making. While there are obvious examples of recent legislation in Scotland to which this applies, I was surprised to learn how far reaching the effect has been with implications for so many policy areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SEEN now has over 900 members across the UK and while our numbers remain small in Scotland they are growing. If you are a Scotland-based civil servant and you share these concerns I urge you to find your voice and get involved. By signing up you contribute anonymously through surveys and research. You can also choose to connect with others and get more involved in the Scotland Group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need a voice at the table and with more members our voice will be strengthened and our fear reduced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you are a member of SEEN and interested in finding more about the SEEN in Scotland Group, or if you would like to find out more about Chapters of SEEN in general, keep an eye out for email correspondence via the SEEN mailing list for contact details.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you are a civil servant and would like to join SEEN please submit your membership request via &lt;a href=&quot;https://seen-network.uk/join/&quot;&gt;our ‘join us’ page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover photo&lt;/strong&gt; with kind permission from a SEEN member. All rights reserved.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>UNSEEN</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="personal experience" />
      
        <category term="why seen" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">A member of SEEN based in Scotland provides some reflections on the setting up of a SEEN in Scotland Group, and meeting other members of SEEN based in Scotland for the first time.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Menopause: A radical perspective</title>
      <link href="/posts/2024-01-17-menopause-a-radical-perspective/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Menopause: A radical perspective" />
      <published>2024-01-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2024-01-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/menopause-a-radical-perspective</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2024-01-17-menopause-a-radical-perspective/">&lt;p&gt;As a 47-year-old woman, it’s not surprising that I’m heartened by the increasing visibility and normalisation of menopause – whether I like it or not, that train is pulling into the station some time soon. But the litany of common problems – the brain fog, the sleeplessness, the pains and sweats – that sounds like a bad cosmic joke, that each new chapter of female life must open with a new swathe of physical inconvenience. Is nature itself a misogynist? No wonder most world religions contend that women are being punished for some original sin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who would want to be a girl? No matter how much my mum insisted slightly desperately that ‘being a girl is just as good as being a boy,’ it just didn’t ring true. How can it be as good? I’m doomed to be weaker, and fatter! I could be attacked, or raped. I have to deal with periods, I could get pregnant. If I ever want a child I’ll &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; to get pregnant. Women get paid less, taken less seriously, expected to shave their legs and wear make-up to look ‘normal’. Name me just one thing that is better for girls! See!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a teenager I was grimly determined to compensate for my bad luck at the sex lottery, the cruel roulette that had put an X chromosome in the way of my human self-actualisation. On my grandparents’ farm I hefted haybales on my own, not one-between-two like mere aunties and mums. I wore trousers with my Venture Scouts uniform, and hauled a superabundance of sanitary products and painkillers on all-day hikes. At school I marched the other way whenever I saw creepy Mr Richards, who addressed all the girls while looking directly at their breasts. I tried, repeatedly, to explain to priapic teenage boys in pub car parks that I thought we were friends. At university I wore a bristling leather jacket and made it clear I could walk home on my own, thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was studying political philosophy, especially the development of post-Enlightenment concepts of the ‘political individual’, who could consent to mutual obligations rather than owing duty to a lord. Foundational thinkers such as Locke and Rousseau had banished women as a sex to the ‘private sphere’, on the basis that they were by nature too emotional, too unruly, to partake in public life (and, presumably, because otherwise there would be no-one to clean the houses and raise the children of the Great Men).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While writing my dissertation, I came across feminist political theorist Carole Pateman. Pateman’s thesis was that the Great Men didn’t &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; exclude women from political personhood out of prejudice and expediency. Rather, the individual they defined had specifically male characteristics which women could not share. Pateman wrote that “the body of the ‘individual’ is very different from women’s bodies. His body is tightly enclosed within boundaries, but women’s bodies are permeable, their contours change shape and they are subject to cyclical processes. All these differences are summed up in the natural bodily process of birth.” I thought this was reductive nonsense. What if women don’t &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; shifting contours and cyclical processes? What if they would like to reproduce (if at all) on an equal basis with men? It seemed a bit embarrassing that these middle-aged feminists were wanging on about some female birth-giving energy or whatever – wouldn’t it be better to stop framing all that icky, painful business as ‘female’, so that it didn’t hold individual women back from their potential? It seemed obvious to me that the solution was not, as Pateman recommended, to create two political actors, one of each sex, but to make sure the political individual was neutral, unsexed, to accommodate all shades of glorious human diversity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I moved through my 20s, though, my sex continued, stubbornly, to affect my life. I wasn’t doing feminine things – hell, I wasn’t even doing specifically female things like having periods or, god forbid, children. And yet I still had to think differently, act differently to men, to navigate my reality – the man who flashed at me as I walked home from the Tube station, or the one who found it funny to follow me along the dark road, didn’t seem to know or care what I felt about my boundaries, permeable or otherwise. I started to become less resentful of my own bad luck to be female, and more angry at how a supposedly liberal society treated female people in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ‘ladette’ feminism of the 90s emphasised personal freedom and equity – individual women having the same choices and opportunities as men, without being judged to a different standard. But that liberal feminism didn’t explain to me the root cause of women’s mistreatment – even in Cool Britannia, there didn’t seem to be a choice I could make that would give me men’s freedoms, so how could more ‘choices’ help the women of Afghanistan, Somalia or Nepal?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was radical (‘of the root’) feminist analysis that finally, to me, made sense of the global systematic oppression of female people. Drawing on Marxist thinking, radical feminism uses class analysis, where a class is a set of people (or things) that meet specific criteria. Importantly, something that is true of the class doesn’t need to be true of all the individual members of that class. For example, the class ‘homo sapiens’, defined as all living humans, has two eyes – it doesn’t tend to have two eyes, or generally have two eyes; it has two eyes. That doesn’t mean that all humans have two eyes, or that anyone with just one eye is not human, or that the purpose or destiny of humans is to have eyes. In all sexually dimorphic species, the female is defined as the kind of organism that produces large gametes (e.g. eggs). So it’s the class of female humans which gestates young and gives birth – that doesn’t mean all female humans give birth, or that anyone who doesn’t give birth isn’t female, or that giving birth is the purpose or destiny of female humans. But it does mean female humans as a class can be, and are, exploited and subordinated in patriarchal systems – regardless of any individual woman’s real or perceived personal characteristics or reproductive status. That’s precisely why there isn’t an opt-out, no matter how much I might have wanted one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Class analysis allows you to see the wood for the trees and examine powerful structures in society without getting distracted by individual variations. It loses some value when the class is porous or can’t be clearly defined – that’s one of the reasons why I’m not a political Marxist or even a socialist (which I’m sure would disappoint my Great Uncle ‘Red’ Eddie, firebrand of the General Strike). My lefty interventionist liberalism reflects my optimism that no-one is fixed forever into a particular socio-economic category. We won’t need to liberate the labouring class if we can effectively abolish it – or at the very least provide means of escape. The same isn’t true of sex class – regardless of our identity, personality or social presentation, it’s not possible in humans to change the material condition of our sex. Glorious human diversity takes place within and across sex classes, and there is powerful intersectionality with other characteristics. But Pateman was right*, in that there’s no point unsexing the political individual when we can’t unsex ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since there can be no escape from our sex, there has to be liberation &lt;em&gt;of&lt;/em&gt; our sex, so that its exploitation doesn’t limit our humanity – structural change to remedy the oppression of women as a sex class. This starts with Marie Shear’s definition of feminism – the radical notion that women are people. That as a sex, we are a whole class of human people in our own right, not a variant or a sub-category (non-men), not a state of mind, and not a shifting collection of whichever individuals happen at a given time to have certain working organs or be manifesting particular bodily functions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this is the context for my own perspective on how we need, collectively, to re-imagine menopause. Yes, of course more awareness of symptoms and greater support for colleagues is wonderful. But we need to take on the challenge of how menopause (among other things) represents the fusion of female biology and female exploitation. Periods, pregnancy and menopause are the foundations for the ancient folk archetypes of the maiden, the mother and the crone. The trivialisation of menopause is intertwined with the invisibility of older women, and the contempt in which they are held in society as a whole. We need to understand and manage menopause as an integral part of female experience, not as another ineffable ordeal that women must fight against and overcome in order to entertain the hopeful fiction that they, too, might be fully human.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*I still disagree with aspects of Pateman’s thesis, but for more nuanced reasons that I don’t have space for here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;•·················•·················•&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover photo with kind permission from the wonderful &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/jessdewahls/&quot;&gt;Jess De Wahls&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;style&gt;
.post-full-content {
    background: #ffffff00 !important;
}
&lt;/style&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>UNSEEN</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="diversity of belief" />
      
        <category term="language" />
      
        <category term="why seen" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">As a 47-year-old woman, it’s not surprising that I’m heartened by the increasing visibility and normalisation of menopause – whether I like it or not, that train is pulling into the station some time soon. But the litany of common problems – the brain fog, the sleeplessness, the pains and sweats – that sounds like a bad cosmic joke, that each new chapter of female life must open with a new swathe of physical inconvenience. Is nature itself a misogynist? No wonder most world religions contend that women are being punished for some original sin.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">What gender critical means to me</title>
      <link href="/posts/2023-12-18-what-gender-critical-means-to-me/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What gender critical means to me" />
      <published>2023-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/what-gender-critical-means-to-me</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2023-12-18-what-gender-critical-means-to-me/">&lt;p&gt;After another week of having to explain again to managers and HR staff what gender critical beliefs are and are not, I thought it would be helpful to put together this primer in case it is of use to others. The term ‘gender critical’ covers a range of views and I don’t speak for everyone, and nor am I a spokesperson for SEEN. But I think the views I explain here are fairly representative of those I have met in SEEN.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;1-sex-and-gendergender-identity-are-different-things&quot;&gt;1. Sex and gender/gender identity are different things&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stonewall define transgender as &lt;em&gt;“An umbrella term to describe people whose gender is not the same as, or does not sit comfortably with, the sex they were assigned at birth”&lt;/em&gt;, so they are not the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;2-everyone-has-a-biological-sex&quot;&gt;2. Everyone has a biological sex&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sex, whether you are male or female, is your biology and is observable and measurable. Everyone has a biological sex that is fixed from the point of conception and recorded at birth. A small proportion of people have one of the rare medical conditions known as Differences of Sexual Development (DSD), but people with DSD’s are still male or female.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone (whether or not they believe in the concept of &lt;em&gt;gender identity&lt;/em&gt;, and whatever their gender identity is, if they have one) can experience sexism, bullying and harassment or discrimination on the basis of their sex. This may be the sexism that a woman faces due to stereotypes about her sex, or the sexism a transwoman (someone registered male at birth who considers themselves to have a female gender identity) faces because they do not follow the sex-based stereotypes associated with their sex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sex is a protected characteristic. Sex is also the basis of the protected characteristics of sexual orientation (opposite-, same- or both-sex attracted) and maternity and pregnancy (which only applies to women).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is vital that we are able to talk about sex when relevant to our employment and that our employers provide us all with the sex-based protections in place in law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;3-some-people-believe-they-have-a-gender-identity&quot;&gt;3. Some people believe they have a gender identity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gender identity is defined by Stonewall as &lt;em&gt;“A person’s innate sense of their own gender, whether male, female or something else, which may or may not correspond to the sex assigned at birth.”&lt;/em&gt; Gender identity cannot be observed or measured.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some people believe in the concept of gender identity, and some people do not. Some people that do hold this belief, consider that their gender identity does not match their sex, and they may describe themselves as transgender or non-binary, cisgender, or something else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gender reassignment is a protected characteristic. Someone with the protected characteristic of gender reassignment may hold a Gender Recognition Certificate (GRC), or they may not. Either way, no one should face bullying, harassment or discrimination because their gender identity does not match their sex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Belief in the concept of gender identity may also be a protected belief under the Equality Act. No one should face bullying, harassment or discrimination due to their belief in the concept of gender identity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, a belief in gender identity should not be assumed or imposed on employees. The civil service has a duty to remain neutral both for its staff and for those we serve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;4-some-people-have-gender-critical-beliefs&quot;&gt;4. Some people have Gender Critical beliefs&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those with gender critical beliefs do not subscribe to the concept of gender identity. They think that gender identity must not be conflated with or used to replace sex in law, policy, guidance or elsewhere. If there is a need to segregate men and women for reasons of privacy, dignity, safety or safeguarding it is sex that should be used (and which is permitted under the Equality Act), not self-identified gender identity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gender critical beliefs are a protected belief under the Equality Act. Noone should face bullying, harassment or discrimination due to their lack of belief in the concept of gender identity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I do not hold a belief in gender identity, this does not mean I do not acknowledge the existence of transgender or non-binary people. My lack of Christian faith does not mean I deny the existence of Christians. Of course Christians exist, but their existence does not prove the existence of a Christian God. Equally, my lack of belief in innate gender identity does not mean I deny the existence of transgender or non-binary colleagues. Everyone should be treated with respect. But someone’s beliefs about their own gender identity do not override the protections written into law on the basis of sex, nor my (lack of) belief.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So to me, gender critical beliefs are simply about expecting my employer to apply the sex-based protections afforded to us all in law, and not imposing a belief system on me that I do not share.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;see also &lt;a href=&quot;/myths/#myth-6-intersex-people-are-proof-that-sex-is-not-binary&quot;&gt;SEEN’s position&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>UNSEEN</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="diversity of belief" />
      
        <category term="language" />
      
        <category term="why seen" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">After another week of having to explain again to managers and HR staff what gender critical beliefs are and are not, I thought it would be helpful to put together this primer in case it is of use to others. The term ‘gender critical’ covers a range of views and I don’t speak for everyone, and nor am I a spokesperson for SEEN. But I think the views I explain here are fairly representative of those I have met in SEEN.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Why SEEN is important to me (viii)</title>
      <link href="/posts/2023-09-17-why-is-seen-important-to-me-viii/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why SEEN is important to me (viii)" />
      <published>2023-09-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-09-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/why-is-seen-important-to-me-viii</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2023-09-17-why-is-seen-important-to-me-viii/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;To Celebrate Bisexuality Week, we wanted to share this post from a civil servant. This post shares an individual’s personal experience, which includes frank references to his negative experiences in another civil service network.  Many staff networks will have members and interests in common, but we also serve differing needs and as this post makes clear, these are sometimes incompatible.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;We hope that sharing these experiences will allow a better understanding of this, and this in turn will help act as a first step to allow us to work together to reach a place where all staff networks can complement and support one another.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Our network, as ever, welcomes collaborative dialogue between networks and across government departments.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;︵‿︵‿︵‿︵‿︵&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted to share some thoughts on why, as a bisexual man, SEEN is important to me, and why I haven’t found a home in the existing LGBT+ networks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The popular cliché is that a bisexual is some young, frivolous person with blue, green or purple hair and probably various facial and other piercings and a devil-may-care attitude to societal norms and who believes that gender is fluid.  But it also includes people like me, a 50 something ex-policeman, in the Civil Service, divorced with kids and who is attracted to both sexes: appreciating the masculinity in men and the femininity in women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Early on I accepted that my bisexuality was purely one manifestation of the continuum of human sexuality and I was relatively content in that knowledge. In spite of my own acceptance, I have always wanted to protect those around me from the knowledge or, where I had told them, at least the stigma of being the parent, sibling, wife, child or friend of someone who is bisexual. I believed this was the least I could do to show my gratitude and love.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In recent years, I had become very isolated and alone, in part because I had moved around quite a lot geographically, but also because I lacked contact with people with whom I could be myself, and who shared some of my life experiences. I knew intuitively that there were others in a similar predicament, but I didn’t know where I could find them. I had read that bisexuals are at risk of poor mental health and I did feel that I was suffering, so I looked first to the LGBT network for support, and in particular the Bi+ Inclusion Group. It wasn’t something that came easy to me and I was sceptical about whether I would fit in. However, I had hoped to find a friendly welcoming group where I could discuss my feelings and find other bisexual people with similar life experiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The people on the calls were friendly enough and we all conducted ourselves respectfully, but unfortunately it was apparent that the “+” was more important than the “bi” in the title of the group, even though often the “+” was omitted, as if it were a given that we all accept that there are many genders rather than two sexes. Stonewall came up in conversation once and I questioned why there seemed to be such an obsession with the view of one organisation, when there were other organisations such as the LGB Alliance with differing views. I was told that the LGB Alliance was a fascist and anti-trans organisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sadly, after several months of attending I was approached privately and it was made clear that having gender critical views was not welcome. It felt like the ultimate bi erasure as a bi man not being welcome in a Bi(+) group. However, looking back at my experience of the group I recognised that I had never found what I wanted there; a place to relax and speak openly. It seemed that rather than being allowed to speak about our own feelings and experiences, we were required to submit to a political ideology whether or not we agreed with it. There were also very few men who regularly dialled into the calls, so again it was difficult to find people with a similar life experience to my own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having gone back into my shell somewhat, it was a revelation to later happen across SEEN where different perspectives are tolerated, diverse voices welcome and same sex attraction is recognised as a unique category of experience.  I hope others will also find a welcome here too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover image&lt;/strong&gt;:  “Bisexuality symbol (bold, color)” by Kwamikagami is licensed under CC BY-SA 4.0. To view a copy of this license, visit https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/?ref=openverse.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>UNSEEN</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sexual orientation" />
      
        <category term="lesbian gay and bisexual" />
      
        <category term="why seen" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">To Celebrate Bisexuality Week, we wanted to share this post from a civil servant. This post shares an individual’s personal experience, which includes frank references to his negative experiences in another civil service network. Many staff networks will have members and interests in common, but we also serve differing needs and as this post makes clear, these are sometimes incompatible.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Why SEEN is important to me (vii)</title>
      <link href="/posts/2023-07-19-why-is-seen-important-to-me-vii/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why SEEN is important to me (vii)" />
      <published>2023-07-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-07-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/why-is-seen-important-to-me-vii</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2023-07-19-why-is-seen-important-to-me-vii/">&lt;p&gt;Bring your whole self to work is what my employer tells me. Unless of course you happen to believe like I do that sex is binary and fixed from conception. In that case I am allowed to hold that belief (thank you &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.judiciary.uk/judgments/forstater-v-cgd-europe-and-ors/&quot;&gt;Maya&lt;/a&gt;), but not to express it plainly in case it causes offense to those who believe that the concept of innate gender identity is more important in all cases than biological sex, or somehow denies their identity.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;But what about my identity?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When my employer asks for my gender but not my sex, or asks for my gender without giving me the option to say that I do not believe in an innate gender, this denies my identity. My sex is important to me. My sex has shaped my life. During my career I have experienced sexism, disadvantage and discrimination due to my sex and I have had to fight against the stereotypes imposed upon me due to my sex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When my employer asks me to state whether I identify as a woman, this denies my identity. To use woman in this way is to change it from a definition based on sex, to one based on gender identity. I am not a woman because I have womanly thoughts and feelings which are separate and distinct from manly thoughts and feelings - and if you think I am you need to reconsider as this is the very definition of sexism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When my employer allows me to be referred to as cis-gendered, this denies my identity. I am not a woman because my personality happens to align with the stereotypical expectations that society places on me due to my sex, any more than I would not be a woman if my personality did not. And my personality, like that of everyone else I have ever met, is a mix of those traits that society ascribes to be feminine and masculine because stereotypes are nonsense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am a woman because my sex is female. But knowing my sex tells you nothing about me except what my sex is. It does not tell you about my personality, my likes and dislikes, my strengths and weaknesses. There is no trait, characteristic, thought or feeling that I share with all other women on this planet and which is distinct from those shared by men, other than our biology. So I say again, I am a woman because my sex is female.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are all afforded protections in law to prevent us from suffering from discrimination and harassment or to preserve our privacy and dignity because of our sex. But as it stands my employer has no record of my sex and has replaced sex with gender and that is why SEEN is so important to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover image&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/photos/DRzYMtae-vA&quot;&gt;Nadine Shaabana&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/license&quot;&gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>UNSEEN</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="personal experience" />
      
        <category term="language" />
      
        <category term="gender stereotyping" />
      
        <category term="why seen" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Bring your whole self to work is what my employer tells me. Unless of course you happen to believe like I do that sex is binary and fixed from conception. In that case I am allowed to hold that belief (thank you Maya), but not to express it plainly in case it causes offense to those who believe that the concept of innate gender identity is more important in all cases than biological sex, or somehow denies their identity.But what about my identity?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Why SEEN is important to me (vi)</title>
      <link href="/posts/2023-04-24-why-is-seen-important-to-me-vi/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why SEEN is important to me (vi)" />
      <published>2023-04-24T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-04-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/why-is-seen-important-to-me-vi</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2023-04-24-why-is-seen-important-to-me-vi/">&lt;p&gt;In this time of strikes by the public service professions dominated by women, I’ve been reflecting on the often-overlooked history of women in the UK trade union movement and parallels to today, where many women still struggle to have their needs met for appropriate pay and suitable health and safety conditions, including to protect them during pregnancy and maternity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new film &lt;em&gt;Enola Holmes 2&lt;/em&gt; features (spoiler alert) the story of young women and girls working in a match factory, and striking for better pay and conditions. Whilst romanticised elements were added, the story is grounded in fact. 1888 was the start of action by an unlikely group of heroic young women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Girls and women in the Bryant and May match factory in Bow, now a block of luxury flats, were treated appallingly. They worked 12-hour shifts, standing up, dipping wooden matches into a mixture of chemicals which included the highly dangerous white phosphorus, and packing them into boxes. The chemical caused toothaches which worsened into abscesses and necrosis of the jaw – a condition known as “phossy jaw”. As depicted in &lt;em&gt;Enola Holmes 2&lt;/em&gt;, the managers often dismissed the girls and women affected. The pay for this work was very meagre, and halved for girls under the age of 18, even though they were doing the same work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/3/32/Matchgirl_strikers.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of matchgirls participating in a strike against Bryant &amp;amp; May, London 1888&quot; title=&quot;Photo of matchgirls participating in a strike against Bryant &amp;amp; May, London 1888&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The socialist activist and author Annie Besant took up the cause. She interviewed a number of workers, and wrote a shocking and damning article for her own magazine, &lt;em&gt;The Link&lt;/em&gt;, which she entitled &lt;em&gt;“White Slavery in London”&lt;/em&gt;. In it, she described the factory as being like a “prison-house” and the match girls as “undersized, helpless and oppressed”, with one child living on “only bread-and-butter and tea, alike for breakfast and dinner”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Annie Besant’s article enraged the factory owners, who threatened to sue her, and put pressure on their employees to deny the truth of it. The employees wrote to Annie:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Dear lady, they are trying to get the poor girls to say that it is all lies that has been printed and sign papers to say it is lies. Dear lady, we will not sign them.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When one of the women was sacked on suspicion of being the author, on 5th July 1888, all 1,400 women and girls went on strike: “One girl began, and the rest said ‘yes’ so out we all went.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Annie Besant supported the matchmakers to set up a union, led by eight of the matchmakers, including Sarah Chapman, who features in &lt;em&gt;Enola Holmes 2&lt;/em&gt;. They were supported by Annie’s colleagues in the Fabian Society, by Toynbee Hall (an enterprise for social change in the East End, which supported the strike fund) and by newspapers including the widely read &lt;em&gt;Pall Mall Gazette&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;The Times&lt;/em&gt;. Annie took a group of 56 strikers to Parliament, and MPs raised questions about their treatment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within a fortnight of the strike starting, the Bryant and May directors, horrified by the negative publicity, caved completely and met all of the strikers’ demands. Sarah Chapman became the first Matchmakers’ Union delegate, and first woman, to attend the Trades Union Congress, where a resolution was passed stating that men and women should be paid at the same rate for equal work. The match girls’ strike inspired the men of the East End to undertake the dockers’ strike a few weeks later, which closed the Thames for a month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;125 years after the match girls’ strike, I named my own daughter Annie, after Annie Besant – and at 10 she shows every sign of being a similarly fierce feminist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it wasn’t until over a century later,that the Equal Pay Act 1970 was passed, led by Barbara Castle, and it was 1976 before the Act came into force. This followed a 1970 strike by women workers at the Ford factory in Dagenham (also depicted in a film, &lt;em&gt;Made in Dagenham&lt;/em&gt;) because they were paid 15% less than men for the same work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even now, UK legislation only covers disparities between men and women working for the same employer. Government statistics for the UK for 2022 indicate that there remains a median pay gap between men and women of 9.71%. This is attributed to women being more likely to work part-time due to caring responsibilities, with part-time working commanding less pay bargaining power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are also lower rates of pay for professions in which women are or become the majority, a phenomenon known as “workforce feminisation”, whereby female dominated occupations or workplaces are paid less than those which are male-dominated, even if they were previously male-dominated. As the European Commission states: &lt;em&gt;“Highly feminised jobs tend to be systematically undervalued.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pay disparity for women increases with pregnancy, childbirth and care of infants, and again as women reach their 40s, with many reducing their hours to care both for their children and elderly relatives, while often suffering from stress and fatigue. The pay gap is also significantly larger for women from some ethnic groups and for women with disabilities and health challenges, who are likely to suffer particularly from further social and economic barriers to obtaining well-paid work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The workforce “feminisation problem” may also be an issue in some parts of the civil service, and we know there remain other barriers to women thriving in the civil service. This is why it’s so important that SEEN highlights discrimination that is connected to sex and reminds employers to collect and keep sex-disaggregated data. When it comes to equal pay and to health and safety at work, sex really matters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;sources-and-further-reading&quot;&gt;Sources and further reading:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.matchgirls1888.org/the-story-of-the-strike&quot;&gt;https://www.matchgirls1888.org/the-story-of-the-strike&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matchgirls%27_strike&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matchgirls%27_strike&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/dit-gender-pay-gap-report-and-data-2021-to-2022/dit-gender-pay-gap-report-2021-to-2022#:~:text=or%20a%20woman.-,The%20gender%20pay%20gap,to%20%C2%A32.68%20in%202021&quot;&gt;https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/dit-gender-pay-gap-report-and-data-2021-to-2022/dit-gender-pay-gap-report-2021-to-2022#:~:text=or%20a%20woman.-,The%20gender%20pay%20gap,to%20%C2%A32.68%20in%202021&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://commission.europa.eu/strategy-and-policy/policies/justice-and-fundamental-rights/gender-equality/equal-pay/gender-pay-gap-situation-eu_en&quot;&gt;https://commission.europa.eu/strategy-and-policy/policies/justice-and-fundamental-rights/gender-equality/equal-pay/gender-pay-gap-situation-eu_en&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2016/03/20/upshot/as-women-take-over-a-male-dominated-field-the-pay-drops.html&quot;&gt;https://www.nytimes.com/2016/03/20/upshot/as-women-take-over-a-male-dominated-field-the-pay-drops.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://human-resources-health.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12960-019-0406-0&quot;&gt;https://human-resources-health.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12960-019-0406-0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover image:&lt;/strong&gt; “Matchgirl strikers”, Unknown author. Wikimedia Commons https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Matchgirl_strikers.PNG&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Liz</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="biography" />
      
        <category term="sex based rights" />
      
        <category term="equality" />
      
        <category term="why seen" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In this time of strikes by the public service professions dominated by women, I’ve been reflecting on the often-overlooked history of women in the UK trade union movement and parallels to today, where many women still struggle to have their needs met for appropriate pay and suitable health and safety conditions, including to protect them during pregnancy and maternity.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Why SEEN is important to me (v)</title>
      <link href="/posts/2023-03-27-why-is-seen-important-to-me-v/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why SEEN is important to me (v)" />
      <published>2023-03-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-03-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/why-is-seen-important-to-me-v</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2023-03-27-why-is-seen-important-to-me-v/">&lt;p&gt;This wasn’t something I ever saw myself doing, after I came out as a lesbian to my family that loved and accepted me, to walking with Stonewall at London’s Pride Parade. I didn’t know that a new ideology was emerging from internet discussions into general life and into politics. I didn’t see myself as a very political person until I realised what you can lose if you don’t pay attention to the discussions around you. This is why I’m no longer afraid to speak, because I’m now aware of what there is to lose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My life as a lesbian is determined by my sex and the sex of the person I fall in love with. This same-sex attraction is what gays and lesbians have fought to protect in this country, and in countries where my grandparents were born – is still illegal and could get me killed. My elderly, Jamaican grandparents who live in the UK have amazingly accepted me with love—even more challenging for them than me telling them that I was an atheist!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I feel now, in communities expressly for people like me, is a poison of distrust and hate for reasons that are far from reasonable. Apparently now it’s true that my earlier definition of homosexuality is now a statement of hate and a ‘dogwhistle’. It seems like without any balanced discussion, we have now accepted the ideology of gender identity, something I see as similar to adopting the Christian faith of my grandparents without question, because they would feel distress if I didn’t?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gender identity in the workplace forces me to lie, and I like to think that I’m an honest and open person.  Gender identity makes me worry for the boundaries of private spaces such as toilets. Sometimes I go into work sweaty and need to change clothes, and rather than use the small cubicles I quickly switch tops near the sinks. Gender identity puts an extra stress on a lone female, unsure if the toilets will truly be single-sex, and if a male person states his right to use our spaces, we will further worry about what may happen if we show anything but blind faith in the male’s personal belief that he is the same as us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am respectful with my own beliefs, but I do not use religious epithets when talking to a Sunni Muslim colleague, nor pray with my Christian colleague over her lunch. When I tell them I am an atheist I’m not called slurs, but when women say we do not believe in gender ideology we are called “terfs”, bigots and casual violence is promised by either a punch or murder by those of particular strong faith (protest signs in Scotland come to mind). This toxic environment makes one wary of speaking out, which is why I really do think you will not hear many voices like mine, because they are silenced out of fear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really do love my job, I can see the many great ways my career can progress as I learn more. In the end we are trying to be apolitical in our approach to our work with shared goals.  Why would we jeopardise that by forcing people to lie and pretend that biological sex doesn’t matter?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finding SEEN was like a breath of fresh air. It was exactly what was needed; clear information and a perspective to balance out the poisonous atmosphere. They put sex above gender identity and highlight the reality of living in a sexed world by sharing information on female safety and sexist stereotypes or behaviours. I’m also pleased to see them shine a light on forgotten LGB history this February, especially when important figures are set aside or written over to declare their faith to gender ideology. Here I think of a gay man, Malcolm Michaels Jr, known famously as Marsha P Johnson who was an outspoken gay rights activist.  According to Stonewall veteran Fred Sergeant, he was proud of being a non-confirming gay man, and although he had a drag queen act, did not identify as a trans woman, a label that has only been attributed to him by others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SEEN knows this, and as we learn how to engage with each other’s networks respectfully I feel so much more hopeful about the future of the workplace environment. I hope more voices are heard within the Civil Service, and due to the clear divide of politics within LGBT spaces, it is crucial that talks continue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover image:&lt;/strong&gt; “Woman Silhouette” by pixabay is marked with CC0 1.0. To view the terms, visit https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/?ref=openverse.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Mahalia</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="personal experience" />
      
        <category term="lesbian gay and bisexual" />
      
        <category term="diversity of belief" />
      
        <category term="why seen" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">This wasn’t something I ever saw myself doing, after I came out as a lesbian to my family that loved and accepted me, to walking with Stonewall at London’s Pride Parade. I didn’t know that a new ideology was emerging from internet discussions into general life and into politics. I didn’t see myself as a very political person until I realised what you can lose if you don’t pay attention to the discussions around you. This is why I’m no longer afraid to speak, because I’m now aware of what there is to lose.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Why SEEN is important to me (iv)</title>
      <link href="/posts/2023-02-27-why-is-seen-important-to-me-iv/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why SEEN is important to me (iv)" />
      <published>2023-02-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-02-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/why-is-seen-important-to-me-iv</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2023-02-27-why-is-seen-important-to-me-iv/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[This post is the last of &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/launch-speeches/&quot;&gt;four speeches by SEEN members&lt;/a&gt; from our launch event in October. The author wishes to remain anonymous.]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most people have a favourite Harry Potter character.  For some it’s Hermione, others perhaps Dumbledore.  I’ve always been a Luna Lovegood fan.  I liked the fact she floats slightly off synch and doesn’t care for others’ approval.  I liked the fact that she speaks the truth.  I like the fact that she doesn’t mind that she doesn’t fit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used to mind that I didn’t fit.  In fact, there used to be a lot of things that I minded; a lot of things I wanted to change, thinking that if these changed everything else would fit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was at school that I first used to think about cutting off my breasts: one after the other, until my chest was flat again, back to the pre-fall perfection of childhood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was at school that I discovered that the horror of menstruation could be curtailed if I restricted my food intake enough to trick my body into thinking I was starting to starve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end I kept the cutting to my wrists, and my thoughts to myself.  But they were there, these secret desires to strip myself of this unwanted unfolding into a womanhood I never wanted, but which still came: uninvited with its horrors.  I thought without this everything would be better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so, these changes were a matter of intense misery.  So much so that by the time I left school it was a long time since I’d considered myself capable of happiness.  I accepted this was my lot.  I was just unlucky that my body and brain didn’t fit.  Most unluckily of all, I had to navigate this in silence and in solitude.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did not realise then what I know now: how lucky I was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t appreciate how lucky I was not to be promised  the one thing that I really wanted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t understand how lucky I was that no one told me that there was a way out.  For no one told me there might be a way to return first to childhood; or at very least to stop the fall and from there have time to think and (if I wanted) to start again.  No one told me I could then become one of the real people: one of the men.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No one answered my prayers, gave me a reason to stop hurting myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I was lucky because no one let me think that because I didn’t wear little dresses to go out and disco, but preferred standing with the other DJ boys at the drum and bass night in hoodies and combats, meant anything more than the fact that I really appreciated my breakbeats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I knew I didn’t fit in, that I was awkward and perpetually out of tune.  But I was lucky because no one pointed a way to how I could be made to fit: confirmed and curtailed me through drugs and surgery that promised to make me feel ‘right’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a horrible time at school.  It was miserable.  I hated my adolescence and puberty so much I still don’t talk about them.  But I know now I was lucky because never once was I told anything but the truth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center; font-size: 1.5em;&quot;&gt;*&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am older.  Many things have changed.  I’ve found my own way to navigate the complex dance between being female and expectations of femininity.  I have forgiven my body and found gratitude in what it can do.  I better understand my mind and can present as normal for almost two hours at a time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also have a nephew and I recognise something in him that I once knew in myself. He’s lovely, he’s a rare jewel of a human being, not quite of this earth, half angel.  But he’s autistic odd, like me.  He does a lovely turn to Lady Gaga, makes machines and sits inside them looking into the silver-plated looking glass that belonged to an old aunt.  For a while he begged to have his limbs replaced with metal ones so he could become a cyborg.  Recently he’s started sometimes telling me he wants to become a girl, apparently he wants to go to Rainbows with his sister.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These days people prick up their ears at such a combination.  And there are many ways his parents could frame this behaviour.  But if they were to follow the educational resources recommended at his school, they’d quickly interpret these signs to mean that he was trapped in the wrong body and we should affirm his identity as an imperative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily they, like me, are not so sure that there are wrong bodies, any more than there is wrong skin colour or wrong brains.  There are people and they are diverse, and this diversity is complex and glorious.  But being different doesn’t mean wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am glad they don’t share these teaching resources with him.  I am glad no one has told him that his personality means that his body needs changing to fit. I am glad no one has told him he cannot ‘be himself’ without lifelong medication and permanent surgical damage to his body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some boys are sensitive and want to hang out with girls and wear dresses.  That doesn’t mean they need ‘fixing’.   They need to be made welcome and feel celebrated as they are.  I am glad he is being made to feel welcome as who he is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center; font-size: 1.5em;&quot;&gt;*&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like many of you, I’ve been through the wars and having been through the wars I want to protect.  I am determined to protect those I love; those I don’t know but who I recognise as like me; and those who are not like me but I recognise are vulnerable.  I want to protect others so that they have the opportunity to grow up to be the rare, non-conforming, unconventional humans they deserve to become.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not here out of hate, or out of anger, or out of fear.  I’m here because the truth matters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No one should lie, even if those lies are designed to be kind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No one – especially children – should ever be encouraged to believe the lie that they can change sex, and that damaging their bodies will take away their unhappiness.  Lies are complex structures that require constant complex shoring up.  And however hard we try, everyone eventually comes to understand that they have been lied to, and that is a terrible thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of all the kindness that I have received in life, gentleness and honesty are among those I most cherish.  And we owe the most vulnerable the respect of honesty, of speaking the truth.  Everyone deserves that gift.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover image:&lt;/strong&gt;  “Thinking woman” by pacogaitero is licensed under CC BY-NC-SA 2.0. To view a copy of this license, visit https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/2.0/?ref=openverse.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>UNSEEN</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="personal experience" />
      
        <category term="neurodiverse" />
      
        <category term="coming of age" />
      
        <category term="launch speeches" />
      
        <category term="why seen" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">[This post is the last of four speeches by SEEN members from our launch event in October. The author wishes to remain anonymous.]</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Why SEEN is important to me (iii)</title>
      <link href="/posts/2023-01-25-why-is-seen-important-to-me-iii/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why SEEN is important to me (iii)" />
      <published>2023-01-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-01-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/why-is-seen-important-to-me-iii</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2023-01-25-why-is-seen-important-to-me-iii/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[This post is the third of &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/launch-speeches/&quot;&gt;four speeches by SEEN members&lt;/a&gt; from our launch event in October.]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-loss-of-the-word-woman&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Loss of the Word Woman&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to speak about language – primarily the loss of the word ‘woman’ to describe an adult human female  - and its emotional impact on me. Language matters and the loss of our words hurt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve seen a quiet dismantling over the past few years across our public institutions (including the Civil Service) of sex-based language. By ‘quiet’ I mean that it’s happened without any consultation with the group it primarily impacts – women. It starts by replacing the word ‘sex’ (the material fact of being male or female) with the word ‘gender’ (the social roles and stereotypes associated with either sex) and ends with the word ‘woman’ being routinely separated from our female bodies or reproductive functions, and suddenly we find ourselves referred to as cervix-havers, menstruators, birthing parents, lactators, bodies with vaginas, pregnant people or ‘people experiencing the menopause’. These examples aren’t one-offs - they are now seen regularly in NHS information campaigns, women’s health charities, corporate advertising, Civil Service policies, networks and newsletters, and mainstream media news reports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The phenomenon isn’t restricted to the UK. Women’s Declaration International&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, which reaffirms women and girls’ sex-based rights as set out in CEDAW (Convention on the Elimination of Discrimination against Women) recognises that in relation to protecting women’s sex based rights including reproductive rights, protection from male violence against women, participation in sports and the need for single-sex spaces, we are unable to safeguard women’s rights effectively while at the same time, twisting our language to include men.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The words ‘gender neutral’ and ‘inclusive’ might sound positive and well-intentioned and may be intended as a way to avoid hurting anyone’s feelings, but in considering the feelings of one group  - those who find sexed language problematic - we give real pain to another group.  When women say that erasing the words we use to describe ourselves and our reality is painful, (and we do say this) why are we not listened to?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me tell you about my feelings.  When I see or hear any of these female body-part or reproductive function terms such as ‘pregnant people’ instead of ‘pregnant women’, or ‘anyone with a cervix aged 25-64 ’ instead of ‘women aged 25-64’ I experience distress and rage, my heart rate speeds up, my chest tightens, and I feel nauseous. I consciously calm myself before I decide whether to ignore it or to challenge with a &lt;em&gt;‘We are women. Call us women.’&lt;/em&gt; There’s a real emotional cost either way – ignore it and I lose self-respect and feel I lack courage; challenge it and I know I will either be ignored, or receive a dismissive &lt;em&gt;‘this organisation uses inclusive language’&lt;/em&gt; response, which implies it’s my reaction that’s out of kilter, or that my concern is not valid or that my views are fringe. Challenging in a public space can sometimes mean being called unkind, hateful, out-of-touch, or even fascist. Such accusations might be made out of a misguided desire to be kind and accommodating to others but they are often intended to ostracise, alienate and instil fear.  They prevent reasonable discourse and aim instead to silence, to shame and to control. And it works – I know many women who say nothing out of fear. And all this just for believing that adult females should be called women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So where does my anger at this language, which has surprised me by its strength, come from and why does it matter?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was brought up to be a feminist  by a single mother. She would say the personal is political. My emotion doesn’t come out of nowhere. I was a child in the 60s and 70s and learned from a young age that women have had to fight to achieve social and political equality with men, that our biological reproductive role, and vulnerability to male violence, mean that we sometimes require additional legal protections and safe spaces to achieve equality and that one of the reasons girls and women have struggled to achieve parity with men is that men control language. ‘Man’ in the Bible includes ‘Woman’ or does it? The ‘Rights of Man’ – to vote, to speak, to own property, to organise politically &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; include women but it often did not. Whether we were included or excluded was sometimes hard to discern and out of our control. Women were invisible, subsumed by the male default, and separately defined only in relation to men. Our names belonged to our fathers, then our husbands and our history became harder to trace. We began to understand this and for a few short decades that coincide with my life, we started to reclaim female language, history and experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, in a sudden reversal of progress, that I and many others did not foresee, the word ‘woman’ is routinely used to mean – not an adult human who is female, as understood by humanity for thousands of years and as defined in the Equality Act 2010 - but to mean anyone of either sex who says they’re a woman. So women as a separately defined sex class are, if not invisible, then blurred and ill-defined. This hurts because the words woman along with girl, mother, daughter and sister are precious. I remember the charity SANDS - which supports anyone affected by the death of a baby - putting out a communication on social media which did not use the word ‘mother’ once, instead saying ‘parent’ or ‘birthing parent’. This was done in the name of ‘inclusion’. The number of responses from bereaved women anguished at not being called ‘mothers’ was heart-breaking and led SANDS to back down and apologise to those women. Such ability to listen to the strength of this emotion and reflect seems sadly to be rare. Women now have to lobby and complain to each individual organisation, employer and charity just to persuade them to use the word ‘women’ and even then it usually falls on deaf ears which teaches us a lesson. It teaches us that the opinions and feelings of women matter very little to institutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our mothers and grandmothers achieved so much, and social and political parity appeared to be within sight by the 1980s. And now this. We are at risk of losing the language which describes our sex as based in material reality. If that happens, we will have no collective means to describe our female experience or to combat inequality. I despair when I hear the fight to retain abortion rights in the US framed as the ‘rights of people capable of becoming pregnant’. Imagine if the suffragettes had been hamstrung by language that was so inclusive that instead of “Votes For Women!” they’d felt obliged to say ‘Votes for people with a cervix!’  A battle cannot be won without clear and ringing language - ‘A Vindication of The Rights of Woman’!&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; We find ourselves now having to fight just to protect and define the word ‘woman’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are tempted to think that language has changed simply to reflect a more inclusive and equal society, ask yourself why you rarely, if ever, see men referred to either by the NHS or the Civil Service as ‘prostate owners’ or ‘sperm providers.’ They are just called men! Why? In one recent newsletter in my own civil service department  I saw that one staff event referred to &lt;em&gt;‘people going through the menopause’&lt;/em&gt;, and another event on the same page referred to &lt;em&gt;‘men’s mental health.’&lt;/em&gt; Particularly ironic when mental health issues are experienced by both men and women and the menopause exclusively by women. We are experiencing a new and insidious form of sexism and exclusion that comes disguised as inclusion and kindness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I see invisibility shrouding women one short generation after the battle for sex equality seemed to be all over bar the shouting. I say sex equality, never gender equality. I, like millions of women, have experienced girlhood, female puberty, womanhood, pregnancy, childbirth, motherhood, breastfeeding and menopause. These are all experiences exclusive to the female sex. I attended the traumatic and frightening birth of one grandson. My daughter and I knew what being a woman meant during that night and day. It is real. It is not an identity, a feeling or a costume.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Calling women birthing parents, menstruators and ‘people going through the menopause’, is not only dehumanising and insulting but it has the catastrophic psychological effect of dividing women from each other. What does a menstruator have in common with a ‘person experiencing the menopause’ or with a 70-year-old cervix-haver or with a birthing parent? Unless we can say without any qualification that ‘of course they are all women’, the effect is that they have nothing in common other than their humanity which we share with boys and men, and we have broken the cherished link that all girls and women, young and old, mothers or childless, and with or without various reproductive experiences, have in common with each other as we pass from childhood to old age and which we do not share with any boy or man.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want SEEN to be a place in the Civil Service where women can say all of this without fear of censure and to remind every HR department and policy maker to think carefully about whether reducing women and girls to a multiplicity of body parts and functions is kind or inclusive at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover image:&lt;/strong&gt;  “Thinking woman” by pacogaitero is licensed under CC BY-NC-SA 2.0. To view a copy of this license, visit https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/2.0/?ref=openverse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.womensdeclaration.com/&quot;&gt;https://www.womensdeclaration.com/&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.womensdeclaration.com/en/about/use-language/&quot;&gt;https://www.womensdeclaration.com/en/about/use-language/&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Wollstonecraft, Mary, 1759-1797. A Vindication of the Rights of Woman: with Strictures on Political and Moral Subjects. London :Printed for J. Johnson, 1792. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Louise</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="personal experience" />
      
        <category term="language" />
      
        <category term="launch speeches" />
      
        <category term="why seen" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">[This post is the third of four speeches by SEEN members from our launch event in October.]</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
