<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title> - Articles</title>
    <description>Sex Equality and Equity Network</description>
    <link>
    https://seen-network.uk</link>
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Elimination of violence against women and girls</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;Our duty and our honour: what can we as public servants do to stop violence against women and girls?&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Wed, 27 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        https://seen-network.uk/posts/2024-11-27-idevaw-2024/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://seen-network.uk/posts/2024-11-27-idevaw-2024/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>SEEN in Northern Ireland</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A member of SEEN based in Northern Ireland provides some reflections on the setting up of a SEEN in Northern Ireland group, and meeting other members of SEEN based in Northern Ireland for the first time.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        https://seen-network.uk/posts/2024-11-18-seen-in-northern-ireland/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://seen-network.uk/posts/2024-11-18-seen-in-northern-ireland/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>SEEN in Scotland</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;A member of SEEN based in Scotland provides some reflections on the setting up of a SEEN in Scotland Group, and meeting other members of SEEN based in Scotland for the first time.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Thu, 07 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        https://seen-network.uk/posts/2024-11-07-seen-in-scotland/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://seen-network.uk/posts/2024-11-07-seen-in-scotland/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Women in the Olympic Games: From Paris 1900 to Paris 2024</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;The Olympic Games have long been a symbol of human excellence, unity, and the relentless pursuit of athletic achievement. However, the journey to equality between men and women within this prestigious event has been a winding path, filled with significant milestones and pioneering figures.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        https://seen-network.uk/posts/2024-07-26-olympics/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://seen-network.uk/posts/2024-07-26-olympics/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>James Barry: female pioneer</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;“So tell me”, my first history professor liked to start, after hearing my latest essay, “what have you left out, and how have you filled the gaps?”&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Sun, 03 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        https://seen-network.uk/posts/2024-03-03-james-barry-female-pioneer/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://seen-network.uk/posts/2024-03-03-james-barry-female-pioneer/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Menopause: A radical perspective</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;As a 47-year-old woman, it’s not surprising that I’m heartened by the increasing visibility and normalisation of menopause – whether I like it or not, that train is pulling into the station some time soon. But the litany of common problems – the brain fog, the sleeplessness, the pains and sweats – that sounds like a bad cosmic joke, that each new chapter of female life must open with a new swathe of physical inconvenience. Is nature itself a misogynist? No wonder most world religions contend that women are being punished for some original sin.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        https://seen-network.uk/posts/2024-01-17-menopause-a-radical-perspective/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://seen-network.uk/posts/2024-01-17-menopause-a-radical-perspective/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>What gender critical means to me</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;After another week of having to explain again to managers and HR staff what gender critical beliefs are and are not, I thought it would be helpful to put together this primer in case it is of use to others. The term ‘gender critical’ covers a range of views and I don’t speak for everyone, and nor am I a spokesperson for SEEN. But I think the views I explain here are fairly representative of those I have met in SEEN.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Mon, 18 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-12-18-what-gender-critical-means-to-me/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-12-18-what-gender-critical-means-to-me/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Violence against women and girls - language matters</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;Language matters when we talk about violence against women and girls. In the last 15 years we have seen the word woman not being used, replaced with the word people or non-man, or replaced with dehumanising body-part terms such as cervix havers, chestfeeders, pregnant people or menstruators.  Attempting to eradicate biological sex by not naming women as women doesn’t make all the nasty, horrible things disappear and it does not give equality to women. The violence and rapes still happen it just means it is harder to measure something that is not defined. When it comes to violence against women and girls if we cannot name those who are being violated it makes it very difficult to defend them.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Tue, 28 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-11-28-idevaw-language-matters/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-11-28-idevaw-language-matters/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Violence against women - A personal account</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;I am not a victim, but I have been hurt by men. I won’t recount every time as the pain and fear crouches within me ready to pounce at any given opportunity. I am a woman who has served at the altar of men, perpetuating the entitlement that men can do as they please, whenever they please but no more, I am saying no.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Mon, 27 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-11-27-idevaw-a-personal-account/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-11-27-idevaw-a-personal-account/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Violence against women. The judicial system is trying – is it succeeding?</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;I have been a magistrate for over thirty years and prior to that was a special constable.  During those decades views on domestic violence, specifically violence against women have changed considerably – but there is still a long way to go.  In the past, the model was largely the ‘Andy Capp’ cartoon featured in the Daily Mirror from 1957.  Women were subservient, best placed in the home with a single role to provide for all mens’ needs.  The cartoon strip thrived on Florence Capp being unprepared for tea on the table at 5pm sharp and Andy’s violent response to it.  The view of police and the wider judiciary was - then and until recently - largely that if he hit her, she obviously deserved it.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Sun, 26 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-11-26-idevaw-is-the-judicial-system-succeeding/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-11-26-idevaw-is-the-judicial-system-succeeding/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Violence Against Women &amp; Girls – 16 days of activism</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;November 25 is the UN’s &lt;em&gt;International Day for the Elimination of Violence Against Women&lt;/em&gt; (IDEVAW).Between then and &lt;em&gt;International Human Rights Day&lt;/em&gt; on 10 December, the UN is calling for &lt;em&gt;16 days of activism&lt;/em&gt; &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; to raise awareness and seek solutions to this oldest and most pervasive of problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.unwomen.org/en/what-we-do/ending-violence-against-women/unite/16-days-of-activism&quot;&gt;UN Women: 16 days of activism&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        
        <pubDate>Sat, 25 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-11-25-idevaw-16-days-of-activism/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-11-25-idevaw-16-days-of-activism/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Ending violence against women and girls</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;For this year’s &lt;em&gt;International Day for the Elimination of Violence against Women&lt;/em&gt; SEEN is publishing articles today and over the next few days by four of our general members (outside our network leadership team), three of whom must remain anonymous.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Sat, 25 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-11-25-ending-violence-against-women/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-11-25-ending-violence-against-women/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Impartiality and Finding Common Ground</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;On 14th November, SEEN was invited to participate in the “Navigating Difference Finding Common Ground” webinar, and interfaith and belief event, which formed part of Faith and Belief Week 2023.  This was our presentation, given by a SEEN co-chair, as a part of the panel.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Tue, 21 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-11-21-impartiality-and-finding-common-ground/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-11-21-impartiality-and-finding-common-ground/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Men, we need to talk</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;WARNING:  This blog contains references to suicide and suicidal ideation.  There is support available and you are not alone.  Please see the links at the end of this blog.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Sun, 19 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-11-19-men-we-need-to-talk/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-11-19-men-we-need-to-talk/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Let’s Talk About Pronouns..</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;On the afternoon of Monday, 9th October we approached everyone on our mailing list to ask them what they thought about practices related to the statement of pronouns in email signatures and elsewhere.  One thing was immediately clear: this was something many had been burning to talk about!  Within 3 hours we’d had close to 50 responses, and from there they continued coming in steadily until we received our 100th contribution on Friday.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Wed, 18 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-10-18-lets-talk-about-pronouns/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-10-18-lets-talk-about-pronouns/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Manifestation, misunderstanding and ‘misgendering’</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;A frequent area of discussion and dispute around gender critical views is whether and how much they can be expressed (or &lt;em&gt;‘manifested’&lt;/em&gt; to use the legal term) in the workplace.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Mon, 16 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-10-16-manifestation/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-10-16-manifestation/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Why SEEN is important to me (viii)</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;To Celebrate Bisexuality Week, we wanted to share this post from a civil servant. This post shares an individual’s personal experience, which includes frank references to his negative experiences in another civil service network.  Many staff networks will have members and interests in common, but we also serve differing needs and as this post makes clear, these are sometimes incompatible.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Sun, 17 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-09-17-why-is-seen-important-to-me-viii/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-09-17-why-is-seen-important-to-me-viii/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>The Fahmy v Arts Council England tribunal judgment</title>
        
          <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;background&quot;&gt;Background&lt;/h3&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Sat, 09 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-09-09-the-fahmy-v-arts-council-england-tribunal-judgment/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-09-09-the-fahmy-v-arts-council-england-tribunal-judgment/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Why SEEN is important to me (vii)</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;Bring your whole self to work is what my employer tells me. Unless of course you happen to believe like I do that sex is binary and fixed from conception. In that case I am allowed to hold that belief (thank you &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.judiciary.uk/judgments/forstater-v-cgd-europe-and-ors/&quot;&gt;Maya&lt;/a&gt;), but not to express it plainly in case it causes offense to those who believe that the concept of innate gender identity is more important in all cases than biological sex, or somehow denies their identity.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;But what about my identity?&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Wed, 19 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-07-19-why-is-seen-important-to-me-vii/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-07-19-why-is-seen-important-to-me-vii/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>The Protected Characteristics</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;We often come across training and guidance that makes reference to the protected characteristics, and it’s really important that this is presented correctly.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-07-04-the-protected-characteristics-a-reminder/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-07-04-the-protected-characteristics-a-reminder/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Rural lesbians and a safer world</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;I grew up in the rural idyll of Herefordshire &amp;amp; Worcestershire, having known most of my life that I was attracted to my own sex. There was little chance of my ever “coming out”, even though I went to an all-girls school, because at that time there was still huge stigma attached to being lesbian. It would have been social death at school, and I really didn’t want to cope with being ostracised while trying to complete my O-levels. The successful gaining of O-levels was directly linked to my gaining a motorbike and I wanted that nearly as much as I wanted a set of drums.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Thu, 29 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-06-29-rural-lesbians-and-a-safer-world/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-06-29-rural-lesbians-and-a-safer-world/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Celebrating Lesbian Visibility Day 2023</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;Lesbians in history have tended to be largely invisible (try naming five famous lesbians… or try naming five famous lesbians without mentioning Martina). Despite a heyday in the 1990s, we are once again disappearing - hence Lesbian Visibility Day.  Let’s prepare for our day of celebration and visibility by looking at a selection of historical highlights.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Wed, 26 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-04-26-lesbian-visibility-day/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-04-26-lesbian-visibility-day/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Why SEEN is important to me (vi)</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;In this time of strikes by the public service professions dominated by women, I’ve been reflecting on the often-overlooked history of women in the UK trade union movement and parallels to today, where many women still struggle to have their needs met for appropriate pay and suitable health and safety conditions, including to protect them during pregnancy and maternity.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Mon, 24 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-04-24-why-is-seen-important-to-me-vi/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-04-24-why-is-seen-important-to-me-vi/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Why SEEN is important to me (v)</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;This wasn’t something I ever saw myself doing, after I came out as a lesbian to my family that loved and accepted me, to walking with Stonewall at London’s Pride Parade. I didn’t know that a new ideology was emerging from internet discussions into general life and into politics. I didn’t see myself as a very political person until I realised what you can lose if you don’t pay attention to the discussions around you. This is why I’m no longer afraid to speak, because I’m now aware of what there is to lose.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Mon, 27 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-03-27-why-is-seen-important-to-me-v/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-03-27-why-is-seen-important-to-me-v/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>An interview with Ritchie Herron for Detrans Awareness Day</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;‘Detransitioners’ are people who have taken social or medical steps to change their gender but who later decide they feel more comfortable with their birth sex. Detransitioners are diverse and have varied and complex histories to tell, and we must respect how each one tells their own story and how they would like to be supported, including at work. We are platforming one SEEN member today to tell his own story today, to mark Detransition Awareness Day 2023.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Sun, 12 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-03-12-detrans-awareness-day/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-03-12-detrans-awareness-day/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>International Women’s Day 2023</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;At my mixed-sex primary school, our playground consisted simply of one big rectangle made of concrete. The playground didn’t have any lines marked on it, and it had no goal posts. And yet every playtime and lunchtime, it became a football pitch for the boys, the goals marked by their grubby jumpers. God help you if you were a boy who didn’t like football, but that’s another story. We girls gathered around the edges, chatting, skipping, cartwheeling, or playing endless games of catch. If we strayed onto the football pitch, the boys met us with shouts and shoves. When the football got kicked out, we were expected to toss it back to the boys in the right direction.  Occasionally a particularly bolshy girl (future feminists of the UK? You know who you are, ladies) would boot the football away into the car-park and then all hell would break loose.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Wed, 08 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-03-08-international-womens-day/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-03-08-international-womens-day/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Why SEEN is important to me (iv)</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[This post is the last of &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/launch-speeches/&quot;&gt;four speeches by SEEN members&lt;/a&gt; from our launch event in October. The author wishes to remain anonymous.]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Mon, 27 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-02-27-why-is-seen-important-to-me-iv/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-02-27-why-is-seen-important-to-me-iv/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Gluck</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;Another forgotten hero for LGBT history month, another lesser known artist from the 20th Century, this time a woman.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Sun, 26 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-02-26-gluck/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-02-26-gluck/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Willem Arondeus</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;This LGBT History Month we would like to invite a celebration of some lesser known heroes who don’t always feature on the mainstream narrative.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Tue, 21 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-02-21-willem-arondeus/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-02-21-willem-arondeus/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Understanding our sex-based rights and protections at work</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;We hear often from colleagues concerned that HR teams, management and staff training providers have made mistakes when they talk about equality law, and especially about sex-based rights and protections.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Fri, 17 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-02-17-understanding-our-sex-based-rights-and-protections-at-work/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-02-17-understanding-our-sex-based-rights-and-protections-at-work/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Gay in the UK</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;I have been delighted to write this blog for SEEN, for LGB(T) History Month.. This blog particularly focuses on a potted history of gay rights in the UK as they relate to gay men, but later in the month a ‘sister’ piece will be released focusing on lesbian history. The blog covers 500 years worth of history, and shows how the rights for gay men to live and love freely are an incredibly recent occurrence within the history of the UK, still very much in living memory.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Tue, 14 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-02-14-gay-in-the-uk/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-02-14-gay-in-the-uk/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Zero tolerance for Female Genital Mutilation</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;6th February is the UN’s International Day of Zero Tolerance for Female Genital Mutilation.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Mon, 06 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-02-06-zero-tolerance-for-fgm/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-02-06-zero-tolerance-for-fgm/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Why SEEN is important to me (iii)</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[This post is the third of &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/launch-speeches/&quot;&gt;four speeches by SEEN members&lt;/a&gt; from our launch event in October.]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-01-25-why-is-seen-important-to-me-iii/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-01-25-why-is-seen-important-to-me-iii/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Why SEEN is important to me (ii)</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[This post is the second of &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/launch-speeches/&quot;&gt;four speeches by SEEN members&lt;/a&gt; from our launch event in October. Named individuals are anonymised.]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Tue, 10 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-01-10-why-is-seen-important-to-me-ii/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-01-10-why-is-seen-important-to-me-ii/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Why SEEN is important to me (i)</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[This post is the first of &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/launch-speeches/&quot;&gt;four speeches by SEEN members&lt;/a&gt; from our launch event in October.]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-01-04-why-is-seen-important-to-me/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-01-04-why-is-seen-important-to-me/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Ending violence against women</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;We like to think that in the UK we have equality between the sexes now. On the statute book, we mostly do. But can we ever be equal while women and girls live our lives in fear of violence from men? Do we even think about this? Or have we just accepted that male violence against women and girls has always been normal and always will be? Women and girls plan our daily lives in anticipation of sexual assault, rape and beating. Is it an instinct we are born with, because of our female sex, that comes with our female reproductive system? Or does it begin that day our mother first tells us to watch out for strange men (what does she mean?), or the day we watch the 5 o’clock news after cartoon-time and see the photo of a woman murdered by her husband?&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Fri, 25 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        https://seen-network.uk/posts/2022-11-25-ending-violence-against-women/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://seen-network.uk/posts/2022-11-25-ending-violence-against-women/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>On tolerance</title>
        
          <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;reflecting-society&quot;&gt;Reflecting society&lt;/h2&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Tue, 22 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        https://seen-network.uk/posts/2022-11-22-on-tolerance/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://seen-network.uk/posts/2022-11-22-on-tolerance/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>A network update</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;A quick post to update our supporters and other interested parties.  It has been quite a month since our launch event on October 20th!  We wanted to reassure you that while we may have been keeping quiet, we have been incredibly busy.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Mon, 21 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        https://seen-network.uk/posts/2022-11-21-network-update/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://seen-network.uk/posts/2022-11-21-network-update/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>A new staff network</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;We are happy to announce the launch of our new UK cross-government staff network, the &lt;em&gt;Sex Equality and Equity Network&lt;/em&gt;.  For more on our mission and who we are see &lt;a href=&quot;/about/&quot;&gt;About us&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Thu, 13 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        https://seen-network.uk/posts/2022-10-13-a-new-staff-network/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://seen-network.uk/posts/2022-10-13-a-new-staff-network/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
  </channel>
</rss>
