<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/sex-discrimination/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2025-08-26T22:05:27+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/sex-discrimination/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">SEEN | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Sex Equality and Equity Network</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Elimination of violence against women and girls</title>
      <link href="/posts/2024-11-27-idevaw-2024/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Elimination of violence against women and girls" />
      <published>2024-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2024-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/idevaw-2024</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2024-11-27-idevaw-2024/">&lt;p&gt;Our duty and our honour: what can we as public servants do to stop violence against women and girls?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Entrenched patriarchy at almost every level of society, combined with a rise in misogyny that permeates the physical and online world, is denying thousands of women and girls across the UK the right to live in safety, free from fear and violence.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;  &lt;em&gt;- Reem Alsalem, the UN Special Rapporteur on violence against women and girls, London, 21 February 2024&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;November is a solemn month. Darkness, cold, heaviness, fatigue. We trudge through dead leaves and deadlines. On the 11th November, the knell of Remembrance Day forces us to visualise the horror of violence and the long reach of grief. Slog through two more weeks and we reach the 25th November, the International Day for the Elimination of Violence Against Women and Girls. Whether it’s the split second of the bomb explosion or the slower stealth of the thousand acts of violence which can cripple women’s lives, we remember how fragile we humans are. And we try to puzzle out again that insane equation: the enormous effort and love we give to birth and raise every human compared to how easily a life can be destroyed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this time of remembering, colleagues and I have been reflecting also about why we became public servants. It comes down to this: we love life. In the dark of November, let’s remember the honour we have in being entrusted to take care of the people of the UK. And so, we look forward with hope to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.un.org/en/observances/ending-violence-against-women-day&quot;&gt;sixteen days of world action&lt;/a&gt; for women and girls that the 25th November begins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us use this opportunity to focus our minds on what I believe should be integral to our ethics as public servants: that we must consciously work for the rights, safety and dignity of women and girls. As Reem Alsalem set out so forensically in her recent UN report (link below), the UK has come far in establishing rights for women, at least on paper, and yet, in 2024, we can look around us any day and despair. We still live in a society where male violence against women and girls, in all its many forms, is widespread and often taken for granted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, we think first about the violence at home, which may come from our fathers, husbands or brothers, and we remember the violence from the stranger in the street. But our culture where violence against women and girls, usually from males, is tolerated, is also shaped by our state structures and our roles, as public servants, within those structures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We as public servants take thousands of policy and operational decisions every week which form what happens in our schools, our hospitals, our laws, our job centres, our immigration systems, our social security systems, our police, our prisons and probation services, our care homes, our housing estates, our family courts, our women’s refuges, our foreign aid. The decisions we make can deter or enable male violence. Our institutions and systems can be structures of care and safety, or they can condemn women and girls to more insecurity and fear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None of us looks lovingly at a new baby girl and imagines she will grow up to be the girl sexually assaulted by the boys in her class at school, the teenager forced into prostitution to pay her rent, the mother struggling to raise her children while sinking deeper into debt or having her children taken away because she can’t protect them from her violent boyfriend, the woman in prison with a drug addiction or suicidal in a mental hospital because she can’t cope with her traumatic memories. Or is she just that quiet little woman in the office whom you barely notice, who lives a small life scared by her own shadow, wondering when a man will rape her again?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We as public servants must insist on noticing that quiet little woman, and all the other women and girls who live and die under violence. We refuse to accept violence as normal. It is our duty and our honour as public servants, whether male or female, to see violence and to act on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let’s not just view equality for women and girls as another tick box on an equality impact assessment, that we go through the motions with ‘because of that PSED training’. There can never be equality for women and girls while we continue to build  misogyny and violence into our culture. Today and every day, let every one of us look at how we do our jobs and see what we can do better for women and girls and so make our society better for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We hope you will find some inspiration from the links below, including the good example of our colleagues at the Youth Justice Board. Over the next fortnight, on the SEEN website and ‘X’, we will highlight more of the positive work being done by our colleagues: please do contact us with links to examples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Links:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/government/news/white-ribbon-day-2024-a-call-to-action-for-men-and-boys&quot;&gt;https://www.gov.uk/government/news/white-ribbon-day-2024-a-call-to-action-for-men-and-boys&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ohchr.org/en/press-releases/2024/02/no-time-lose-uk-declares-violence-against-women-national-threat-un-expert&quot;&gt;https://www.ohchr.org/en/press-releases/2024/02/no-time-lose-uk-declares-violence-against-women-national-threat-un-expert&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.unwomen.org/en/what-we-do/ending-violence-against-women/unite&quot;&gt;https://www.unwomen.org/en/what-we-do/ending-violence-against-women/unite&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.endviolenceagainstwomen.org.uk/about/&quot;&gt;https://www.endviolenceagainstwomen.org.uk/about/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see here our articles for IDEVAWG from 2023 and 2022:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-11-25-ending-violence-against-women/&quot;&gt;https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-11-25-ending-violence-against-women/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://seen-network.uk/posts/2022-11-25-ending-violence-against-women/&quot;&gt;https://seen-network.uk/posts/2022-11-25-ending-violence-against-women/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover art&lt;/strong&gt; from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.un.org/en/observances/ending-violence-against-women-day/background&quot;&gt;United Nations&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>UNSEEN</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="violence against women and girls" />
      
        <category term="sex discrimination" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Our duty and our honour: what can we as public servants do to stop violence against women and girls?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Violence against women. The judicial system is trying – is it succeeding?</title>
      <link href="/posts/2023-11-26-idevaw-is-the-judicial-system-succeeding/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Violence against women. The judicial system is trying – is it succeeding?" />
      <published>2023-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/idevaw-is-the-judicial-system-succeeding</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2023-11-26-idevaw-is-the-judicial-system-succeeding/">&lt;p&gt;I have been a magistrate for over thirty years and prior to that was a special constable.  During those decades views on domestic violence, specifically violence against women have changed considerably – but there is still a long way to go.  In the past, the model was largely the ‘Andy Capp’ cartoon featured in the Daily Mirror from 1957.  Women were subservient, best placed in the home with a single role to provide for all mens’ needs.  The cartoon strip thrived on Florence Capp being unprepared for tea on the table at 5pm sharp and Andy’s violent response to it.  The view of police and the wider judiciary was - then and until recently - largely that if he hit her, she obviously deserved it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have advanced significantly.  The courts have moved from a model where violence in a domestic context was a mitigating factor reducing the assailant’s sentence, to one where it is a serious aggravating factor, resulting in a higher sentence for any comparable level of violence.  Victim shaming at court was previously prevalent (‘she asked for it’ or ‘she provoked him’) to a current regime where most judges (me included) will stop any attempt by a defence advocate to blame or shame the victim.  The system isn’t perfect and there is still quite a way to go to ensure the judiciary supports women in that context, without prejudicing the rights of the accused to a proper defence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Support for women who are victims, or potential victims of violence varies across the country and is afforded a different priority, principally by different Police and Crime Commissioners, the elected policing budget holders in each area in England and Wales.  In Cambridgeshire for example, the commissioner funds the “Bobby Scheme”, a local charity (of which I am a trustee) formed in 2000 which works with vulnerable victims of crime and has long had a particular focus on women caught in, or likely to be caught in domestic violence.  The charity will support victims after an incident perhaps by replacing locks, providing alarms and so on, through to construction of a full panic room, also working proactively on the recommendations of police, social services or others.  Frequently the Samaritans refer women to us.  We have never had to turn down a request for support for want of funds.  Unfortunately there are only a small number of such schemes nationally (about six) and support for victims varies widely, relying on local authorities and charities to fund and provide support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A major challenge which I regularly observe at court is that the defendants accused of violence towards women don’t see that there is any issue.  At a trial I heard within the last month, the male defendant  had hit the female complainant multiple times resulting in severe cuts and bruises and also a broken nose, with enduring physical and emotional pain.  He could not see that he had done anything wrong, as she had (he said) grossly over-reacted to his cheating on her.  Under cross-examination he volunteered that if she had cheated on him, he might have killed her.  Alas that outcome is all too common.  Estimates vary but the current view is that at least two women die each week as a result of male perpetrated violence.  In the case of my trial, although she has recovered from the physical damage, he will have some time in prison to think about what he has done.  Unfortunately, I am not convinced that he will emerge at the end of his sentence as a changed and reformed man.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://niaendingviolence.org.uk/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;nia&lt;/strong&gt; - niaendingviolence.org.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://refuge.org.uk/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Refuge&lt;/strong&gt; - refuge.org.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is one of a series of four blogs SEEN is publishing to mark the International Day for the Elimination of Violence against Women 2023. &lt;a href=&quot;/posts/2023-11-25-ending-violence-against-women/&quot;&gt;See here&lt;/a&gt; for the others.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover photo&lt;/strong&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/unwomen/51737051738&quot;&gt;UN Women&lt;/a&gt; on Flickr (&lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.0/&quot;&gt;licence&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>benjamyn</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="violence against women and girls" />
      
        <category term="sex discrimination" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">I have been a magistrate for over thirty years and prior to that was a special constable. During those decades views on domestic violence, specifically violence against women have changed considerably – but there is still a long way to go. In the past, the model was largely the ‘Andy Capp’ cartoon featured in the Daily Mirror from 1957. Women were subservient, best placed in the home with a single role to provide for all mens’ needs. The cartoon strip thrived on Florence Capp being unprepared for tea on the table at 5pm sharp and Andy’s violent response to it. The view of police and the wider judiciary was - then and until recently - largely that if he hit her, she obviously deserved it.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Violence Against Women &amp;amp; Girls – 16 days of activism</title>
      <link href="/posts/2023-11-25-idevaw-16-days-of-activism/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Violence Against Women &amp; Girls – 16 days of activism" />
      <published>2023-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/idevaw-16-days-of-activism</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2023-11-25-idevaw-16-days-of-activism/">&lt;p&gt;November 25 is the UN’s &lt;em&gt;International Day for the Elimination of Violence Against Women&lt;/em&gt; (IDEVAW).Between then and &lt;em&gt;International Human Rights Day&lt;/em&gt; on 10 December, the UN is calling for &lt;em&gt;16 days of activism&lt;/em&gt; &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; to raise awareness and seek solutions to this oldest and most pervasive of problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Violence against women, by men, is endemic, both globally and very close to home (often literally). In 2020 in the UK, 110 women were killed by men &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; – a level of femicide that has remained consistent over time. In general, a woman is killed by a man in the UK every 3 days, every single year – most commonly a man she knows, or is related to, and most often in her own or someone else’s home. Moreover, rape conviction rates in the UK are at an historic low, and ONS figures show that 73% of UK domestic abuse victims in 2020/21 were female.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don’t have to be a statistician to recognise that the fact 98% of sexual violence is committed by male people doesn’t mean that 98% of male people commit sexual violence. But if we insist that violence against women is just the sum of horrible but isolated things done to some unlucky female people by a minority of damaged male people, we can’t begin to understand the bigger question of why this violence is so overwhelmingly gendered. Gender, after all, is understood by radical-minded feminists as the means by which patriarchal societies enforce the oppression of female people – by designating women a subordinate class, and using gendered norms to maintain male hegemony.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Male violence, then, commonly functions to enforce gender conformity, ie the subordination of women and the entrenchment of masculine entitlement. Aggression against gay and transgender people, for example, is commonly rooted in the perceived threat of non-conformity. Misogyny itself is deeply entwined with a thwarted sense of male entitlement – many terrorist attackers have a history as domestic abusers, and mass shootings and incel atrocities have often started with the killing of female relatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seen as a weapon of patriarchy, it’s clear that systemic violence against women is not limited to physical abuse, rape and murder. Violence and oppression against female people are also meted out in more insidious ways that are no less effective at keeping women as a sex class disempowered and therefore subordinated. Sometimes the silencing and banishment of women is very literal, if brutal – forced veiling, guardianship and disenfranchisement, for example. But oppression also works through cultural and social mechanisms – two thirds of the world’s illiterate population is female&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, and this is linked to the prevalence of child marriage of girls. This isn’t limited to the developing world – five US states have no minimum age for marriage, with a parental or judicial waiver, and marriage to an underage girl is a defence against statutory rape in most US states. &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Bodily exploitation through prostitution or surrogacy might not be done at knifepoint, but its framing as a commercial transaction makes explicit the status of female bodies as a patriarchal resource.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A woman doesn’t have to be personally attacked or exploited to be a victim of patriarchal violence – throughout history, female people as a class have suffered from the stranglehold of gender norms, which deem brains, spirit and self-determination to be incompatible with being a woman. Some women may have famously slipped the net though a male pseudonym, an amanuensis or even a full male identity, if they could convince enough people to go along with it. But for most women, this wasn’t an option – and yet the gendered expectations placed on female people by patriarchy can be intolerable. When they are, women’s and girls’ distress has been weaponised against them – women have been institutionalised for hysteria, given lobotomies and drugged up on tranquilisers when they have failed to comply with gendered subordination. Girls’ higher rates of dysmorphia, self-harm and eating disorders point to the struggles of growing up in a patriarchal society where a female body can feel like a prison – who wouldn’t want to escape?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So to eliminate violence against women, it isn’t enough to find and stop the minority of individual men who beat, rape and kill. Violence against women describes the systematic oppression and subordination of female people as a class, though its presentation takes many forms. By recognising this, we are better able to challenge it by changing the shape of our societies, rather than tackling one bad man at a time, and wondering why this keeps happening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/posts/2023-11-25-ending-violence-against-women/&quot;&gt;See here&lt;/a&gt; for our other posts for IDEVAW 2023.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover photo&lt;/strong&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/unwomen/51737051738&quot;&gt;UN Women&lt;/a&gt; on Flickr (&lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.0/&quot;&gt;licence&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.unwomen.org/en/what-we-do/ending-violence-against-women/unite/16-days-of-activism&quot;&gt;UN Women: 16 days of activism&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;femicidecensus.org&quot;&gt;femicidecensus.org&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://uis.unesco.org/sites/default/files/documents/fs32-adult-and-youth-literacy-2015-en_0.pdf&quot;&gt;UNESCO: Adult and Youth Literacy Factsheet 2015&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.unchainedatlast.org/united-states-child-marriage-problem-study-findings-april-2021/&quot;&gt;unchainedatlast.org&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>UNSEEN</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="violence against women and girls" />
      
        <category term="sex discrimination" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">November 25 is the UN’s International Day for the Elimination of Violence Against Women (IDEVAW).Between then and International Human Rights Day on 10 December, the UN is calling for 16 days of activism 1 to raise awareness and seek solutions to this oldest and most pervasive of problems. UN Women: 16 days of activism &amp;#8617;</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Why SEEN is important to me (ii)</title>
      <link href="/posts/2023-01-10-why-is-seen-important-to-me-ii/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why SEEN is important to me (ii)" />
      <published>2023-01-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-01-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/why-is-seen-important-to-me-ii</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2023-01-10-why-is-seen-important-to-me-ii/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[This post is the second of &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/launch-speeches/&quot;&gt;four speeches by SEEN members&lt;/a&gt; from our launch event in October. Named individuals are anonymised.]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good afternoon everyone, I am one of the Co-Chairs of the new Network.  It gives me great pleasure, on behalf of myself, my-Co-Chairs and the rest of our steering group, to welcome you all today to the first meeting of the new Civil Service Sex Equality and Equity Network and I’d like to thank you all for coming.  I’ve opened and chaired meetings with that form of words on many occasions, but it has rarely been so whole-heartedly true as it is today.  This gathering and the formation of this network is something that a group of us have been looking forward to for quite a while.  We have all, for different reasons, felt that there has been a gap in the activities that take place to promote diversity in the Civil Service in that they do not recognise the existence and legitimacy of those of us who consider that there will always be circumstances where sex is important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quite a number of us are lawyers, and we all start from the position that civil servants should uphold the law in all our dealings.  The central focus of our network will be on the sex-based rights and protections that the law provides.  As we state in our constitution: “we will focus on challenging sex discrimination, and upholding rights and protections that relate to sex (including the protections provided to those with the protected characteristics of sex and sexual orientation).  We recognise that ensuring sex equality and equity sometimes requires treating women and men differently, according to our different rights”.  Because the law is so central to what we stand for, we are fortunate enough to have a lawyer who specialises in discrimination law, here this afternoon to give a brief introduction to some of the legal provisions that create and support sex-based rights and protections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are also committed to the protected belief (covered by the protected characteristic of religion and belief in the Equality Act 2010) that biological sex is binary and immutable, that biological sex matters for both women and men in our everyday lives, including for many of our rights and needs in the workplace, and that biological sex must not be conflated with the concepts of gender identity or gender.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What will this mean in practice in terms of the goals we will pursue as a network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It means, for example, that we will push for the Civil Service to collect accurate and meaningful data on the protected characteristic of sex.  Because of the importance of data in understanding inequalities and acting to achieve sex equality, we have also invited a colleague who specialises in statistics, to speak briefly on this topic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also means that we will advocate for workplace policies and practices that contain clear sex-based language, where relevant.  To this end, we are also fortunate to be hearing from one of my colleagues on the topic of language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, in addition to a clear understanding and application of the law, data and language, an understanding of our network would not be complete without an appreciation of the experiences which have drawn many of us to have an interest in this field.  So, you will also hear testimonies from other SEEN members as to why the formation of this network is important to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll give you may own - rather mundane - personal story in a moment, but I wanted to start by explaining a bit more about why we have set up this network and what we hope it will achieve.  I hope most of you will be able to relate to our motivation and support what we want to accomplish.  We have deliberately kept the guest list for this event small and largely limited to people who have contacted us because they wanted to be part of something like this, so that we have the confidence to share experiences here.  But we have some guests who are involved in Diversity and Inclusion in the civil service and hope those guests will also understand and support what we are trying to do in the interests of promoting greater diversity and inclusion in the civil service.  By encouraging a range of voices to speak up and create an open and respectful dialogue, we aim to achieve greater tolerance between those with differing beliefs and experiences and ‘foster good relations between people who share particular protected characteristic and those who do not’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone should have their legal rights and interests properly respected and protected in the workplace.  We recognise that this includes those who disagree with us.  Conversely, just because others may disagree with our protected beliefs, this is not an excuse to vilify us or try to restrict the exercise of our legal rights.  We will strongly resist such an approach.  Amongst our aims is to promote understanding between people with different beliefs and ensure that the civil service properly caters for those who hold all of them, balancing them where necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We very much hope that all those aims will be achieved by this network coming into existence and we intend to make good use of the voice that the network will give us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will now turn briefly to the personal and explain why I care so much about this.  There are three main reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, because I regard the substitution of sex with gender identity in relation to equality aims as a retrograde step for women’s rights.  When I was starting out on my career, my father told me that he was worried about the cost of educating girls and that if I incurred debts in the course of my training, it would give me a ‘negative dowry’, a very sexist and demeaning viewpoint which I did not allow to throw me off course.  Then my uncle, who was a solicitor, told me that he would offer a training contract to my husband, and not to me, because being a trainee solicitor involved lots of ‘out-door work’ and so was not suitable work for a woman! We’ve collectively proved him wrong, more than 50% of solicitors are now women and that percentage is even higher in the civil service.  I have personally proved him wrong by having a successful career as a lawyer.  Both of these views were based on harmful stereotypes in relation to the role of women in society.  I am concerned that an insistence on the idea that everyone has an innate gender identity is a way of allowing those types of stereotype, which until a few years ago I thought were well on the way to being eradicated, back into society by the back door.  The concept of gender identity, whilst proponents describe it as an internal feeling, is difficult to separate from societal expectations of how each sex is expected to behave.  As someone who does not consider I have a gender identity, the idea that if I do not conform to the societal expectations for my sex, I may actually be of a different sex or even gender, seems highly regressive.  If this serves to reinforce, rather than rid us of such unhelpful stereotypes, the consequences for the equality of women, and indeed for all gender non-conforming people, for equity in our society to the benefit of both sexes seem to me to be highly damaging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, I care because of the impact on single-sex services for women.  In my spare time I was for many years the chair of the board of a charity running a women’s refuge.  In the course of that work, I met and my organisation helped many severely traumatised women and their children by providing a safe refuge and a service provided by women and for women, taking advantage of an exception in what is now the Equality Act 2010.  Refuge services are a strong example of the importance of sex-based rights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst of course not all men are abusers, it is surely contrary to a tradition of recognising the need for single sex provision in this are, to up to date evidence on perpetrators and victims and to much good-practice in trauma-informed health care to require female victims of male abuse and their children to live in close proximity to biological male victims, no matter how they identify.  Any traumatised victim is likely to feel unsafe and more traumatised in such an environment, and where biological sex dictates having different needs in any event, such a practice would have been likely to undermine the effectiveness of the service our charity provided (particularly given such services could instead be provided more effectively in separate facilities).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This issue is not directly relevant to the work of this network which will focus on where they are important in our Civil Service workplaces, but it is part of what motivates me to care about this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I also care about the impact of the difficulty of speaking up about sex-based rights on my gay and neurodiverse colleagues and friends, but I’ll let colleagues speak to that shortly.  Please be aware that they cover some sensitive topics in a frank fashion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I’ve set out why we are setting up this network and given you a flavour of my personal motivation.  Some of my colleagues are now going to address specific aspects of our aims and offer you an insight into their motivations.  We’ll take a brief break for networking in the middle of the speaker slots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you have heard from them we’d like to lead a more participative session about the network and its plans.  We’ll try to answer questions but please don’t ask for more personal information from our speakers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, a note about context.  We want our network to recognise freedom of speech and hope you will feel comfortable to share your views.  I am sure you will all express yourselves sensitively though and bear in mind that this is a meeting of an official civil service network and so we need to abide by the Civil Service Code and conduct ourselves accordingly as I am sure you will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover image:&lt;/strong&gt;  “Thinking woman” by pacogaitero is licensed under CC BY-NC-SA 2.0. To view a copy of this license, visit https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/2.0/?ref=openverse.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Mary</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="personal experience" />
      
        <category term="sex discrimination" />
      
        <category term="gender stereotyping" />
      
        <category term="launch speeches" />
      
        <category term="why seen" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">[This post is the second of four speeches by SEEN members from our launch event in October. Named individuals are anonymised.]</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
