<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/network/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2025-08-26T22:05:27+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/network/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">SEEN | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Sex Equality and Equity Network</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Impartiality and Finding Common Ground</title>
      <link href="/posts/2023-11-21-impartiality-and-finding-common-ground/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Impartiality and Finding Common Ground" />
      <published>2023-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/impartiality-and-finding-common-ground</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2023-11-21-impartiality-and-finding-common-ground/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;On 14th November, SEEN was invited to participate in the “Navigating Difference Finding Common Ground” webinar, and interfaith and belief event, which formed part of Faith and Belief Week 2023.  This was our presentation, given by a SEEN co-chair, as a part of the panel.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;•·················•·················•&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’d be the first to admit that SEEN - the Sex Equality and Equity network - is a strange one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve been a cross governmental network for a year, and our journey has certainly been unconventional: at times controversial, sometimes even fractious.  It’s also taught us something about the importance of a fair and demonstrably impartial workplace, and about how we might find common ground when we profoundly disagree.  I’d like to share these thoughts today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But first: a mystery.  We are not the only network underpinned by a clear set of beliefs.  The same is also true of both the Gender and LGBT+ networks.  These are often stated as ‘trans women are women, trans men are men and non-binary identities are valid’.  Conversely, our position can also be stated very briefly as: sex is binary and immutable and matters more than gender.  So why were we the ones that ended up as a ‘faith and belief’ network?   Well, the answer is because until 2019 you could be fired for voicing these views in the workplace.  The now famous &lt;em&gt;Forstater&lt;/em&gt; case changed that, confirming that our views are worthy of respect in a democratic society.  And so - our belief protected - the rest is history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d like to just repeat something again.  &lt;em&gt;Back in 2019 people were being fired for expressing these views.&lt;/em&gt;  And even now it can still be taboo to state what ten years ago would have been utterly unremarkable.  How did this radical shift happen?  We see some of the explanation lying in well-intentioned workplace activism, perpetuated through training, webinars, blog posts and even email signatures; an activism which became so prevalent that our members tell us they felt shamed and even coerced into demonstrating a particular set of beliefs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But does that even matter if this results in a kinder, more diverse and inclusive workplace?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, the first question is whether it really does.  On the surface such workplaces may appear united, but the veneer of harmony presides over deep discomfort and fear.  We don’t think employees should have their thoughts and beliefs policed, or be pushed into demonstrating adherence to an ideology they don’t share.  More importantly, we don’t think anyone benefits from this approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our network can also be understood as a pushback against this enforced homogeny: the idea that ‘kindness’, ‘inclusivity’ and ‘diversity’ come via only one set of beliefs and fall under only one flag.  We don’t think harmony is achieved by making everyone pretend to believe the same thing.  And because we’ve seen these dangers, we have no desire to replace one activism with another.  I’ll even let you into a secret about our end-game.  What we are aiming for is a return to the impartiality which - at its best - characterises the Civil Service.  Then we’ll happily hang up our SEEN lanyards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what’s so great about impartiality?  It sounds cold and indifferent.  But our experience is that in practice it can operate to do something magical.  Impartiality is nonjudgmental and fair.  It accepts that the workplace can’t be made perfect, it will always reflect our wider, complex society.  It recognises that it’s not the role of our employer to forge us into anyone’s vision of what a better human being looks like.   The real world and the people within it are subtle, complex and interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There will always be differences between us.  But genuine impartiality allows for difference and diversity to flourish.  And diversity is a vital part of the Civil Service’s success. Our steering group came together through our shared interest in this issue, but accidentally formed a microcosm of the diversity that we think makes the Civil Service great.  Within our small group we have members of four different faiths (and others of none), those from a range of social and ethnic backgrounds, some who are lesbian or gay and – of course – both men and women.  There are huge differences between us, in outlook, approach, background and personality.  Working with this extraordinary group of people has taught me first hand how true diversity can make a team more than the sum of its parts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But is impartiality enough?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think there needs to be something else as well.  And so, what?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, we are not in a crèche.  We can’t expect our employer to solve all our problems.  And this is where I think us - employees - have an important role to play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I look for a secular solution, that of humanism and its emphasis on a common humanity.  Since forming as a network I’ve talked to many people, and the more I talk, the clearer it becomes that there is more that unites than divides us.  If we sharpen the edges of our identities to the point where one aspect of ourselves is all that matters, then the differences between us seem vast and it becomes easy to mistrust and dislike.  However I believe it is possible to create a work environment where even the most fundamental differences can be overcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, it’s not always necessary to talk about our differences.  I was once in a difficult conversation with a colleague who told me she was frightened I might start talking about my views.  I explained I’d much rather talk about our shared love of the same film director.  Sometimes discretion is the better part of valour.  However, there are times when difficult discussions are relevant.  And then it’s vital to understand that to disagree is not to dehumanise.  To be faced with polite disagreement over your world view is not to be rendered &lt;em&gt;unsafe&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, for all the lip service paid to ‘diversity’ we seem to have lost confidence in the idea that we &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; all be different – really, profoundly different – and still get on.  We seem to have forgotten that, however much we disagree (and even when these are on matters which go to the very core of our being) we can still be civil, maybe even friends.  That may sound impossibly idealistic, but we actually do it all the time.  Here’s an example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some time ago I was on a train.  It was hot and the journey was slow.  People were being incredibly annoying in the way that only people on trains can; music playing, bags on seats, dogs on seats, screaming children, arguing couples, smelly food, annoying sitcoms played without headphones.  Everyone was doing all they could to assert their personal train space and wind everyone else up.  Then in came this guy.  He was drunk, and slightly dangerous.  He started to pick fights and harass the female passengers.  Everyone went quiet, watching his progress, hoping he wouldn’t pick on them next.  Finally when the train stopped in the next station, the police came onboard and took the troublemaker away.  When the train doors shut and we finally moved off, the drunk man had gone but something else had changed.  Instead of a carriage full of people who slightly disliked each other on principle, we were now united: conversation broke out, people laughed, talked and had fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I’m not suggesting the Civil Service would benefit from a drunk maniac with anger management issues blundering through the office chased by the police.  But this incident highlighted to me that, as well as our fundamental need for individual communities and personal identities, there is another need which is one of the strongest of all: and that is to connect with those around us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And for me this is the real opportunity: by demonstrating confident impartiality, our workplace can create a neutral space which allows us - for all our differences - to step forward to work respectfully and civilly together.  And I’m optimistic that if we follow the basic ground rules, we may find we have more in common than we think, and thus work can become a place to make the connections that really enrich us.  And that is surely a win for us all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover photo&lt;/strong&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@charlesdeluvio?utm_content=creditCopyText&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_source=unsplash&quot;&gt;charlesdeluvio&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/photos/human-hand-neon-signage-AT5vuPoi8vc?utm_content=creditCopyText&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_source=unsplash&quot;&gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Elspeth Duemmer Wrigley</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="tolerance" />
      
        <category term="diversity of belief" />
      
        <category term="civil service" />
      
        <category term="network" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">On 14th November, SEEN was invited to participate in the “Navigating Difference Finding Common Ground” webinar, and interfaith and belief event, which formed part of Faith and Belief Week 2023. This was our presentation, given by a SEEN co-chair, as a part of the panel.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">On tolerance</title>
      <link href="/posts/2022-11-22-on-tolerance/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On tolerance" />
      <published>2022-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2022-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/on-tolerance</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2022-11-22-on-tolerance/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;reflecting-society&quot;&gt;Reflecting society&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Civil Service has always been a microcosm of British society. At first it was largely white and male, along with the other public and private institutions of the day. But with each new generation the bureaucracy adapted to changing societal norms and became gradually more diverse and representative, with some of the most significant changes happening within our lifetimes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It hasn't been a smooth journey. Progress often mirrors the build-up and release of pressures in tectonic shifts. Legislative and political developments like the Sex Discrimination Act 1975, sexual offences law changes of 1967, 2000 and 2003 (decriminalising homosexuality), the Data Protection Acts of 1984 and 1998, the Stephen Lawrence report in 1999, and the Freedom of Information Act 2000, and others all played important roles in bringing about much needed changes. By the turn of the millennium, all government departments were striving to attain Investors in People accreditation - the then-gold standard for inclusive working practices. Pluralism and tolerance were becoming dominant Civil Service values. Departmental staff networks sprang up everywhere, and could be found representing their organisations at Glastonbury and Pride. There were many issues that needed to be addressed, but the zeitgeist felt new and positive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In recent years something has changed. In 2019 a British woman lost her job for expressing her belief in the importance and nature of biological sex&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, a view never recorded in our history as controversial. Last year a university professor resigned following sustained abuse and harassment by her colleagues and students for having written a book that explored the same philosophical issues&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Stating what many (possibly most) people consider to be basic facts of life is now forbidden in many workplaces, sometimes by human resources codes, but more often by a chilling culture that suppresses substantive discussion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a matter of public debate that we may be witnessing the emergence of a new form of intolerance linked to changing attitudes towards freedom of expression&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. The trend is illustrated in the context of our universities by a survey of UK student opinion in May 2022&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, which found significant increases over the past 6 years in demands for protections from feeling threatened and for banning speakers that cause offence. It seems to mirror a similar shift in attitudes in the US&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;our-launch&quot;&gt;Our launch&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our network celebrates the drive towards greater equality, pluralism and respect for difference over recent decades, and in particular the more tolerant society that this has heralded. We are concerned that this progress is now under threat. Seeing some of the reactions to the launch of SEEN as an officially recognised cross-government staff network has made it clear to us that the Civil Service is not immune to this trend away from mutual tolerance. We have attracted significant criticism and hostility purely for announcing ourselves, and some colleagues have openly discussed getting us banned. Yet our network website (our only communication to date) makes clear our commitments to protection of everyone’s rights, encouraging a diversity of voices, and open and respectful dialogue and tolerance between those with differing beliefs and experiences, as well as the need to respect colleagues’ beliefs (or lack thereof). Some perhaps genuinely believe these are empty words, but they are not. We are the same people you have always worked alongside with mutual respect, and these values are in our DNA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The criticism of SEEN’s launch - which contrasts starkly with the hundreds of supportive messages and membership information requests we have received privately - has almost all focused on the nature of &lt;a href=&quot;/faq/#what-are-seens-values&quot;&gt;our core belief&lt;/a&gt;. It is a belief that our courts have ruled to be “worthy of respect in a democratic society” (and so holds the status of a protected belief under the Equality Act), and is shared by people from all backgrounds, of all political leanings, and by theist, atheist and agnostic alike. This hostile reaction to us has only strengthened our view that, for some in our society, their perceived needs have come to demand the silencing of those who hold beliefs they feel threatened by, regardless of the holders’ stated commitments to tolerance and pluralism. For this reason we would like to use our first blog article to consider tolerance, and why it matters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-paradox-of-tolerance&quot;&gt;The paradox of tolerance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One SEEN-critical comment in particular has stood out from the others by articulating an ostensible justification for silencing us. It referenced a popular philosophical maxim known as the “paradox of tolerance”, attributed to the philosopher Karl Popper, which in its simplest terms states that tolerance without limit will result in intolerance. The specific example Popper gave of those views which should be excluded because of their fundamental intolerance of others was Nazism (which courts have ruled gender critical belief “does not get anywhere near to approaching”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:6&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commonly omitted from such citations of the paradox is the fact that Popper went on to say:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I do not imply, for instance, that we should always suppress the utterance of intolerant philosophies; as long as we can counter them by rational argument and keep them in check by public opinion, suppression would certainly be most unwise. But we should claim the right to suppress them if necessary even by force; for it may easily turn out that they are not prepared to meet us on the level of rational argument, but begin by denouncing all argument &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:7&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:7&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Popper was speaking of philosophies inclined to meet rational argument with “fists or pistols”. A lucid reading of his words makes clear that what SEEN has said does not reflect anything like such a philosophy, let alone merit suppression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, other philosophers like Raphael Cohen-Almagor&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:8&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:8&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; have gone further to argue (again using the example of Nazism) that psychological harm is equal to physical harm. Ideas that cause others distress can, therefore, be legitimately restricted. Some of our critics have made this argument against us, claiming that even a statement of our core belief causes emotional harm and should be withdrawn or taken down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From our perspective there are two problems with this argument. The first is that it ignores the fact that the law protects the reasonable expression&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:9&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:9&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; of a protected religion or belief. The second is this: who gets to decide when a particular speaker, group or people with a particular belief pose a risk of psychological harm so great that they should be kept silent? And how can others be sure the decision is fair? Under Cohen-Almagor’s proposed scenario, judgements on what is acceptable speech seem far more likely to emerge not through consensus but through the dominance of certain perspectives over others. Hence in the context of a policy to prioritise emotional ‘safety’, those holding beliefs perceived as threatening are likely to be disproportionately affected, regardless of their actual commitment to pluralism and tolerance. And the evidence suggests the notion of emotional safety is not impartial: support in our universities for banning speakers from our main political parties is very unequal&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:10&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:10&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of the potential for causing harm, we invite readers to contrast our commitment to pluralism and tolerance with the open hostility we have received from some of our colleagues, which has caused intense distress and anxiety for some members of SEEN. We call upon colleagues who may disagree with our reasonably expressed viewpoints to express their disagreement with respect and professionalism, to tolerate different beliefs, and to call out the use of hostile language. Everyone deserves to be treated with respect and to be able to do their jobs free from bullying, harasment and discrimination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tolerance-in-a-pluralist-society&quot;&gt;Tolerance in a pluralist society&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We do not have to share beliefs in order to tolerate them. We live in a pluralist and diverse society. The beauty of living in a pluralist democracy is that we tolerate and indeed celebrate differences, and we manage to get along, including with those whose beliefs we do not share. A pluralist society allows us all to be free to express our beliefs, within the bounds of the law. For such a society to thrive, as Popper recognised, there must be limits to tolerance. However, these limits are not defined by those who shout the loudest, but ultimately by what is lawful. The Equality Act 2010 provides a legal framework to prevent people acting on their prejudices or disagreements in a way that results in discriminatory treatment of others. It sets out the nine characteristics that are protected by the law&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:11&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:11&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, including the protected characteristic of religion or belief, which is extended to beliefs that must, amongst other criteria, “be worthy of respect in a democratic society, be not incompatible with human dignity and not conflict with the fundamental rights of others”. Harassment of and discrimination against those holding and respectfully expressing such beliefs are examples of genuine intolerance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tolerance-and-expression-within-the-civil-service&quot;&gt;Tolerance and expression within the Civil Service&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Civil Servants we are bound by the Civil Service Code which requires political neutrality. So it is not appropriate for us to express views on matters of political controversy at work; we abide by that restriction and expect others to do likewise. We therefore only assert our right for our views to be heard with tolerance in respect of matters relevant to the workplace. Sometimes it will be necessary to explain the underlying beliefs in order to exercise our rights at work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2022 Civil Service Diversity and Inclusion Strategy&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:12&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:12&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; makes a specific commitment to challenging groupthink and inspiring a greater diversity of thinking. SEEN is committed to working to ensure that departmental policies for human resources and diversity and inclusion, as well as their implementation, reflect this commitment. If you support our &lt;a href=&quot;/faq/#what-is-seens-mission&quot;&gt;mission and values&lt;/a&gt; consider &lt;a href=&quot;/join/&quot;&gt;joining us&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Cover image: &lt;a href=&quot;https://pixabay.com/photos/exhibition-visitors-gallery-viewer-2944064/&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://pixabay.com/service/terms/&quot;&gt;licence&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-57426579&quot;&gt;https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-57426579&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-england-sussex-59084446&quot;&gt;https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-england-sussex-59084446&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/minister-donelan-addresses-policy-exchange&quot;&gt;https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/minister-donelan-addresses-policy-exchange&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hepi.ac.uk/2022/06/23/you-cant-say-that-new-polling-shows-students-want-more-controls-on-free-expression/&quot;&gt;https://www.hepi.ac.uk/2022/06/23/you-cant-say-that-new-polling-shows-students-want-more-controls-on-free-expression/&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2015/09/the-coddling-of-the-american-mind/399356/&quot;&gt;https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2015/09/the-coddling-of-the-american-mind/399356/&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://assets.publishing.service.gov.uk/media/60c1cce1d3bf7f4bd9814e39/Maya_Forstater_v_CGD_Europe_and_others_UKEAT0105_20_JOJ.pdf&quot;&gt;https://assets.publishing.service.gov.uk/media/60c1cce1d3bf7f4bd9814e39/Maya_Forstater_v_CGD_Europe_and_others_UKEAT0105_20_JOJ.pdf&lt;/a&gt; (para 111) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:6&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:7&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/dli.ernet.537231/page/265/mode/2up&quot;&gt;https://archive.org/details/dli.ernet.537231/page/265/mode/2up&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:7&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:8&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Raphael_Cohen-Almagor&amp;amp;oldid=1108658836#Freedom_of_Expression&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Raphael_Cohen-Almagor&amp;amp;oldid=1108658836#Freedom_of_Expression&lt;/a&gt; (and &lt;a href=&quot;https://ora.ox.ac.uk/objects/uuid:e02067a0-ba42-428c-967a-1f3ba11c64bf/download_file?file_format=application%2Fpdf&amp;amp;safe_filename=602327189.pdf&amp;amp;type_of_work=Thesis&quot;&gt;doctoral thesis&lt;/a&gt;) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:8&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:9&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.judiciary.uk/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/Forstater-Press-statement.pdf&quot;&gt;https://www.judiciary.uk/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/Forstater-Press-statement.pdf&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:9&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:10&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hepi.ac.uk/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/You-cant-say-that-What-students-really-think-of-free-speech-on-campus.pdf&quot;&gt;https://www.hepi.ac.uk/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/You-cant-say-that-What-students-really-think-of-free-speech-on-campus.pdf&lt;/a&gt; (p6) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:10&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:11&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/faq/#what-is-the-equality-act-2010-and-what-are-protected-characteristics&quot;&gt;FAQ: What is the Equality Act 2010 and what are protected characteristics?&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:11&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:12&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/civil-service-diversity-and-inclusion-strategy-2022-to-2025/civil-service-diversity-and-inclusion-strategy-2022-to-2025-html&quot;&gt;https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/civil-service-diversity-and-inclusion-strategy-2022-to-2025/civil-service-diversity-and-inclusion-strategy-2022-to-2025-html&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:12&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>SEEN Network</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="network" />
      
        <category term="tolerance" />
      
        <category term="diversity of belief" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Reflecting society</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A network update</title>
      <link href="/posts/2022-11-21-network-update/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A network update" />
      <published>2022-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2022-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/network-update</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2022-11-21-network-update/">&lt;p&gt;A quick post to update our supporters and other interested parties.  It has been quite a month since our launch event on October 20th!  We wanted to reassure you that while we may have been keeping quiet, we have been incredibly busy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The interest in our network has been phenomenal!  SEEN has been noticed and discussed not only on social media but also in the mainstream press.  We will continue to increase our visibility as a network across the Civil Service to promote who we are and what we stand for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several hundred people have so far expressed interest in SEEN membership from nearly 50 eligible organisations from across central government, the executive agencies and arm’s length bodies.  Considering the short time since our launch this is an amazing and humbling response.  &lt;strong&gt;If you have requested more information on membership and are waiting to hear back from us, please don’t fret.&lt;/strong&gt;  We aim to be in touch with you within the next week or two.  We will also shortly activate our mailing list to keep people up to speed with our latest news by email.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have also received many membership enquiries and requests from people that we sadly cannot extend membership to (given the permitted scope for cross-departmental staff networks), including in local and devolved governments, the NHS and police.  We very much hope that SEEN will help to inspire equivalent networks to organise in other areas of the public sector.  For those that have just reached out to express support we appreciate these messages too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re looking forward to the journey ahead, and remain resolute in our commitment to further our mission.  We have lots of ideas of things to do and events to run, so watch this space!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exciting times ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SEEN&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;8 Feb 2023 edit: On the basis of advice from the Cabinet Office we amend the eligibility paragraph from “local and devolved governments” to read “local governments”.  Civil servants in the devolved governments are in fact eligible for SEEN membership.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>SEEN Network</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="network" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">A quick post to update our supporters and other interested parties. It has been quite a month since our launch event on October 20th! We wanted to reassure you that while we may have been keeping quiet, we have been incredibly busy.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A new staff network</title>
      <link href="/posts/2022-10-13-a-new-staff-network/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A new staff network" />
      <published>2022-10-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2022-10-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/a-new-staff-network</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2022-10-13-a-new-staff-network/">&lt;p&gt;We are happy to announce the launch of our new UK cross-government staff network, the &lt;em&gt;Sex Equality and Equity Network&lt;/em&gt;.  For more on our mission and who we are see &lt;a href=&quot;/about/&quot;&gt;About us&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Edit (22/11/2022): in the interest of transparency here is the version of our About page as it looked when this post first issued.  This will not be changed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are happy to announce the launch of our new UK cross-government staff network, the &lt;em&gt;Sex Equality and Equity Network&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SEEN is a staff network committed to promoting and supporting sex equality and equity between women and men in our workplaces, and helping all staff to thrive at work and fulfil their potential. The focus of our network is on challenging sex discrimination and upholding sex-based rights (including the protected characteristics of sex and sexual orientation, as set out in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2010/15/contents&quot;&gt;Equality Act 2010&lt;/a&gt;).  We recognise that to achieve this and ensure sex equality and equity sometimes requires treating women and men differently, according to our different rights and needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are also committed to the protected belief (covered by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2010/15/section/10&quot;&gt;protected characteristic of religion and belief&lt;/a&gt; in the Equality Act 2010) that biological sex is binary and immutable, that biological sex matters for both women and men in our everyday lives, including for our rights and needs in the workplace, and that biological sex must not be conflated with, or replaced by, the concepts of gender or gender identity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a part of our mission we want civil servants to feel safe to exercise their legal rights under the European Convention of Human Rights to freedom of thought, conscience and religion, freedom of expression and freedom of assembly and association, provided they manifest their rights lawfully and respectfully and within the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/civil-service-code/the-civil-service-code&quot;&gt;Civil Service Code&lt;/a&gt;.  We wish to encourage a diversity of voices and open and respectful dialogue and tolerance between those with differing beliefs and experiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also aim to be a source of expertise for staff on the protected characteristic of sex, pregnancy, maternity and sexual orientation; as well as the importance of taking these fully into account to meet staff rights and needs, including through the development of workplace policies and practices.  We also plan to hold events and webinars in due course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SEEN membership is open to staff who share our values, from central government departments, agencies, and their associated public bodies including arm’s length bodies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you would like to learn more about our mission, or to be added to our mailing list, please get in touch: [contact details available very shortly].&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>SEEN Network</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="network" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">We are happy to announce the launch of our new UK cross-government staff network, the Sex Equality and Equity Network. For more on our mission and who we are see About us</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
