<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/seen/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2025-08-26T22:05:27+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/seen/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">SEEN | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Sex Equality and Equity Network</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Ending violence against women and girls</title>
      <link href="/posts/2023-11-25-ending-violence-against-women/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ending violence against women and girls" />
      <published>2023-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/ending-violence-against-women</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2023-11-25-ending-violence-against-women/">&lt;p&gt;For this year’s &lt;em&gt;International Day for the Elimination of Violence against Women&lt;/em&gt; SEEN is publishing articles today and over the next few days by four of our general members (outside our network leadership team), three of whom must remain anonymous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trigger warning:&lt;/strong&gt; As these blogs are to mark the IDEVAW, they necessarily refer to violence against women including domestic abuse, rape and femicide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;1--16-days-of-activism&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/posts/2023-11-25-idevaw-16-days-of-activism/&quot;&gt;#1  &lt;em&gt;“16 days of activism”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our first post sets out some of the very sobering facts around this &lt;em&gt;“oldest and most pervasive of problems”&lt;/em&gt;, and delves into its societal context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;2--the-judicial-system-is-trying--is-it-succeeding&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/posts/2023-11-26-idevaw-is-the-judicial-system-succeeding/&quot;&gt;#2  &lt;em&gt;“The judicial system is trying – is it succeeding?”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Benjamyn Damazer in Department for Business &amp;amp; Trade reflects on the shifts he has witnessed in his long experience as a magistrate and special constable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;3--a-personal-account&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/posts/2023-11-27-idevaw-a-personal-account/&quot;&gt;#3  &lt;em&gt;“A personal account”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A SEEN member shares the powerful and moving story of her experience survivng an abusive relationship, and its ongoing impact on her life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;4-language-matters&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/posts/2023-11-28-idevaw-language-matters/&quot;&gt;#4 &lt;em&gt;“Language matters”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final post examines the recent trend towards censoring sex-based language - in particular &lt;em&gt;‘woman’&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;‘women’&lt;/em&gt; - and how this hinders efforts to end violence against women and girls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover photo&lt;/strong&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/unwomen/51737051738&quot;&gt;UN Women&lt;/a&gt; on Flickr (&lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.0/&quot;&gt;licence&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>SEEN Network</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="violence against women and girls" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">For this year’s International Day for the Elimination of Violence against Women SEEN is publishing articles today and over the next few days by four of our general members (outside our network leadership team), three of whom must remain anonymous.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Let’s Talk About Pronouns..</title>
      <link href="/posts/2023-10-18-lets-talk-about-pronouns/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Let’s Talk About Pronouns.." />
      <published>2023-10-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-10-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/lets-talk-about-pronouns</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2023-10-18-lets-talk-about-pronouns/">&lt;p&gt;On the afternoon of Monday, 9th October we approached everyone on our mailing list to ask them what they thought about practices related to the statement of pronouns in email signatures and elsewhere.  One thing was immediately clear: this was something many had been burning to talk about!  Within 3 hours we’d had close to 50 responses, and from there they continued coming in steadily until we received our 100th contribution on Friday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had such a brilliant selection of answers, we’d like to share some of them in full, alongside a general summary and some overall themes. None of the comments included are from the SEEN Steering Group (we’ll follow up with some of our opinions at a later date).  We’ve attributed contributors in the way they’ve asked us to (be that first names, initials or just anonymous). Not all of them reflect views held within SEEN’s steering group, but we wanted to publish a varied selection to promote debate and showcase the diverse perspectives on this issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;impartiality-and-the-cs-code&quot;&gt;Impartiality and the CS Code&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over three quarters of respondents highlighted what they see as the political nature of pronoun declaration and the associated ideology underpinning it (that is, belief in gender identity), with the view that this was not considered appropriate in an impartial Civil Service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some examples of these comments include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;‘It does often feel like we have to show support regardless of if we agree with the cause and in an impartial Civil Service I don’t think that’s right’ – Anonymous, Home Office&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;‘We don’t indicate our affiliation with other ideological beliefs on official emails, e.g. which political or religious ideology we support. It is unnecessary for us to do our jobs and shouldn’t be encouraged as we are public servants who should strive to be as impartial as possible on all matters.’ – Anonymous, DSTL&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;‘As civil servants we are expected to remain politically impartial, a simple rule to which I am careful to adhere. Plastering your beliefs on every email sent out does not imply a political impartiality, quite the opposite.’ – Anonymous, APHA&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;‘Senior managers should be aware of the pressure that this display of partisan support for one side of this highly political issue places on other staff members to avoid expressing non-conforming views.  Senior Civil Servants (in particular) should be scrupulously neutral, and pronoun declarations are anything but.’ – Emma, HMRC&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;‘I see no reason why I should advertise where I stand on an issue which is going to be a political hot potato in the run up to the next election.’ – Gill, MOJ&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These highlight that the adding of pronouns is considered by many to be far from a neutral step, especially when adopted by senior management.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;sexism-womens-rights-and-sex-stereotypes&quot;&gt;Sexism, women’s rights and sex stereotypes&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of our members see stating pronouns as a clear indicator of a belief in gender identity (and that this should always take precedence over sex).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over a third of respondents highlighted how they believed the pushing / attempted enforcement of gender identity beliefs was having a detrimental effect on the rights of women in the workplace. Notably, a number of women in STEM from the MOD highlighted this, including Liz and Clare. Liz said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;‘As a female in engineering, I am normally in the minority.  Although overt sexism within engineering is no way near as bad as it once was, use of pronouns highlights that I’m not in the ‘boys club’ as even now there is a general belief that engineering is not for women.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clare had this to say:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;‘I have experienced a lot of sexism throughout my career in IT and seriously considered going by my gender-neutral middle name before joining the civil service. I decided not to, but I still consider that reinforcing that someone is female exposes them to implicit bias and potential disadvantage. I also think that declaring pronouns is like declaring your star sign, if there was a climate where expressing a lack of belief in horoscopes could lead to a person being disciplined or even fired from their jobs. It’s reliant on a belief and therefore very divisive and because it’s known that some people feel so passionately about it, it’s a reminder that those people could hate you or harbour a grudge against you.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many who highlighted this angle also expressed their concerns about how encouraging the use of pronouns (and thus implying belief in gender identity) was distressing, as it implied a &lt;em&gt;‘right’&lt;/em&gt; way to be a man or a woman, tied to stereotypes of femininity/masculinity, such as &lt;em&gt;‘FF, MoJ’&lt;/em&gt; who said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;‘It promotes an ideology that if you are female who does not [reflect] social roles and stereotypes of femininity you are not a woman, [and] similarly if you are a man who rejects the social roles of masculinity then you are not a man.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;homophobialgbt-concerns&quot;&gt;Homophobia/LGBT concerns&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A number of gay and lesbian members also wrote to express that, in addition to sexism, they believed the practice was also a signpost for homophobia, such as &lt;em&gt;‘Anonymous, DWP’&lt;/em&gt; who said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;‘Lesbians are being banned from creating lesbian only events. As a gay man, listing my pronouns would feel like publicly supporting an ideology that seeks to erase gays and lesbians.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several members also expressed their concerns for those who have gender dysphoria or are struggling with issues around identity, and how the enforcement of this practice may make them uncomfortable, such as &lt;em&gt;‘Anonymous from DEFRA’&lt;/em&gt; who said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;‘I worry that encouraging people to add pronouns to emails or provide them in introductions places undue pressure on those who are still working through issues of gender dysphoria. It’s not work’s place to ‘out’ people in this way.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Others highlighted that while the practice of pronoun declaration made them uncomfortable, they still had great sympathy for those struggling with gender dysphoria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;autism-and-neurodiversity&quot;&gt;Autism and neurodiversity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A number of respondents also highlighted how people with autism or other neurodiverse conditions can struggle with preferred pronouns that do not match a person’s clearly observed sex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;‘Anonymous from Scottish Government’&lt;/em&gt; said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;‘I have always used pronouns in line with my presumption of someone’s sex except where it is clear they wish me to do something different. In that case I tend to default to using their first name repeatedly as using their preferred pronouns makes me feel complicit in a lie which is probably more awkward for me as my autism makes me very reluctant to dissemble.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While &lt;em&gt;‘Kate from DEFRA’&lt;/em&gt; commented:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;‘I also really feel for people with neurodivergence such as autism, I know a lot of folk are worried that they will accidentally misgender someone and with CS buying into the Stonewall narrative that accidentally ‘misgendering’ someone is transphobic I worry that the pronoun pushing will get these folks in trouble and potentially on a disciplinary.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;a-culture-of-fear&quot;&gt;A culture of fear&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many members highlighted the culture of fear that is created around pronoun declaration and associated beliefs about gender identity. Some described having faced direct discrimination and harassment from colleagues for refusing to participate in pronoun declarations to the extent that they are now scared or concerned when they interact with someone who has pronouns in their signature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;‘AG from UK Export Finance’&lt;/em&gt; commented:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;‘it shouldn’t be done… Additionally, the threats when pronouns aren’t included or added by those that want them to be is horrific.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;‘NM from DEFRA’&lt;/em&gt; was one of the many people who expressed the view that it led to exclusion, rather than inclusion:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;‘I feel the use of pronouns in the workplace is unnecessary and alienating to many people. It does not create an inclusive culture, but instead a culture of fear and isolation’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The use of links to external blogs that appeared to push the practice was something also raised by many, particularly &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cultureamp.com/blog/gender-pronouns-in-workplace&quot;&gt;this blog from Culture Amp&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other SEEN members have queried why blogs like the above are allowed, whereas &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.filia.org.uk/latest-news/2021/12/1/should-you-declare-your-pronouns-a-simple-guide&quot;&gt;blogs like this&lt;/a&gt; aren’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;support-for-preferred-pronouns&quot;&gt;Support for preferred pronouns&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the overwhelming response from those who disagreed with the declaration of pronouns, we also received a handful of responses which said they didn’t mind pronouns in other people’s signatures, as long as they weren’t expected to declare pronouns themselves, and as long as they could still accurately describe someone’s sex in situations where relevant.  We also received four contributions strongly in favour of use of pronouns in signatures and work profiles, if necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SEEN welcomes a plurality of views and opinions, and we also look to seek tolerance and understanding between those with differing views.  For these reasons, we have also  included two perspectives in favour of pronouns below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;‘Will from MoJ’&lt;/em&gt; had this to say:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;‘Another potential benefit of having everyone record their pronouns on their profile is that should someone feel the need to challenge whether someone was using the ‘correct’ facilities in the workplace because they were spending too much time in them themselves to mind their own business and return to work, they would be able to confirm how they identify against their profile (if they knew who the individual was) and avoid making a mistake in thinking someone was in a space they shouldn’t have been. If someone was to then bring an issue like this up to management etc to ‘deal with’ they would be able to challenge back about what they themselves were doing in the facilities for so long to be able to notice when they should only be in those facilities to do their business and then return to work, ensuring everyone is protected from those who loiter in the facilities and report them to the police if necessary.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;‘John (they/them) from MoJ’&lt;/em&gt; said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;‘I am non-binary and I include my pronouns in my email signature and it is also configured to appear in Teams via an option in my Global Address List Entry. It allows colleagues to correctly gender me in meetings without me having to state my pronouns regularly or correct them if they initially assume I use different pronouns. This makes me feel much more included, less stressed, and less awkward.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many will have sympathy for John and will choose to add pronouns for the purpose of kindness.  However,  &lt;em&gt;‘Anonymous, DESNZ’&lt;/em&gt; has a different view of the result of such intentions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;My line manager, a pleasant bloke with young children, has ‘pronouns he/him’ after his name on his email signature. Next to it, he has carefully made a hyperlink marked ‘Why do I do this?’, which links to a political blog about ‘allyship’. Whenever an email from him pops up, there also pops up the ‘pronouns he/him’. And every time his name and pronouns pop up on my screen, I get a lurch of dread in my stomach and fight back tears. My lovely, fragile young niece comes into my mind again, I feel helpless, and I can’t concentrate on my work. My teenaged, soon-to-be-adult niece, who has for years struggled with depression, anxiety and obsessive-compulsive disorder. We all helped and supported her as best as we could and hoped maturity and time would work its magic and foster her growing into the strong, healthy young woman we know she can be, just like a million awkward teenagers before her have grown up and worked it out.  Instead, she got caught up in the gender identity movement and is trapped in an alternate universe.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Now she feels ‘special’ and ‘chosen’, rather than just an awkward ugly duckling who got teased by the cool kids. Now she is praised for her ‘bravery’ by the cool kids at her new 6th Form and they tell her the rest of the world is against her and only her ‘allies’ will defend her.   […]&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;We try still to hold her as close as we can and tell her we love her just the way she is, and that she doesn’t need to pretend to be a boy for the world to accept her. We hope we can keep hold of her before she is old enough to buy cross-sex hormones or get on a surgery waiting list to have her breasts chopped off. She threatens both on her darkest days, full of weeping and panic attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Does my line manager know about girls like my niece? Every day, I think, I must talk to him. But what can I say, when our workplace policies allow and encourage ‘pronouns’? He has also been praised as ‘brave’, for being ‘a good ally to vulnerable people’. Does he know how this violent political movement of gender identity, that he so casually promotes with his ‘pronouns’, damages vulnerable girls like my niece? If he doesn’t know, why doesn’t he bother to find out? If he does know, how can he be so callous?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We would like to thank you all for your honesty and engagement in this issue.  Watch out for Part 2 (coming soon).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover by &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@magicetea?utm_content=creditCopyText&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_source=unsplash&quot;&gt;Ice Tea&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/photos/LXQeSfkY660?utm_content=creditCopyText&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_source=unsplash&quot;&gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script&gt;

    document.addEventListener(&quot;DOMContentLoaded&quot;, function () {
        const words = {
            &quot;he&quot;: &quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/He_(pronoun)&quot;,
            &quot;him&quot;: &quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/He_(pronoun)&quot;,
            &quot;his&quot;: &quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/He_(pronoun)&quot;,
            &quot;she&quot;: &quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/She_(pronoun)&quot;,
            &quot;her&quot;: &quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/She_(pronoun)&quot;,
            &quot;hers&quot;: &quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/She_(pronoun)&quot;,
            &quot;they&quot;: &quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/They&quot;,
            &quot;them&quot;: &quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/They&quot;,
            &quot;theirs&quot;: &quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/They&quot;,
            &quot;xe&quot;: &quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neopronoun&quot;,
            &quot;xem&quot;: &quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neopronoun&quot;,
            &quot;xyr&quot;: &quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neopronoun&quot;,
            &quot;ey&quot;: &quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neopronoun&quot;,
            &quot;em&quot;: &quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neopronoun&quot;,
            &quot;ze&quot;: &quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neopronoun&quot;,
            &quot;hir&quot;: &quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neopronoun&quot;,
            &quot;zir&quot;: &quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neopronoun#History&quot;,
            &quot;heer&quot;: &quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neopronoun#History&quot;,
            &quot;zir&quot;: &quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neopronoun#History&quot;
        };
        const wordElements = [];
        var w = window.innerWidth;
        var h = window.innerHeight;
        var post_image = document.getElementById('post-image');

        post_image.offsetHeight
        post_image.offsetLeft
        post_image.offsetTop

        Object.keys(words).forEach(word =&gt; {
            const wordElement = document.createElement(&quot;a&quot;);
            wordElement.className = &quot;word&quot;;
            wordElement.innerText = word;
            wordElement.href = words[word];
            wordElement.target = '_blank';
            wordElement.target = &quot;this link opens in a new window&quot;;
            wordElement.style.left = (w * 0.1) + (Math.random() * w * 0.75) + 'px';
            wordElement.style.top = post_image.offsetTop + 60 + Math.random() * post_image.clientHeight * 0.7 + 'px';
            wordElement.style.color = '#000';
            document.body.appendChild(wordElement);
            wordElements.push(wordElement);
        });

        document.addEventListener(&quot;mousemove&quot;, function (event) {
            const mouseX = event.clientX;
            const mouseY = event.clientY;

            wordElements.forEach(wordElement =&gt; {
                const rect = wordElement.getBoundingClientRect();
                const wordX = rect.left + rect.width / 2;
                const wordY = rect.top + rect.height / 2;

                const deltaX = wordX - mouseX;
                const deltaY = wordY - mouseY;
                const distance = Math.sqrt(deltaX * deltaX + deltaY * deltaY);

                if (distance &lt; 100) {
                    const angle = Math.atan2(deltaY, deltaX);
                    const newX = wordX + Math.cos(angle) * 5;
                    wordElement.style.left = newX - rect.width / 2 + &quot;px&quot;;
                    wordElement.style.top = parseInt(wordElement.style.top) + Math.sin(angle) * 5 + 'px';
                }
            });
        });
    });
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;style&gt;
    .word {
        position: absolute;
        font-size: 40px;
        font-family: seenfont, &quot;Times New Roman&quot;, Georgia, serif;
        background-color: #E9F1DB;
        padding: 20px 14px 18px 14px;
        box-shadow: -3px 7px 3px #000;
        white-space: nowrap;
        z-index: 100;
    }
&lt;/style&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>SEEN Network</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="language" />
      
        <category term="civil service" />
      
        <category term="gender stereotyping" />
      
        <category term="lesbian gay and bisexual" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">On the afternoon of Monday, 9th October we approached everyone on our mailing list to ask them what they thought about practices related to the statement of pronouns in email signatures and elsewhere. One thing was immediately clear: this was something many had been burning to talk about! Within 3 hours we’d had close to 50 responses, and from there they continued coming in steadily until we received our 100th contribution on Friday.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Manifestation, misunderstanding and ‘misgendering’</title>
      <link href="/posts/2023-10-16-manifestation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Manifestation, misunderstanding and ‘misgendering’" />
      <published>2023-10-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-10-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/manifestation</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2023-10-16-manifestation/">&lt;p&gt;A frequent area of discussion and dispute around gender critical views is whether and how much they can be expressed (or &lt;em&gt;‘manifested’&lt;/em&gt; to use the legal term) in the workplace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no simple answer to this question as each situation will turn on its own unique facts, but the caselaw is clear that there can be no blanket prohibition on the expression of gender critical views.  There might be circumstances where there is a good reason to curtail the expression of gender critical views (or indeed another protected belief).  However, any actions to curtail any protected belief cannot be taken lightly.  It must have a clear justification and must be proportionate.  A careful consideration of the facts will be needed before making any decision, to minimise legal risk and avoid creating unfairness and inequality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article focuses on what the law currently says on the expression of gender critical beliefs and highlights areas of legal ambiguity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-right-to-freedom-of-thoughts-belief-and-religion&quot;&gt;The right to freedom of thoughts, belief and religion&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The principle that lies behind the right to manifest a protected belief is the right to freedom of thought, belief and religion.  The right to express all protected beliefs in some way is enshrined in Article 9 of the European Convention on Human Rights (&lt;em&gt;“ECHR”&lt;/em&gt;), which includes the right to not only privately hold a belief, but to manifest it publicly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This right has been integrated into the Equality Act 2010 (&lt;em&gt;“Equality Act”&lt;/em&gt;) which makes ‘religion and belief’ a ‘protected characteristic’ under s.4.  The scope of ‘religion and belief’ is defined in s.10 and in caselaw and includes any religion or religious or philosophical belief&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, including a lack of belief.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-expression-of-gender-critical-beliefs&quot;&gt;The expression of gender critical beliefs&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turning now to gender critical views.  When considering if conduct restricting the expression of gender critical beliefs is lawful, there are two tests.  The first is whether gender critical views are ‘protected’ by the Equality Act.  The second is whether the precise way they are being manifested is lawful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;are-gender-critical-beliefs-protected-by-law&quot;&gt;Are gender critical beliefs protected by law?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here the law is settled, and the answer straightforward: yes they are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The test for whether a belief falls under s.10 and qualifies for protection under the Equality Act is set out in the case of &lt;em&gt;Grainger&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;  Gender critical beliefs – the belief that biological sex is real, important and immutable – qualifies for protection under s.10 following the well-known case of &lt;em&gt;Forstater&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;manifestation-of-gender-critical-beliefs&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Manifestation”&lt;/em&gt; of gender critical beliefs&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether a belief is protected is only the first limb to consider.  There is also the question of whether and how a belief can be manifested.   It is here that the law is more complex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start with the question of what ‘manifestation’ actually means.  Legally speaking, the term is broad when applied to beliefs and covers a wide range of ways in which a protected belief is expressed or made known to others.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing the law is clear on is that the right to manifest protected beliefs is extremely important.  As the case of &lt;em&gt;Higgs&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; highlighted (in relation to the Equality Act), the freedom to manifest a protected belief and to express views relating to that belief are &lt;em&gt;“essential rights in any democracy, whether or not the belief in question is popular or mainstream and even if its expression may offend”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is important and worth reflecting on, because it is sometimes suggested that the opposite applies to gender critical views.  Although the belief that biological sex is real, immutable and important is widely held, it is sometimes claimed that this is a controversial view which could cause offence to some people, and it is therefore always inappropriate to express this view in the workplace.  This is not the case.  The Courts have set a high threshold for the restriction of the manifestation of a protected belief, including gender critical beliefs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, while the expression of protected beliefs is regarded as a fundamental democratic right, it can nevertheless be lawfully curtailed in limited circumstances. To understand the circumstances in which this can happen, the first step is to return to where the concept originates, in the ECHR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both Article 9 and Article 10 of the ECHR are &lt;em&gt;qualified&lt;/em&gt; rights, which means they can be restricted provided the following three tests are met.  The restriction in question must be:
prescribed by law;
in the pursuit of a &lt;em&gt;legitimate&lt;/em&gt; aim; and,
necessary in a democratic society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any interference must also be &lt;em&gt;proportionate&lt;/em&gt; (see endnote &lt;a href=&quot;#bank-mellat-v-hmt-2013-uksc-39&quot;&gt;Bank Mellat v HMT 2013&lt;/a&gt;).  The principles to be applied in deciding whether an interference is ‘proportionate’ are set out in detail in the Employment Appeals Tribunal case of &lt;em&gt;Higgs&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;#higgs-v-farmores-school-2023-eat-89&quot;&gt;seen endnote&lt;/a&gt;), in which the Tribunal said that there are a number of tests that need to be met, and that serious thought and consideration should be given to all these factors by any organisation seeking to introduce a policy restricting the manifestation of belief.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is, in short, not a decision to take lightly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-about-some-practical-advice-for-example-on-issues-such-as-misgendering&quot;&gt;What about some practical advice, for example on issues such as misgendering?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The law remains big on principles and tests, and relatively sparse on precise examples, although more cases are slowly testing the parameters of gender critical beliefs and their expression.  However, the Courts have given some indication of the type of conduct that would be a permissible manifestation of a protected belief and what would not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;Forstater&lt;/em&gt;, the Employment Appeal Tribunal (&lt;em&gt;“EAT”&lt;/em&gt;) was clear that &lt;strong&gt;there cannot be a blanket ban on the expression of gender critical beliefs&lt;/strong&gt; (or indeed any protected belief).   We have highlighted this, because there continue to be instances where it is suggested that gender critical beliefs simply don’t have an active and visible place in the workplace.  The law states that they do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite some claims to the contrary, the EAT in the case of &lt;em&gt;Forstater&lt;/em&gt; did not find that it is never okay to misgender in the workplace.  In fact, the EAT concluded that referring to a person by their biological sex, rather than their preferred gender, &lt;em&gt;would &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; necessarily constitute conduct that could justifiably be curtailed&lt;/em&gt;.  Whether it was acceptable or not would depend entirely on the circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Equally importantly, &lt;em&gt;the fact that others might be offended by gender critical views&lt;/em&gt; is entirely subjective and does not, in itself, give rise to any justification to restrict the expression of that belief.  The EAT was very clear that the Claimant (Maya Forstater) could &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; be required to refer to a transwoman as a woman (or face accusations of harassment), as &lt;em&gt;this would constitute a blanket ban on the expression of her belief which could not possibly be proportionate&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:6&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This said, everyone in the workplace (whatever their protected beliefs, or lack thereof) are subject to the same prohibitions on discrimination, victimisation and harassment under the Equality Act.   It is important to state that &lt;em&gt;deliberate and gratuitous ‘misgendering’&lt;/em&gt; (referring to a transgender person as their biological sex, or conversely – and equally – referring to a gender critical person or a person who does not believe in gender identity theory as &lt;em&gt;‘cis’&lt;/em&gt;) &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; constitute harassment.  The same is likely to be true of attempts to exert pressure on colleagues to convert to a particular protected belief&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:7&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:7&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, something that would be as true for those with gender critical beliefs as those who believe passionately in ideas around gender identity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Forstater&lt;/em&gt; is the best-known case on manifestation of gender critical beliefs, but further guidance can be found in two other subsequent cases, Mackareth&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:8&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:8&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and Fahmy&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:9&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:9&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.  More are likely to follow, as case law is developing on this point.  In &lt;em&gt;Fahmy&lt;/em&gt;, the Employment Tribunal found that an employee had been subjected to harassment for holding and expressing gender critical beliefs at work. Other employees had described the Claimant’s gender critical views as &lt;em&gt;“anti-trans”&lt;/em&gt; and compared her beliefs to racism, sexism and other forms of bigotry and the Employment Tribunal found that this response to the Claimant’s gender critical beliefs &lt;em&gt;“went beyond the reasonable expression of a personal opinion in terms which were highly derogatory”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both gender critical beliefs and their manifestation are protected by the law, which means that any limitation imposed on the way in which gender critical views can be manifested must be prescribed by law and necessary for the protection of the rights of others (and meet the additional tests, such as proportionality).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst the law is now settled on whether gender critical beliefs are protected, the question on how far they can be expressed or manifest, remains complex and nuanced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each situation turns on its individual facts and there are no blanket prohibitions or impunities as to exactly how a person may manifest gender critical beliefs or when curtailments will be justified.  However, two things are clear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, anyone who suggests that gender critical beliefs can be held but should not be manifested in the workplace (for whatever reason) is just wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, there is no hierarchy of rights or protected characteristics.  Employers should not make the mistake of prioritising the interests, feelings or perspectives of one protected group or set of beliefs over another, for &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; reason.  This is also true of decisions on when and how protected beliefs can be manifested.  Not only is this a fundamental part of a democratic society, it is essential in an inclusive, diverse and politically impartial Civil Service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover photo by &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@lunarts?utm_content=creditCopyText&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_source=unsplash&quot;&gt;Volodymyr Hryshchenko&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/photos/V5vqWC9gyEU?utm_content=creditCopyText&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_source=unsplash&quot;&gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;•·················•·················•&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;end-notes&quot;&gt;END NOTES&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;bank-mellat-v-hmt-2013-uksc-39&quot;&gt;Bank Mellat v HMT [2013] UKSC 39&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bailii.org/uk/cases/UKSC/2013/39.html&quot;&gt;this case&lt;/a&gt; the Supreme Court identified the correct test for proportionality in this context as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is the objective of the measure sufficiently important to justify the limitation of a protected right?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is the measure rationally connected to the objective?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Could a less intrusive measure have been used without unacceptably compromising the achievement of the objective?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Whether, balancing the severity of the measure’s effects on the rights of the persons to whom it applies against the importance of the objective, to the extent that the measure will contribute to its achievement, the former outweighs the latter.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;higgs-v-farmores-school-2023-eat-89&quot;&gt;Higgs v Farmore’s School [2023] EAT 89&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/employment-appeal-tribunal-decisions/mrs-kristie-higgs-v-1-farmors-school-2-archbishops-council-of-the-church-of-england-2023-eat-89-eat-89&quot;&gt;This case&lt;/a&gt; concerned a Christian employee who had been suspended and subsequently dismissed for gross misconduct by her employer (a school) because she had posted on social media about her views on ‘gender fluidity’ and same sex marriage.  The ET had found that the Claimant had not been discriminated against or harassed because of her protected belief, as there was not a sufficient nexus between her belief and the way in which she had manifested them. On appeal, the EAT found that the ET had taken the wrong approach and has remitted the case back to the ET for a proper determination of whether the Claimant’s dismissal was because of the manifestation of her protected belief or because of a justified objection to the way in which her belief was manifested, i.e. was the dismissal a proportionate response to the manifestation of a protected belief. (At the time of writing the case is ongoing).  In reaching its decision the EAT followed the proportionality test set out in Mellat, and at para 94 set out the following principles to be considered when considering proportionality:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;“foundational nature of the rights”&lt;/em&gt; must be recognised. The freedom to manifest a protected belief and to express views relating to that belief are &lt;em&gt;“essential rights in any democracy, whether or not the belief in question is popular or mainstream and even if its expression may offend”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Where the restriction of a protected belief is justified, the curtailment is due to the objectionable manner of the manifestation, and not the exercise of the right to hold/manifest a protected belief.  In other words, you cannot restrict the right to hold a protected belief, nor to express it.  The only expressions or manifestations that can be restricted are where those manifestations that are objectionable.  (More on what makes a manifestation ‘objectionable’ below).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The question of whether a limitation on the manifestation of a protected belief is justified will always be context-specific and therefore a proportionality assessment must pay careful attention to the individual facts of a case.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The following questions must then be asked:
    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;is the objective the employer seeks to achieve is sufficiently important to justify the limitation of the right in question;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;is the limitation rationally connected to that objective;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;could a less intrusive limitation be imposed without undermining the achievement of the objective in question; and&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;when balancing the severity of the limitation on the rights of the worker concerned against the importance of the objective, does the former outweighs the latter.
 All of these tests must be satisfied if the restriction is to be considered proportionate.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Regard should be had to:
    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;the content of the manifestation;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;the tone used;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;the extent of the manifestation;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;the worker’s understanding of the likely audience;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;the extent and nature of the intrusion on the rights of others, and any consequential impact on the employer’s ability to run its business;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;whether the worker has made clear that the views expressed are personal, or whether they might be seen as representing the views of the employer, and whether that might present a reputational risk;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;whether there is a potential power imbalance given the nature of the worker’s position or role and that of those whose rights are intruded upon;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;the nature of the employer’s business, in particular where there is a potential impact on vulnerable service users or clients;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;whether the limitation imposed is the least intrusive measure open to the employer.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;•·················•·················•&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;style&gt;
.post-full-content {
    background: #ffffffbb !important;
}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;It has been found that philosophical belief can have just as much importance to a person’s life as a religious belief, see &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/employment-appeal-tribunal-decisions/the-general-municipal-and-boilermakers-union-v-mr-keith-henderson-ukeat-0073-14-dm&quot;&gt;General Municipal and Boilermakers Union v Henderson UKEAT/0073/14&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bailii.org/uk/cases/UKEAT/2009/0219_09_0311.html&quot;&gt;Grainger plc and others v Nicholson [2010] IRLR 4&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/employment-appeal-tribunal-decisions/maya-forstater-v-cgd-europe-and-others-ukeat-slash-0105-slash-20-slash-joj&quot;&gt;Forstater v CGD Europe and Others: UKEAT/0105/20/JOJ&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;For conduct to constitute the manifestation of a protected belief, there must be a sufficiently close and direct nexus between the conduct and the underlying belief, though the conduct need not be a mandatory requirement of an established religion for it to qualify (see &lt;a href=&quot;https://hudoc.echr.coe.int/fre#%7B%22itemid%22:%5B%22002-7391%22%5D%7D&quot;&gt;Eweida and others v UK&lt;/a&gt;). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/employment-appeal-tribunal-decisions/mrs-kristie-higgs-v-1-farmors-school-2-archbishops-council-of-the-church-of-england-2023-eat-89-eat-89&quot;&gt;Higgs v Farmore’s School [2023] EAT 89&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The mistake made by the ET in Forstater was to fail to apply the proportionality test.  This led them to (wrongly) conclude that any manifestation of her belief could potentially constitute harassment for the purposes of s.26 of the Equality Act, meaning that there were no circumstances where she could refer to a person by their biological sex and not their preferred gender in all circumstances.  See Forstater para 103-104. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:6&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:7&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;See Wasteney v East London NHS Foundation [2016] 4 WLUK 120). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:7&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:8&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;For instance, in Mackereth the EAT found that the ET had wrongly assumed that a failure to use a service user’s chosen pronoun would in all cases give rise to unlawful discrimination or harassment. Once again it was reiterated: the expression of a protected belief does not in of itself constitute discrimination, victimisation or harassment, and does not of itself trigger justifiable limitations on the expression of that belief. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:8&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:9&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/employment-tribunal-decisions/ms-d-fahmy-v-arts-council-england-6000042-slash-2022&quot;&gt;Fahmy v Arts Council England 2023 WL 04315316&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:9&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>SEEN Network</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="language" />
      
        <category term="diversity of belief" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">A frequent area of discussion and dispute around gender critical views is whether and how much they can be expressed (or ‘manifested’ to use the legal term) in the workplace.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Fahmy v Arts Council England tribunal judgment</title>
      <link href="/posts/2023-09-09-the-fahmy-v-arts-council-england-tribunal-judgment/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Fahmy v Arts Council England tribunal judgment" />
      <published>2023-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/the-fahmy-v-arts-council-england-tribunal-judgment</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2023-09-09-the-fahmy-v-arts-council-england-tribunal-judgment/">&lt;h3 id=&quot;background&quot;&gt;Background&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 21 June 2023, Ms Fahmy won an important &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/employment-tribunal-decisions/ms-d-fahmy-v-arts-council-england-6000042-slash-2022&quot;&gt;employment tribunal&lt;/a&gt; (ET) decision against her former employer, Arts Council England (ACE), the first ET case relating to harassment for gender critical beliefs. ACE is an executive non-departmental public body, and also a registered charity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ms Fahmy was a long-standing employee of ACE and had attended an internal Teams meeting where hostile comments were made about people who hold gender critical beliefs. These comments were made during a work discussion about the award (and removal) of an ACE grant to &lt;a href=&quot;https://lgballiance.org.uk/&quot;&gt;LGB Alliance&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the meeting, Ms Fahmy made comments which made it clear that she holds gender critical beliefs. Following the hostile meeting some of her colleagues circulated a petition with further hostile and intimidating comments which were aimed at all gender critical people, calling them &lt;em&gt;“openly discriminatory transphobic staff”&lt;/em&gt;, and comparing them to racists, while also calling supporters of LGB Alliance &lt;em&gt;“neo-nazis, homophobes and Islamophobes”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In response Ms Fahmy raised a Dignity at Work complaint with ACE asserting that she had been harassed during the meeting. Her internal complaint was not upheld and Ms Fahmy was, wrongly, not given the right to appeal the decision.  Given the circumstances, she felt she could no longer work for ACE and resigned before the final ET hearing took place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a unanimous judgment, the Leeds Employment Tribunal ruled that Ms Fahmy was subjected to harassment for her gender critical beliefs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;treatment-of-gender-critical-beliefs-in-the-public-sector&quot;&gt;Treatment of gender critical beliefs in the public sector.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Comments made by ACE staff members in chat forums were found to have crossed the threshold for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.acas.org.uk/discrimination-and-the-law/harassment&quot;&gt;harassment&lt;/a&gt; when they wrote:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“It is clear that there are members of our own organisation who are happy to be vocally anti-trans and “gender critical”. We shouldn’t have to put up with this any more than we would racist or sexist behaviour. It’s time to stamp out bigotry in the Arts Council in general and that change is to come from the top down and filtered through all departments PS… The mistake imho has come from the lack of clear condemnation of a transphobic organisation and no action being taken against the so-called “gender critical” anonymous who are openly expressing their distaste at the funding being? withdrawn. Much like how our recent antiracism training has illustrated there is an ongoing problem with racism in our ranks that needs to be challenged, this cancer needs to be removed from our organisation. Hatred of others for their differences should not be tolerated.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“… It’s extremely disappointing to see people trying to defend them [LGB Alliance] here of all places”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Tribunal found that the tone and content of these individuals’ emails and comments &lt;em&gt;“went beyond the reasonable expression of a personal opinion in terms which were highly derogatory”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many civil servants will have read and heard similar comments in their own workplace in blogs, forums, training sessions and meetings. SEEN received numerous examples of this sort of language and behaviour in response to our March 2023 Inclusion Survey. 70% of respondents reported that they have either witnessed/experienced bullying, harassment or discrimination (BHD) against staff for having gender critical views or do not feel that their workplace offers a sufficiently respectful and tolerant environment to voice a view that does not align with the belief in gender identity.  38% of respondents reported having themselves witnessed or experienced BHD against staff for having gender critical views (15% didn’t know or preferred not to say).  Of the 47% (142) of respondents that had not witnessed or experienced BHD themselves, only 45% (65) felt their workplace &lt;strong&gt;does&lt;/strong&gt; offer a sufficiently respectful and tolerant environment to voice a view that does not align with the belief in gender identity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This judgment suggests that they are right to be concerned, especially when managers and senior leaders themselves use similar language, or endorse (or ignore) such behaviour by their staff. In Ms Fahmy’s case, Simon Mellor, the ACE Deputy Chief Executive expressed the view in a staff meeting that LGB Alliance &lt;em&gt;“has a history of anti-trans activity”&lt;/em&gt;.  In the words of the judgment, Mellor’s comments &lt;em&gt;“opened the door, for the subsequent petition and comments within that petition. Whether intended or not, it led to the petition”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-the-fahmy-judgment-means&quot;&gt;What the Fahmy judgment means&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Fahmy judgment is not an appeal judgment, and so is therefore not in itself binding.  While it does not introduce any new principles of law it does give an important indication of the kind of comments and conduct likely to constitute bullying and harassment in the workplace of those with the protected characteristic of holding gender critical beliefs.  In this case, such comments included likening gender critical views to hate, transphobia or bigotry, and the suggestion that such lawful views should or will not be tolerated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to note that, although the ACE staff who made the derogatory comments were subsequently disciplined, this did not prevent Ms Fahmy’s claim from succeeding.  Employers have a responsibility to create workplace cultures where such harassment is understood to be unacceptable.   Indeed, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2010/15/section/109&quot;&gt;section 109 of the Equality Act&lt;/a&gt; makes employers liable for what their staff do, unless they have taken reasonable steps to prevent it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is perhaps why the Tribunal was also critical of the ACE Deputy Chief Executive Simon Mellor.  Despite finding that the views he expressed didn’t meet the threshold for harassment, the Tribunal &lt;em&gt;“doubted the wisdom of Simon Mellor providing his personal opinions during a meeting which was available to all members of staff”&lt;/em&gt; and found that it was inappropriate for Mellor to have expressed his personal views and solidarity with one side of the debate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In upholding Ms Fahmy’s claim, the Tribunal found that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The respondent was aware this was a contentious issue. The respondent was aware of the need to update its policies and provide appropriate training with regard to the issue of belief but the Tribunal is not satisfied that the respondent has taken all reasonable steps as required in section 109(4) to prevent its employees from harassing someone with the claimant’s protected characteristic.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is, therefore, incumbent on an employer who knows (or ought to know) that there is contention between competing beliefs held by its staff to ensure that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;its policies reflect the law as it is;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;that training is available to staff, in particular staff who may have to deal with grievances relating to these matters; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to ensure that workplace network activity is conducted with due regard to the protected characteristic of belief.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is also important to note that any approach which seeks to suppress, exclude or prioritise one protected belief over another on the basis that this aligns with organisational values (e.g. purported ‘inclusivity’) or in order to avoid perceived controversy, is unlikely to be found to be lawful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;With thanks from SEEN to one of our members, who kindly summarised the above case for use in our blog.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover image&lt;/strong&gt;: Equality law by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nyphotographic.com/&quot;&gt;Nick Youngson&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a rel=&quot;license&quot; href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/&quot;&gt;CC BY-SA 3.0&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://pix4free.org/&quot;&gt;Pix4free&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>SEEN Network</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="civil service" />
      
        <category term="equality act 2010" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Background</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Protected Characteristics</title>
      <link href="/posts/2023-07-04-the-protected-characteristics-a-reminder/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Protected Characteristics" />
      <published>2023-07-04T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-07-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/the-protected-characteristics-a-reminder</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2023-07-04-the-protected-characteristics-a-reminder/">&lt;p&gt;We often come across training and guidance that makes reference to the protected characteristics, and it’s really important that this is presented correctly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following is a list of all the characteristics defined as ‘protected characteristics’ by the Equality Act 2010:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;age&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;disability&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;gender reassignment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;marriage and civil partnership&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;pregnancy and maternity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;race&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;religion or belief&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;sex (being male or female)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;sexual orientation (being attracted to people of the opposite sex, the same sex or both)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is against the law to discriminate against someone in the workplace because of a protected characteristic, so it is very important to be clear as to which characteristics are protected and to understand what they cover.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of us will be protected by at least four, maybe more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did you know that the protected characteristic of &lt;em&gt;‘religion or belief’&lt;/em&gt; also covers lack of belief (e.g. our colleagues who are Humanist or atheist)?  For example, you cannot be compelled to demonstrate your adherence or support for a belief system you do not share.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Religion or belief&lt;/em&gt; also not only covers religious beliefs (such as those held by our colleagues who are Christian, Muslim, or another faith), it also covers philosophical and non-religious ethical positions (such as following a vegan diet and lifestyle, or being gender critical).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Religion or belief&lt;/em&gt; may also cover beliefs about gender and gender identity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Equality Act, a person has the protected characteristic of &lt;em&gt;gender reassignment&lt;/em&gt; if the person is proposing to undergo, is undergoing or has undergone a process (or part of a process) for the purpose of reassigning the person’s sex by changing physiological or other attributes of sex.  This may also cover some issues relating to gender or gender identity.  It is described in more detail on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.equalityhumanrights.com/en/advice-and-guidance/gender-reassignment-discrimination&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Equality and Human Rights Commission&lt;/em&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, we have also seen internal training which incorrectly states the protected characteristics also include one or more of the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;gender&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;gender expression&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;gender identity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None of these are listed as protected characteristics, which are the nine listed at the start of this post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you come across any training or advice which gets this wrong, please do &lt;a href=&quot;/contact/&quot;&gt;let us know&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover image&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Books-book-pages-read-literature-159866.jpg&quot;&gt;Creative Commons&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>SEEN Network</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="equality act 2010" />
      
        <category term="equality" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">We often come across training and guidance that makes reference to the protected characteristics, and it’s really important that this is presented correctly.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Understanding our sex-based rights and protections at work</title>
      <link href="/posts/2023-02-17-understanding-our-sex-based-rights-and-protections-at-work/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Understanding our sex-based rights and protections at work" />
      <published>2023-02-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-02-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/understanding-our-sex-based-rights-and-protections-at-work</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2023-02-17-understanding-our-sex-based-rights-and-protections-at-work/">&lt;p&gt;We hear often from colleagues concerned that HR teams, management and staff training providers have made mistakes when they talk about equality law, and especially about sex-based rights and protections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve been given examples of mistakes in relation to women’s issues, including pregnancy and maternity.  Many of our members are lesbian, gay or bisexual and have told us their concerns regarding misleading language about sexual orientation.  Another common error we have seen is where policies or training incorrectly use the words ‘gender’ or ‘gender identity’ when they actually mean ‘sex’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sex-based rights and protections matter for everyone, so it’s important that everyone gets the law and language correct, or rights can be put at risk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone wants to get the law right, so if you find confusing or misleading workplace policies, staff training or communications, it’s a good idea to highlight these so that HR can check and, if necessary, make corrections.  In particular, when any policy or communication concerns the Equality Act 2010, the correct legal language should be used, including the correct names of all the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.equalityhumanrights.com/en/equality-act/protected-characteristics&quot;&gt;nine protected characteristics&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don’t need to be an expert to reach out to your HR team and management if you think something has gone wrong in a workplace policy, training or communication. Any member of staff can set out concerns and ask them for a chat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you belong to a union, you can also tell your union what has happened and ask them to help you, including to talk to your HR team or management.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And don’t forget that union branch annual general meetings and national conferences are coming up very soon. Union members make union policies at these meetings, so if there is a policy you care about, make sure you take part and make your voice count.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Staff networks like SEEN are brilliant for information, support and friendship between colleagues, but only unions have an official right to be consulted by employers and only unions can provide you with representation and legal advice. So if you’re not already a member of a union, why not join one and ask them what they are doing to improve sex equality and equity in the civil service and protect sex-based rights?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please do also continue to &lt;a href=&quot;/contact/&quot;&gt;share your experiences with us&lt;/a&gt; so that we can better understand what support you need. We love to hear from you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can find clear information about sex-based rights, protections and equality and human rights law, including the Equality Act 2010 (and in particular the public sector equality duty (PSED), on the website of the Equality and Human Rights Commission (EHRC), the UK’s independent watchdog on equality and human rights law. Here are some useful links:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.equalityhumanrights.com/en&quot;&gt;EHRC homepage&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.equalityhumanrights.com/en/equality-act/equality-act-2010&quot;&gt;Equality Act 2010&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.equalityhumanrights.com/en/equality-act/know-your-rights&quot;&gt;Equality Act - know your rights&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.equalityhumanrights.com/en/advice-and-guidance/public-sector-equality-duty&quot;&gt;Public sector equality duty&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.equalityhumanrights.com/en/equality-act/protected-characteristics&quot;&gt;Protected characteristics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.equalityhumanrights.com/en/advice-and-guidance/sex-discrimination&quot;&gt;Sex discrimination&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.equalityhumanrights.com/en/our-work/managing-pregnancy-and-maternity-workplace&quot;&gt;Managing pregnancy and maternity workplace&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.equalityhumanrights.com/en/advice-and-guidance/sexual-orientation-discrimination&quot;&gt;Sexual orientation discrimination&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Other links:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/public-sector-equality-duty&quot;&gt;Ministry of Justice - Public Sector Equality Duty&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/letter-to-ministers-on-public-sector-equality-duty-assessments/letter-to-ministers-on-public-sector-equality-duty-assessments&quot;&gt;Minister for Equalities letter of 10 December 2021 to ministers on Public Sector Equality Duty assessments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>SEEN Network</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="civil service" />
      
        <category term="equality act 2010" />
      
        <category term="sex based rights" />
      
        <category term="ehrc" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">We hear often from colleagues concerned that HR teams, management and staff training providers have made mistakes when they talk about equality law, and especially about sex-based rights and protections.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Zero tolerance for Female Genital Mutilation</title>
      <link href="/posts/2023-02-06-zero-tolerance-for-fgm/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Zero tolerance for Female Genital Mutilation" />
      <published>2023-02-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-02-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/zero-tolerance-for-fgm</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2023-02-06-zero-tolerance-for-fgm/">&lt;p&gt;6th February is the UN’s International Day of Zero Tolerance for Female Genital Mutilation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Female genital mutilation (FGM) refers to all procedures involving cutting a girl or woman’s genitals to mark or remove some or all her external genitalia, including her clitoris, or to stitch her vaginal opening together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite being internationally recognized as an extreme human rights violation against women and girls, it is estimated that at least 200 million girls and women worldwide have suffered FGM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FGM is one of many harmful practices against girls and women which are rooted in deep inequality between the sexes and discrimination against females because of their bodies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FGM is not supported by any religious doctrine, but evolved as a social convention amongst some cultures as a direct way to control girls’ and women’s sexuality. FGM is also likely to destroy a woman’s capacity for sexual pleasure, which is also the intention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FGM has reduced but still persists across the world, particularly but not only in Africa, Asia and the Middle East. Many diaspora communities have continued to practice FGM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FGM can cause severe bleeding and death. If the girl survives, she is likely to suffer physical and mental trauma for her lifetime, including difficulty and pain in urinating and menstruating and in having sex. A girl or woman who has undergone FGM has a much increased risk of being seriously injured or dying during childbirth, and of her baby dying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A minority of FGM is now done under medical supervision, which some people believe to be safer and more acceptable. However, the World Health Organization strongly urges healthcare providers not to perform FGM in any circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FGM has been illegal across the whole UK since 1985 and it’s also now illegal for a girl to be taken outside of the UK to be subjected to FGM. However, some UK girls are still at risk from FGM. Government agencies, schools and charities across the UK work to identify and safeguard girls who may be at risk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Girls and women who have undergone FGM are often in pain  and ashamed and need support to seek help. &lt;strong&gt;Remember that you are not alone.&lt;/strong&gt; There are women doctors and nurses across the UK who will give you expert care for your medical and psychological health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are links to the sources for the information above. You can also use these sources to learn more and get support for yourself or a girl or woman you know who may be at risk of FGM or who has suffered from FGM:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.unicef.org/protection/female-genital-mutilation&quot;&gt;https://www.unicef.org/protection/female-genital-mutilation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/female-genital-mutilation-resource-pack/female-genital-mutilation-resource-pack&quot;&gt;https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/female-genital-mutilation-resource-pack/female-genital-mutilation-resource-pack&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.saverauk.co.uk/information-support/about-savera-uk/&quot;&gt;https://www.saverauk.co.uk/information-support/about-savera-uk/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.filia.org.uk/latest-news/2020/11/27/hibo-wardere-one-womans-fight-against-fgm&quot;&gt;https://www.filia.org.uk/latest-news/2020/11/27/hibo-wardere-one-womans-fight-against-fgm&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/female-genital-mutilation&quot;&gt;https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/female-genital-mutilation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover image:&lt;/strong&gt;  “International Day for zero tolerance against Female Genital Mutilation” by ALDE Group is licensed under CC BY-ND 2.0. To view a copy of this license, visit https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.0/?ref=openverse.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>SEEN Network</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="violence against women and girls" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">6th February is the UN’s International Day of Zero Tolerance for Female Genital Mutilation.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">On tolerance</title>
      <link href="/posts/2022-11-22-on-tolerance/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On tolerance" />
      <published>2022-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2022-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/on-tolerance</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2022-11-22-on-tolerance/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;reflecting-society&quot;&gt;Reflecting society&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Civil Service has always been a microcosm of British society. At first it was largely white and male, along with the other public and private institutions of the day. But with each new generation the bureaucracy adapted to changing societal norms and became gradually more diverse and representative, with some of the most significant changes happening within our lifetimes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It hasn't been a smooth journey. Progress often mirrors the build-up and release of pressures in tectonic shifts. Legislative and political developments like the Sex Discrimination Act 1975, sexual offences law changes of 1967, 2000 and 2003 (decriminalising homosexuality), the Data Protection Acts of 1984 and 1998, the Stephen Lawrence report in 1999, and the Freedom of Information Act 2000, and others all played important roles in bringing about much needed changes. By the turn of the millennium, all government departments were striving to attain Investors in People accreditation - the then-gold standard for inclusive working practices. Pluralism and tolerance were becoming dominant Civil Service values. Departmental staff networks sprang up everywhere, and could be found representing their organisations at Glastonbury and Pride. There were many issues that needed to be addressed, but the zeitgeist felt new and positive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In recent years something has changed. In 2019 a British woman lost her job for expressing her belief in the importance and nature of biological sex&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, a view never recorded in our history as controversial. Last year a university professor resigned following sustained abuse and harassment by her colleagues and students for having written a book that explored the same philosophical issues&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Stating what many (possibly most) people consider to be basic facts of life is now forbidden in many workplaces, sometimes by human resources codes, but more often by a chilling culture that suppresses substantive discussion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a matter of public debate that we may be witnessing the emergence of a new form of intolerance linked to changing attitudes towards freedom of expression&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. The trend is illustrated in the context of our universities by a survey of UK student opinion in May 2022&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, which found significant increases over the past 6 years in demands for protections from feeling threatened and for banning speakers that cause offence. It seems to mirror a similar shift in attitudes in the US&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;our-launch&quot;&gt;Our launch&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our network celebrates the drive towards greater equality, pluralism and respect for difference over recent decades, and in particular the more tolerant society that this has heralded. We are concerned that this progress is now under threat. Seeing some of the reactions to the launch of SEEN as an officially recognised cross-government staff network has made it clear to us that the Civil Service is not immune to this trend away from mutual tolerance. We have attracted significant criticism and hostility purely for announcing ourselves, and some colleagues have openly discussed getting us banned. Yet our network website (our only communication to date) makes clear our commitments to protection of everyone’s rights, encouraging a diversity of voices, and open and respectful dialogue and tolerance between those with differing beliefs and experiences, as well as the need to respect colleagues’ beliefs (or lack thereof). Some perhaps genuinely believe these are empty words, but they are not. We are the same people you have always worked alongside with mutual respect, and these values are in our DNA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The criticism of SEEN’s launch - which contrasts starkly with the hundreds of supportive messages and membership information requests we have received privately - has almost all focused on the nature of &lt;a href=&quot;/faq/#what-are-seens-values&quot;&gt;our core belief&lt;/a&gt;. It is a belief that our courts have ruled to be “worthy of respect in a democratic society” (and so holds the status of a protected belief under the Equality Act), and is shared by people from all backgrounds, of all political leanings, and by theist, atheist and agnostic alike. This hostile reaction to us has only strengthened our view that, for some in our society, their perceived needs have come to demand the silencing of those who hold beliefs they feel threatened by, regardless of the holders’ stated commitments to tolerance and pluralism. For this reason we would like to use our first blog article to consider tolerance, and why it matters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-paradox-of-tolerance&quot;&gt;The paradox of tolerance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One SEEN-critical comment in particular has stood out from the others by articulating an ostensible justification for silencing us. It referenced a popular philosophical maxim known as the “paradox of tolerance”, attributed to the philosopher Karl Popper, which in its simplest terms states that tolerance without limit will result in intolerance. The specific example Popper gave of those views which should be excluded because of their fundamental intolerance of others was Nazism (which courts have ruled gender critical belief “does not get anywhere near to approaching”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:6&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commonly omitted from such citations of the paradox is the fact that Popper went on to say:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I do not imply, for instance, that we should always suppress the utterance of intolerant philosophies; as long as we can counter them by rational argument and keep them in check by public opinion, suppression would certainly be most unwise. But we should claim the right to suppress them if necessary even by force; for it may easily turn out that they are not prepared to meet us on the level of rational argument, but begin by denouncing all argument &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:7&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:7&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Popper was speaking of philosophies inclined to meet rational argument with “fists or pistols”. A lucid reading of his words makes clear that what SEEN has said does not reflect anything like such a philosophy, let alone merit suppression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, other philosophers like Raphael Cohen-Almagor&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:8&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:8&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; have gone further to argue (again using the example of Nazism) that psychological harm is equal to physical harm. Ideas that cause others distress can, therefore, be legitimately restricted. Some of our critics have made this argument against us, claiming that even a statement of our core belief causes emotional harm and should be withdrawn or taken down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From our perspective there are two problems with this argument. The first is that it ignores the fact that the law protects the reasonable expression&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:9&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:9&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; of a protected religion or belief. The second is this: who gets to decide when a particular speaker, group or people with a particular belief pose a risk of psychological harm so great that they should be kept silent? And how can others be sure the decision is fair? Under Cohen-Almagor’s proposed scenario, judgements on what is acceptable speech seem far more likely to emerge not through consensus but through the dominance of certain perspectives over others. Hence in the context of a policy to prioritise emotional ‘safety’, those holding beliefs perceived as threatening are likely to be disproportionately affected, regardless of their actual commitment to pluralism and tolerance. And the evidence suggests the notion of emotional safety is not impartial: support in our universities for banning speakers from our main political parties is very unequal&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:10&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:10&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of the potential for causing harm, we invite readers to contrast our commitment to pluralism and tolerance with the open hostility we have received from some of our colleagues, which has caused intense distress and anxiety for some members of SEEN. We call upon colleagues who may disagree with our reasonably expressed viewpoints to express their disagreement with respect and professionalism, to tolerate different beliefs, and to call out the use of hostile language. Everyone deserves to be treated with respect and to be able to do their jobs free from bullying, harasment and discrimination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tolerance-in-a-pluralist-society&quot;&gt;Tolerance in a pluralist society&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We do not have to share beliefs in order to tolerate them. We live in a pluralist and diverse society. The beauty of living in a pluralist democracy is that we tolerate and indeed celebrate differences, and we manage to get along, including with those whose beliefs we do not share. A pluralist society allows us all to be free to express our beliefs, within the bounds of the law. For such a society to thrive, as Popper recognised, there must be limits to tolerance. However, these limits are not defined by those who shout the loudest, but ultimately by what is lawful. The Equality Act 2010 provides a legal framework to prevent people acting on their prejudices or disagreements in a way that results in discriminatory treatment of others. It sets out the nine characteristics that are protected by the law&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:11&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:11&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, including the protected characteristic of religion or belief, which is extended to beliefs that must, amongst other criteria, “be worthy of respect in a democratic society, be not incompatible with human dignity and not conflict with the fundamental rights of others”. Harassment of and discrimination against those holding and respectfully expressing such beliefs are examples of genuine intolerance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tolerance-and-expression-within-the-civil-service&quot;&gt;Tolerance and expression within the Civil Service&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Civil Servants we are bound by the Civil Service Code which requires political neutrality. So it is not appropriate for us to express views on matters of political controversy at work; we abide by that restriction and expect others to do likewise. We therefore only assert our right for our views to be heard with tolerance in respect of matters relevant to the workplace. Sometimes it will be necessary to explain the underlying beliefs in order to exercise our rights at work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2022 Civil Service Diversity and Inclusion Strategy&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:12&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:12&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; makes a specific commitment to challenging groupthink and inspiring a greater diversity of thinking. SEEN is committed to working to ensure that departmental policies for human resources and diversity and inclusion, as well as their implementation, reflect this commitment. If you support our &lt;a href=&quot;/faq/#what-is-seens-mission&quot;&gt;mission and values&lt;/a&gt; consider &lt;a href=&quot;/join/&quot;&gt;joining us&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Cover image: &lt;a href=&quot;https://pixabay.com/photos/exhibition-visitors-gallery-viewer-2944064/&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://pixabay.com/service/terms/&quot;&gt;licence&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-57426579&quot;&gt;https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-57426579&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-england-sussex-59084446&quot;&gt;https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-england-sussex-59084446&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/minister-donelan-addresses-policy-exchange&quot;&gt;https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/minister-donelan-addresses-policy-exchange&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hepi.ac.uk/2022/06/23/you-cant-say-that-new-polling-shows-students-want-more-controls-on-free-expression/&quot;&gt;https://www.hepi.ac.uk/2022/06/23/you-cant-say-that-new-polling-shows-students-want-more-controls-on-free-expression/&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2015/09/the-coddling-of-the-american-mind/399356/&quot;&gt;https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2015/09/the-coddling-of-the-american-mind/399356/&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://assets.publishing.service.gov.uk/media/60c1cce1d3bf7f4bd9814e39/Maya_Forstater_v_CGD_Europe_and_others_UKEAT0105_20_JOJ.pdf&quot;&gt;https://assets.publishing.service.gov.uk/media/60c1cce1d3bf7f4bd9814e39/Maya_Forstater_v_CGD_Europe_and_others_UKEAT0105_20_JOJ.pdf&lt;/a&gt; (para 111) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:6&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:7&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/dli.ernet.537231/page/265/mode/2up&quot;&gt;https://archive.org/details/dli.ernet.537231/page/265/mode/2up&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:7&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:8&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Raphael_Cohen-Almagor&amp;amp;oldid=1108658836#Freedom_of_Expression&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Raphael_Cohen-Almagor&amp;amp;oldid=1108658836#Freedom_of_Expression&lt;/a&gt; (and &lt;a href=&quot;https://ora.ox.ac.uk/objects/uuid:e02067a0-ba42-428c-967a-1f3ba11c64bf/download_file?file_format=application%2Fpdf&amp;amp;safe_filename=602327189.pdf&amp;amp;type_of_work=Thesis&quot;&gt;doctoral thesis&lt;/a&gt;) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:8&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:9&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.judiciary.uk/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/Forstater-Press-statement.pdf&quot;&gt;https://www.judiciary.uk/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/Forstater-Press-statement.pdf&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:9&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:10&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hepi.ac.uk/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/You-cant-say-that-What-students-really-think-of-free-speech-on-campus.pdf&quot;&gt;https://www.hepi.ac.uk/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/You-cant-say-that-What-students-really-think-of-free-speech-on-campus.pdf&lt;/a&gt; (p6) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:10&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:11&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/faq/#what-is-the-equality-act-2010-and-what-are-protected-characteristics&quot;&gt;FAQ: What is the Equality Act 2010 and what are protected characteristics?&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:11&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:12&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/civil-service-diversity-and-inclusion-strategy-2022-to-2025/civil-service-diversity-and-inclusion-strategy-2022-to-2025-html&quot;&gt;https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/civil-service-diversity-and-inclusion-strategy-2022-to-2025/civil-service-diversity-and-inclusion-strategy-2022-to-2025-html&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:12&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>SEEN Network</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="network" />
      
        <category term="tolerance" />
      
        <category term="diversity of belief" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Reflecting society</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A network update</title>
      <link href="/posts/2022-11-21-network-update/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A network update" />
      <published>2022-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2022-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/network-update</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2022-11-21-network-update/">&lt;p&gt;A quick post to update our supporters and other interested parties.  It has been quite a month since our launch event on October 20th!  We wanted to reassure you that while we may have been keeping quiet, we have been incredibly busy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The interest in our network has been phenomenal!  SEEN has been noticed and discussed not only on social media but also in the mainstream press.  We will continue to increase our visibility as a network across the Civil Service to promote who we are and what we stand for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several hundred people have so far expressed interest in SEEN membership from nearly 50 eligible organisations from across central government, the executive agencies and arm’s length bodies.  Considering the short time since our launch this is an amazing and humbling response.  &lt;strong&gt;If you have requested more information on membership and are waiting to hear back from us, please don’t fret.&lt;/strong&gt;  We aim to be in touch with you within the next week or two.  We will also shortly activate our mailing list to keep people up to speed with our latest news by email.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have also received many membership enquiries and requests from people that we sadly cannot extend membership to (given the permitted scope for cross-departmental staff networks), including in local and devolved governments, the NHS and police.  We very much hope that SEEN will help to inspire equivalent networks to organise in other areas of the public sector.  For those that have just reached out to express support we appreciate these messages too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re looking forward to the journey ahead, and remain resolute in our commitment to further our mission.  We have lots of ideas of things to do and events to run, so watch this space!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exciting times ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SEEN&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;8 Feb 2023 edit: On the basis of advice from the Cabinet Office we amend the eligibility paragraph from “local and devolved governments” to read “local governments”.  Civil servants in the devolved governments are in fact eligible for SEEN membership.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>SEEN Network</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="network" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">A quick post to update our supporters and other interested parties. It has been quite a month since our launch event on October 20th! We wanted to reassure you that while we may have been keeping quiet, we have been incredibly busy.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A new staff network</title>
      <link href="/posts/2022-10-13-a-new-staff-network/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A new staff network" />
      <published>2022-10-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2022-10-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/a-new-staff-network</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2022-10-13-a-new-staff-network/">&lt;p&gt;We are happy to announce the launch of our new UK cross-government staff network, the &lt;em&gt;Sex Equality and Equity Network&lt;/em&gt;.  For more on our mission and who we are see &lt;a href=&quot;/about/&quot;&gt;About us&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Edit (22/11/2022): in the interest of transparency here is the version of our About page as it looked when this post first issued.  This will not be changed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are happy to announce the launch of our new UK cross-government staff network, the &lt;em&gt;Sex Equality and Equity Network&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SEEN is a staff network committed to promoting and supporting sex equality and equity between women and men in our workplaces, and helping all staff to thrive at work and fulfil their potential. The focus of our network is on challenging sex discrimination and upholding sex-based rights (including the protected characteristics of sex and sexual orientation, as set out in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2010/15/contents&quot;&gt;Equality Act 2010&lt;/a&gt;).  We recognise that to achieve this and ensure sex equality and equity sometimes requires treating women and men differently, according to our different rights and needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are also committed to the protected belief (covered by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2010/15/section/10&quot;&gt;protected characteristic of religion and belief&lt;/a&gt; in the Equality Act 2010) that biological sex is binary and immutable, that biological sex matters for both women and men in our everyday lives, including for our rights and needs in the workplace, and that biological sex must not be conflated with, or replaced by, the concepts of gender or gender identity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a part of our mission we want civil servants to feel safe to exercise their legal rights under the European Convention of Human Rights to freedom of thought, conscience and religion, freedom of expression and freedom of assembly and association, provided they manifest their rights lawfully and respectfully and within the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/civil-service-code/the-civil-service-code&quot;&gt;Civil Service Code&lt;/a&gt;.  We wish to encourage a diversity of voices and open and respectful dialogue and tolerance between those with differing beliefs and experiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also aim to be a source of expertise for staff on the protected characteristic of sex, pregnancy, maternity and sexual orientation; as well as the importance of taking these fully into account to meet staff rights and needs, including through the development of workplace policies and practices.  We also plan to hold events and webinars in due course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SEEN membership is open to staff who share our values, from central government departments, agencies, and their associated public bodies including arm’s length bodies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you would like to learn more about our mission, or to be added to our mailing list, please get in touch: [contact details available very shortly].&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>SEEN Network</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="network" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">We are happy to announce the launch of our new UK cross-government staff network, the Sex Equality and Equity Network. For more on our mission and who we are see About us</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
