<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/gender-stereotyping/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2025-08-26T22:05:27+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/gender-stereotyping/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">SEEN | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Sex Equality and Equity Network</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Let’s Talk About Pronouns..</title>
      <link href="/posts/2023-10-18-lets-talk-about-pronouns/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Let’s Talk About Pronouns.." />
      <published>2023-10-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-10-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/lets-talk-about-pronouns</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2023-10-18-lets-talk-about-pronouns/">&lt;p&gt;On the afternoon of Monday, 9th October we approached everyone on our mailing list to ask them what they thought about practices related to the statement of pronouns in email signatures and elsewhere.  One thing was immediately clear: this was something many had been burning to talk about!  Within 3 hours we’d had close to 50 responses, and from there they continued coming in steadily until we received our 100th contribution on Friday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had such a brilliant selection of answers, we’d like to share some of them in full, alongside a general summary and some overall themes. None of the comments included are from the SEEN Steering Group (we’ll follow up with some of our opinions at a later date).  We’ve attributed contributors in the way they’ve asked us to (be that first names, initials or just anonymous). Not all of them reflect views held within SEEN’s steering group, but we wanted to publish a varied selection to promote debate and showcase the diverse perspectives on this issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;impartiality-and-the-cs-code&quot;&gt;Impartiality and the CS Code&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over three quarters of respondents highlighted what they see as the political nature of pronoun declaration and the associated ideology underpinning it (that is, belief in gender identity), with the view that this was not considered appropriate in an impartial Civil Service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some examples of these comments include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;‘It does often feel like we have to show support regardless of if we agree with the cause and in an impartial Civil Service I don’t think that’s right’ – Anonymous, Home Office&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;‘We don’t indicate our affiliation with other ideological beliefs on official emails, e.g. which political or religious ideology we support. It is unnecessary for us to do our jobs and shouldn’t be encouraged as we are public servants who should strive to be as impartial as possible on all matters.’ – Anonymous, DSTL&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;‘As civil servants we are expected to remain politically impartial, a simple rule to which I am careful to adhere. Plastering your beliefs on every email sent out does not imply a political impartiality, quite the opposite.’ – Anonymous, APHA&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;‘Senior managers should be aware of the pressure that this display of partisan support for one side of this highly political issue places on other staff members to avoid expressing non-conforming views.  Senior Civil Servants (in particular) should be scrupulously neutral, and pronoun declarations are anything but.’ – Emma, HMRC&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;‘I see no reason why I should advertise where I stand on an issue which is going to be a political hot potato in the run up to the next election.’ – Gill, MOJ&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These highlight that the adding of pronouns is considered by many to be far from a neutral step, especially when adopted by senior management.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;sexism-womens-rights-and-sex-stereotypes&quot;&gt;Sexism, women’s rights and sex stereotypes&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of our members see stating pronouns as a clear indicator of a belief in gender identity (and that this should always take precedence over sex).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over a third of respondents highlighted how they believed the pushing / attempted enforcement of gender identity beliefs was having a detrimental effect on the rights of women in the workplace. Notably, a number of women in STEM from the MOD highlighted this, including Liz and Clare. Liz said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;‘As a female in engineering, I am normally in the minority.  Although overt sexism within engineering is no way near as bad as it once was, use of pronouns highlights that I’m not in the ‘boys club’ as even now there is a general belief that engineering is not for women.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clare had this to say:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;‘I have experienced a lot of sexism throughout my career in IT and seriously considered going by my gender-neutral middle name before joining the civil service. I decided not to, but I still consider that reinforcing that someone is female exposes them to implicit bias and potential disadvantage. I also think that declaring pronouns is like declaring your star sign, if there was a climate where expressing a lack of belief in horoscopes could lead to a person being disciplined or even fired from their jobs. It’s reliant on a belief and therefore very divisive and because it’s known that some people feel so passionately about it, it’s a reminder that those people could hate you or harbour a grudge against you.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many who highlighted this angle also expressed their concerns about how encouraging the use of pronouns (and thus implying belief in gender identity) was distressing, as it implied a &lt;em&gt;‘right’&lt;/em&gt; way to be a man or a woman, tied to stereotypes of femininity/masculinity, such as &lt;em&gt;‘FF, MoJ’&lt;/em&gt; who said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;‘It promotes an ideology that if you are female who does not [reflect] social roles and stereotypes of femininity you are not a woman, [and] similarly if you are a man who rejects the social roles of masculinity then you are not a man.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;homophobialgbt-concerns&quot;&gt;Homophobia/LGBT concerns&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A number of gay and lesbian members also wrote to express that, in addition to sexism, they believed the practice was also a signpost for homophobia, such as &lt;em&gt;‘Anonymous, DWP’&lt;/em&gt; who said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;‘Lesbians are being banned from creating lesbian only events. As a gay man, listing my pronouns would feel like publicly supporting an ideology that seeks to erase gays and lesbians.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several members also expressed their concerns for those who have gender dysphoria or are struggling with issues around identity, and how the enforcement of this practice may make them uncomfortable, such as &lt;em&gt;‘Anonymous from DEFRA’&lt;/em&gt; who said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;‘I worry that encouraging people to add pronouns to emails or provide them in introductions places undue pressure on those who are still working through issues of gender dysphoria. It’s not work’s place to ‘out’ people in this way.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Others highlighted that while the practice of pronoun declaration made them uncomfortable, they still had great sympathy for those struggling with gender dysphoria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;autism-and-neurodiversity&quot;&gt;Autism and neurodiversity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A number of respondents also highlighted how people with autism or other neurodiverse conditions can struggle with preferred pronouns that do not match a person’s clearly observed sex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;‘Anonymous from Scottish Government’&lt;/em&gt; said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;‘I have always used pronouns in line with my presumption of someone’s sex except where it is clear they wish me to do something different. In that case I tend to default to using their first name repeatedly as using their preferred pronouns makes me feel complicit in a lie which is probably more awkward for me as my autism makes me very reluctant to dissemble.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While &lt;em&gt;‘Kate from DEFRA’&lt;/em&gt; commented:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;‘I also really feel for people with neurodivergence such as autism, I know a lot of folk are worried that they will accidentally misgender someone and with CS buying into the Stonewall narrative that accidentally ‘misgendering’ someone is transphobic I worry that the pronoun pushing will get these folks in trouble and potentially on a disciplinary.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;a-culture-of-fear&quot;&gt;A culture of fear&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many members highlighted the culture of fear that is created around pronoun declaration and associated beliefs about gender identity. Some described having faced direct discrimination and harassment from colleagues for refusing to participate in pronoun declarations to the extent that they are now scared or concerned when they interact with someone who has pronouns in their signature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;‘AG from UK Export Finance’&lt;/em&gt; commented:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;‘it shouldn’t be done… Additionally, the threats when pronouns aren’t included or added by those that want them to be is horrific.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;‘NM from DEFRA’&lt;/em&gt; was one of the many people who expressed the view that it led to exclusion, rather than inclusion:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;‘I feel the use of pronouns in the workplace is unnecessary and alienating to many people. It does not create an inclusive culture, but instead a culture of fear and isolation’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The use of links to external blogs that appeared to push the practice was something also raised by many, particularly &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cultureamp.com/blog/gender-pronouns-in-workplace&quot;&gt;this blog from Culture Amp&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other SEEN members have queried why blogs like the above are allowed, whereas &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.filia.org.uk/latest-news/2021/12/1/should-you-declare-your-pronouns-a-simple-guide&quot;&gt;blogs like this&lt;/a&gt; aren’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;support-for-preferred-pronouns&quot;&gt;Support for preferred pronouns&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the overwhelming response from those who disagreed with the declaration of pronouns, we also received a handful of responses which said they didn’t mind pronouns in other people’s signatures, as long as they weren’t expected to declare pronouns themselves, and as long as they could still accurately describe someone’s sex in situations where relevant.  We also received four contributions strongly in favour of use of pronouns in signatures and work profiles, if necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SEEN welcomes a plurality of views and opinions, and we also look to seek tolerance and understanding between those with differing views.  For these reasons, we have also  included two perspectives in favour of pronouns below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;‘Will from MoJ’&lt;/em&gt; had this to say:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;‘Another potential benefit of having everyone record their pronouns on their profile is that should someone feel the need to challenge whether someone was using the ‘correct’ facilities in the workplace because they were spending too much time in them themselves to mind their own business and return to work, they would be able to confirm how they identify against their profile (if they knew who the individual was) and avoid making a mistake in thinking someone was in a space they shouldn’t have been. If someone was to then bring an issue like this up to management etc to ‘deal with’ they would be able to challenge back about what they themselves were doing in the facilities for so long to be able to notice when they should only be in those facilities to do their business and then return to work, ensuring everyone is protected from those who loiter in the facilities and report them to the police if necessary.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;‘John (they/them) from MoJ’&lt;/em&gt; said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;‘I am non-binary and I include my pronouns in my email signature and it is also configured to appear in Teams via an option in my Global Address List Entry. It allows colleagues to correctly gender me in meetings without me having to state my pronouns regularly or correct them if they initially assume I use different pronouns. This makes me feel much more included, less stressed, and less awkward.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many will have sympathy for John and will choose to add pronouns for the purpose of kindness.  However,  &lt;em&gt;‘Anonymous, DESNZ’&lt;/em&gt; has a different view of the result of such intentions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;My line manager, a pleasant bloke with young children, has ‘pronouns he/him’ after his name on his email signature. Next to it, he has carefully made a hyperlink marked ‘Why do I do this?’, which links to a political blog about ‘allyship’. Whenever an email from him pops up, there also pops up the ‘pronouns he/him’. And every time his name and pronouns pop up on my screen, I get a lurch of dread in my stomach and fight back tears. My lovely, fragile young niece comes into my mind again, I feel helpless, and I can’t concentrate on my work. My teenaged, soon-to-be-adult niece, who has for years struggled with depression, anxiety and obsessive-compulsive disorder. We all helped and supported her as best as we could and hoped maturity and time would work its magic and foster her growing into the strong, healthy young woman we know she can be, just like a million awkward teenagers before her have grown up and worked it out.  Instead, she got caught up in the gender identity movement and is trapped in an alternate universe.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Now she feels ‘special’ and ‘chosen’, rather than just an awkward ugly duckling who got teased by the cool kids. Now she is praised for her ‘bravery’ by the cool kids at her new 6th Form and they tell her the rest of the world is against her and only her ‘allies’ will defend her.   […]&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;We try still to hold her as close as we can and tell her we love her just the way she is, and that she doesn’t need to pretend to be a boy for the world to accept her. We hope we can keep hold of her before she is old enough to buy cross-sex hormones or get on a surgery waiting list to have her breasts chopped off. She threatens both on her darkest days, full of weeping and panic attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Does my line manager know about girls like my niece? Every day, I think, I must talk to him. But what can I say, when our workplace policies allow and encourage ‘pronouns’? He has also been praised as ‘brave’, for being ‘a good ally to vulnerable people’. Does he know how this violent political movement of gender identity, that he so casually promotes with his ‘pronouns’, damages vulnerable girls like my niece? If he doesn’t know, why doesn’t he bother to find out? If he does know, how can he be so callous?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We would like to thank you all for your honesty and engagement in this issue.  Watch out for Part 2 (coming soon).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover by &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@magicetea?utm_content=creditCopyText&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_source=unsplash&quot;&gt;Ice Tea&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/photos/LXQeSfkY660?utm_content=creditCopyText&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_source=unsplash&quot;&gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script&gt;

    document.addEventListener(&quot;DOMContentLoaded&quot;, function () {
        const words = {
            &quot;he&quot;: &quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/He_(pronoun)&quot;,
            &quot;him&quot;: &quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/He_(pronoun)&quot;,
            &quot;his&quot;: &quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/He_(pronoun)&quot;,
            &quot;she&quot;: &quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/She_(pronoun)&quot;,
            &quot;her&quot;: &quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/She_(pronoun)&quot;,
            &quot;hers&quot;: &quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/She_(pronoun)&quot;,
            &quot;they&quot;: &quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/They&quot;,
            &quot;them&quot;: &quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/They&quot;,
            &quot;theirs&quot;: &quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/They&quot;,
            &quot;xe&quot;: &quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neopronoun&quot;,
            &quot;xem&quot;: &quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neopronoun&quot;,
            &quot;xyr&quot;: &quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neopronoun&quot;,
            &quot;ey&quot;: &quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neopronoun&quot;,
            &quot;em&quot;: &quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neopronoun&quot;,
            &quot;ze&quot;: &quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neopronoun&quot;,
            &quot;hir&quot;: &quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neopronoun&quot;,
            &quot;zir&quot;: &quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neopronoun#History&quot;,
            &quot;heer&quot;: &quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neopronoun#History&quot;,
            &quot;zir&quot;: &quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neopronoun#History&quot;
        };
        const wordElements = [];
        var w = window.innerWidth;
        var h = window.innerHeight;
        var post_image = document.getElementById('post-image');

        post_image.offsetHeight
        post_image.offsetLeft
        post_image.offsetTop

        Object.keys(words).forEach(word =&gt; {
            const wordElement = document.createElement(&quot;a&quot;);
            wordElement.className = &quot;word&quot;;
            wordElement.innerText = word;
            wordElement.href = words[word];
            wordElement.target = '_blank';
            wordElement.target = &quot;this link opens in a new window&quot;;
            wordElement.style.left = (w * 0.1) + (Math.random() * w * 0.75) + 'px';
            wordElement.style.top = post_image.offsetTop + 60 + Math.random() * post_image.clientHeight * 0.7 + 'px';
            wordElement.style.color = '#000';
            document.body.appendChild(wordElement);
            wordElements.push(wordElement);
        });

        document.addEventListener(&quot;mousemove&quot;, function (event) {
            const mouseX = event.clientX;
            const mouseY = event.clientY;

            wordElements.forEach(wordElement =&gt; {
                const rect = wordElement.getBoundingClientRect();
                const wordX = rect.left + rect.width / 2;
                const wordY = rect.top + rect.height / 2;

                const deltaX = wordX - mouseX;
                const deltaY = wordY - mouseY;
                const distance = Math.sqrt(deltaX * deltaX + deltaY * deltaY);

                if (distance &lt; 100) {
                    const angle = Math.atan2(deltaY, deltaX);
                    const newX = wordX + Math.cos(angle) * 5;
                    wordElement.style.left = newX - rect.width / 2 + &quot;px&quot;;
                    wordElement.style.top = parseInt(wordElement.style.top) + Math.sin(angle) * 5 + 'px';
                }
            });
        });
    });
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;style&gt;
    .word {
        position: absolute;
        font-size: 40px;
        font-family: seenfont, &quot;Times New Roman&quot;, Georgia, serif;
        background-color: #E9F1DB;
        padding: 20px 14px 18px 14px;
        box-shadow: -3px 7px 3px #000;
        white-space: nowrap;
        z-index: 100;
    }
&lt;/style&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>SEEN Network</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="language" />
      
        <category term="civil service" />
      
        <category term="gender stereotyping" />
      
        <category term="lesbian gay and bisexual" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">On the afternoon of Monday, 9th October we approached everyone on our mailing list to ask them what they thought about practices related to the statement of pronouns in email signatures and elsewhere. One thing was immediately clear: this was something many had been burning to talk about! Within 3 hours we’d had close to 50 responses, and from there they continued coming in steadily until we received our 100th contribution on Friday.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Why SEEN is important to me (vii)</title>
      <link href="/posts/2023-07-19-why-is-seen-important-to-me-vii/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why SEEN is important to me (vii)" />
      <published>2023-07-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-07-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/why-is-seen-important-to-me-vii</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2023-07-19-why-is-seen-important-to-me-vii/">&lt;p&gt;Bring your whole self to work is what my employer tells me. Unless of course you happen to believe like I do that sex is binary and fixed from conception. In that case I am allowed to hold that belief (thank you &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.judiciary.uk/judgments/forstater-v-cgd-europe-and-ors/&quot;&gt;Maya&lt;/a&gt;), but not to express it plainly in case it causes offense to those who believe that the concept of innate gender identity is more important in all cases than biological sex, or somehow denies their identity.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;But what about my identity?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When my employer asks for my gender but not my sex, or asks for my gender without giving me the option to say that I do not believe in an innate gender, this denies my identity. My sex is important to me. My sex has shaped my life. During my career I have experienced sexism, disadvantage and discrimination due to my sex and I have had to fight against the stereotypes imposed upon me due to my sex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When my employer asks me to state whether I identify as a woman, this denies my identity. To use woman in this way is to change it from a definition based on sex, to one based on gender identity. I am not a woman because I have womanly thoughts and feelings which are separate and distinct from manly thoughts and feelings - and if you think I am you need to reconsider as this is the very definition of sexism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When my employer allows me to be referred to as cis-gendered, this denies my identity. I am not a woman because my personality happens to align with the stereotypical expectations that society places on me due to my sex, any more than I would not be a woman if my personality did not. And my personality, like that of everyone else I have ever met, is a mix of those traits that society ascribes to be feminine and masculine because stereotypes are nonsense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am a woman because my sex is female. But knowing my sex tells you nothing about me except what my sex is. It does not tell you about my personality, my likes and dislikes, my strengths and weaknesses. There is no trait, characteristic, thought or feeling that I share with all other women on this planet and which is distinct from those shared by men, other than our biology. So I say again, I am a woman because my sex is female.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are all afforded protections in law to prevent us from suffering from discrimination and harassment or to preserve our privacy and dignity because of our sex. But as it stands my employer has no record of my sex and has replaced sex with gender and that is why SEEN is so important to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover image&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/photos/DRzYMtae-vA&quot;&gt;Nadine Shaabana&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/license&quot;&gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>UNSEEN</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="personal experience" />
      
        <category term="language" />
      
        <category term="gender stereotyping" />
      
        <category term="why seen" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Bring your whole self to work is what my employer tells me. Unless of course you happen to believe like I do that sex is binary and fixed from conception. In that case I am allowed to hold that belief (thank you Maya), but not to express it plainly in case it causes offense to those who believe that the concept of innate gender identity is more important in all cases than biological sex, or somehow denies their identity.But what about my identity?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Why SEEN is important to me (ii)</title>
      <link href="/posts/2023-01-10-why-is-seen-important-to-me-ii/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why SEEN is important to me (ii)" />
      <published>2023-01-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-01-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/why-is-seen-important-to-me-ii</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2023-01-10-why-is-seen-important-to-me-ii/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[This post is the second of &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/launch-speeches/&quot;&gt;four speeches by SEEN members&lt;/a&gt; from our launch event in October. Named individuals are anonymised.]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good afternoon everyone, I am one of the Co-Chairs of the new Network.  It gives me great pleasure, on behalf of myself, my-Co-Chairs and the rest of our steering group, to welcome you all today to the first meeting of the new Civil Service Sex Equality and Equity Network and I’d like to thank you all for coming.  I’ve opened and chaired meetings with that form of words on many occasions, but it has rarely been so whole-heartedly true as it is today.  This gathering and the formation of this network is something that a group of us have been looking forward to for quite a while.  We have all, for different reasons, felt that there has been a gap in the activities that take place to promote diversity in the Civil Service in that they do not recognise the existence and legitimacy of those of us who consider that there will always be circumstances where sex is important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quite a number of us are lawyers, and we all start from the position that civil servants should uphold the law in all our dealings.  The central focus of our network will be on the sex-based rights and protections that the law provides.  As we state in our constitution: “we will focus on challenging sex discrimination, and upholding rights and protections that relate to sex (including the protections provided to those with the protected characteristics of sex and sexual orientation).  We recognise that ensuring sex equality and equity sometimes requires treating women and men differently, according to our different rights”.  Because the law is so central to what we stand for, we are fortunate enough to have a lawyer who specialises in discrimination law, here this afternoon to give a brief introduction to some of the legal provisions that create and support sex-based rights and protections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are also committed to the protected belief (covered by the protected characteristic of religion and belief in the Equality Act 2010) that biological sex is binary and immutable, that biological sex matters for both women and men in our everyday lives, including for many of our rights and needs in the workplace, and that biological sex must not be conflated with the concepts of gender identity or gender.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What will this mean in practice in terms of the goals we will pursue as a network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It means, for example, that we will push for the Civil Service to collect accurate and meaningful data on the protected characteristic of sex.  Because of the importance of data in understanding inequalities and acting to achieve sex equality, we have also invited a colleague who specialises in statistics, to speak briefly on this topic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also means that we will advocate for workplace policies and practices that contain clear sex-based language, where relevant.  To this end, we are also fortunate to be hearing from one of my colleagues on the topic of language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, in addition to a clear understanding and application of the law, data and language, an understanding of our network would not be complete without an appreciation of the experiences which have drawn many of us to have an interest in this field.  So, you will also hear testimonies from other SEEN members as to why the formation of this network is important to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll give you may own - rather mundane - personal story in a moment, but I wanted to start by explaining a bit more about why we have set up this network and what we hope it will achieve.  I hope most of you will be able to relate to our motivation and support what we want to accomplish.  We have deliberately kept the guest list for this event small and largely limited to people who have contacted us because they wanted to be part of something like this, so that we have the confidence to share experiences here.  But we have some guests who are involved in Diversity and Inclusion in the civil service and hope those guests will also understand and support what we are trying to do in the interests of promoting greater diversity and inclusion in the civil service.  By encouraging a range of voices to speak up and create an open and respectful dialogue, we aim to achieve greater tolerance between those with differing beliefs and experiences and ‘foster good relations between people who share particular protected characteristic and those who do not’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone should have their legal rights and interests properly respected and protected in the workplace.  We recognise that this includes those who disagree with us.  Conversely, just because others may disagree with our protected beliefs, this is not an excuse to vilify us or try to restrict the exercise of our legal rights.  We will strongly resist such an approach.  Amongst our aims is to promote understanding between people with different beliefs and ensure that the civil service properly caters for those who hold all of them, balancing them where necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We very much hope that all those aims will be achieved by this network coming into existence and we intend to make good use of the voice that the network will give us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will now turn briefly to the personal and explain why I care so much about this.  There are three main reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, because I regard the substitution of sex with gender identity in relation to equality aims as a retrograde step for women’s rights.  When I was starting out on my career, my father told me that he was worried about the cost of educating girls and that if I incurred debts in the course of my training, it would give me a ‘negative dowry’, a very sexist and demeaning viewpoint which I did not allow to throw me off course.  Then my uncle, who was a solicitor, told me that he would offer a training contract to my husband, and not to me, because being a trainee solicitor involved lots of ‘out-door work’ and so was not suitable work for a woman! We’ve collectively proved him wrong, more than 50% of solicitors are now women and that percentage is even higher in the civil service.  I have personally proved him wrong by having a successful career as a lawyer.  Both of these views were based on harmful stereotypes in relation to the role of women in society.  I am concerned that an insistence on the idea that everyone has an innate gender identity is a way of allowing those types of stereotype, which until a few years ago I thought were well on the way to being eradicated, back into society by the back door.  The concept of gender identity, whilst proponents describe it as an internal feeling, is difficult to separate from societal expectations of how each sex is expected to behave.  As someone who does not consider I have a gender identity, the idea that if I do not conform to the societal expectations for my sex, I may actually be of a different sex or even gender, seems highly regressive.  If this serves to reinforce, rather than rid us of such unhelpful stereotypes, the consequences for the equality of women, and indeed for all gender non-conforming people, for equity in our society to the benefit of both sexes seem to me to be highly damaging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, I care because of the impact on single-sex services for women.  In my spare time I was for many years the chair of the board of a charity running a women’s refuge.  In the course of that work, I met and my organisation helped many severely traumatised women and their children by providing a safe refuge and a service provided by women and for women, taking advantage of an exception in what is now the Equality Act 2010.  Refuge services are a strong example of the importance of sex-based rights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst of course not all men are abusers, it is surely contrary to a tradition of recognising the need for single sex provision in this are, to up to date evidence on perpetrators and victims and to much good-practice in trauma-informed health care to require female victims of male abuse and their children to live in close proximity to biological male victims, no matter how they identify.  Any traumatised victim is likely to feel unsafe and more traumatised in such an environment, and where biological sex dictates having different needs in any event, such a practice would have been likely to undermine the effectiveness of the service our charity provided (particularly given such services could instead be provided more effectively in separate facilities).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This issue is not directly relevant to the work of this network which will focus on where they are important in our Civil Service workplaces, but it is part of what motivates me to care about this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I also care about the impact of the difficulty of speaking up about sex-based rights on my gay and neurodiverse colleagues and friends, but I’ll let colleagues speak to that shortly.  Please be aware that they cover some sensitive topics in a frank fashion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I’ve set out why we are setting up this network and given you a flavour of my personal motivation.  Some of my colleagues are now going to address specific aspects of our aims and offer you an insight into their motivations.  We’ll take a brief break for networking in the middle of the speaker slots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you have heard from them we’d like to lead a more participative session about the network and its plans.  We’ll try to answer questions but please don’t ask for more personal information from our speakers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, a note about context.  We want our network to recognise freedom of speech and hope you will feel comfortable to share your views.  I am sure you will all express yourselves sensitively though and bear in mind that this is a meeting of an official civil service network and so we need to abide by the Civil Service Code and conduct ourselves accordingly as I am sure you will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover image:&lt;/strong&gt;  “Thinking woman” by pacogaitero is licensed under CC BY-NC-SA 2.0. To view a copy of this license, visit https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/2.0/?ref=openverse.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Mary</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="personal experience" />
      
        <category term="sex discrimination" />
      
        <category term="gender stereotyping" />
      
        <category term="launch speeches" />
      
        <category term="why seen" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">[This post is the second of four speeches by SEEN members from our launch event in October. Named individuals are anonymised.]</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
