<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/diversity-of-belief/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2025-08-26T22:05:27+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/diversity-of-belief/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">SEEN | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Sex Equality and Equity Network</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Menopause: A radical perspective</title>
      <link href="/posts/2024-01-17-menopause-a-radical-perspective/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Menopause: A radical perspective" />
      <published>2024-01-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2024-01-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/menopause-a-radical-perspective</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2024-01-17-menopause-a-radical-perspective/">&lt;p&gt;As a 47-year-old woman, it’s not surprising that I’m heartened by the increasing visibility and normalisation of menopause – whether I like it or not, that train is pulling into the station some time soon. But the litany of common problems – the brain fog, the sleeplessness, the pains and sweats – that sounds like a bad cosmic joke, that each new chapter of female life must open with a new swathe of physical inconvenience. Is nature itself a misogynist? No wonder most world religions contend that women are being punished for some original sin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who would want to be a girl? No matter how much my mum insisted slightly desperately that ‘being a girl is just as good as being a boy,’ it just didn’t ring true. How can it be as good? I’m doomed to be weaker, and fatter! I could be attacked, or raped. I have to deal with periods, I could get pregnant. If I ever want a child I’ll &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; to get pregnant. Women get paid less, taken less seriously, expected to shave their legs and wear make-up to look ‘normal’. Name me just one thing that is better for girls! See!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a teenager I was grimly determined to compensate for my bad luck at the sex lottery, the cruel roulette that had put an X chromosome in the way of my human self-actualisation. On my grandparents’ farm I hefted haybales on my own, not one-between-two like mere aunties and mums. I wore trousers with my Venture Scouts uniform, and hauled a superabundance of sanitary products and painkillers on all-day hikes. At school I marched the other way whenever I saw creepy Mr Richards, who addressed all the girls while looking directly at their breasts. I tried, repeatedly, to explain to priapic teenage boys in pub car parks that I thought we were friends. At university I wore a bristling leather jacket and made it clear I could walk home on my own, thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was studying political philosophy, especially the development of post-Enlightenment concepts of the ‘political individual’, who could consent to mutual obligations rather than owing duty to a lord. Foundational thinkers such as Locke and Rousseau had banished women as a sex to the ‘private sphere’, on the basis that they were by nature too emotional, too unruly, to partake in public life (and, presumably, because otherwise there would be no-one to clean the houses and raise the children of the Great Men).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While writing my dissertation, I came across feminist political theorist Carole Pateman. Pateman’s thesis was that the Great Men didn’t &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; exclude women from political personhood out of prejudice and expediency. Rather, the individual they defined had specifically male characteristics which women could not share. Pateman wrote that “the body of the ‘individual’ is very different from women’s bodies. His body is tightly enclosed within boundaries, but women’s bodies are permeable, their contours change shape and they are subject to cyclical processes. All these differences are summed up in the natural bodily process of birth.” I thought this was reductive nonsense. What if women don’t &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; shifting contours and cyclical processes? What if they would like to reproduce (if at all) on an equal basis with men? It seemed a bit embarrassing that these middle-aged feminists were wanging on about some female birth-giving energy or whatever – wouldn’t it be better to stop framing all that icky, painful business as ‘female’, so that it didn’t hold individual women back from their potential? It seemed obvious to me that the solution was not, as Pateman recommended, to create two political actors, one of each sex, but to make sure the political individual was neutral, unsexed, to accommodate all shades of glorious human diversity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I moved through my 20s, though, my sex continued, stubbornly, to affect my life. I wasn’t doing feminine things – hell, I wasn’t even doing specifically female things like having periods or, god forbid, children. And yet I still had to think differently, act differently to men, to navigate my reality – the man who flashed at me as I walked home from the Tube station, or the one who found it funny to follow me along the dark road, didn’t seem to know or care what I felt about my boundaries, permeable or otherwise. I started to become less resentful of my own bad luck to be female, and more angry at how a supposedly liberal society treated female people in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ‘ladette’ feminism of the 90s emphasised personal freedom and equity – individual women having the same choices and opportunities as men, without being judged to a different standard. But that liberal feminism didn’t explain to me the root cause of women’s mistreatment – even in Cool Britannia, there didn’t seem to be a choice I could make that would give me men’s freedoms, so how could more ‘choices’ help the women of Afghanistan, Somalia or Nepal?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was radical (‘of the root’) feminist analysis that finally, to me, made sense of the global systematic oppression of female people. Drawing on Marxist thinking, radical feminism uses class analysis, where a class is a set of people (or things) that meet specific criteria. Importantly, something that is true of the class doesn’t need to be true of all the individual members of that class. For example, the class ‘homo sapiens’, defined as all living humans, has two eyes – it doesn’t tend to have two eyes, or generally have two eyes; it has two eyes. That doesn’t mean that all humans have two eyes, or that anyone with just one eye is not human, or that the purpose or destiny of humans is to have eyes. In all sexually dimorphic species, the female is defined as the kind of organism that produces large gametes (e.g. eggs). So it’s the class of female humans which gestates young and gives birth – that doesn’t mean all female humans give birth, or that anyone who doesn’t give birth isn’t female, or that giving birth is the purpose or destiny of female humans. But it does mean female humans as a class can be, and are, exploited and subordinated in patriarchal systems – regardless of any individual woman’s real or perceived personal characteristics or reproductive status. That’s precisely why there isn’t an opt-out, no matter how much I might have wanted one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Class analysis allows you to see the wood for the trees and examine powerful structures in society without getting distracted by individual variations. It loses some value when the class is porous or can’t be clearly defined – that’s one of the reasons why I’m not a political Marxist or even a socialist (which I’m sure would disappoint my Great Uncle ‘Red’ Eddie, firebrand of the General Strike). My lefty interventionist liberalism reflects my optimism that no-one is fixed forever into a particular socio-economic category. We won’t need to liberate the labouring class if we can effectively abolish it – or at the very least provide means of escape. The same isn’t true of sex class – regardless of our identity, personality or social presentation, it’s not possible in humans to change the material condition of our sex. Glorious human diversity takes place within and across sex classes, and there is powerful intersectionality with other characteristics. But Pateman was right*, in that there’s no point unsexing the political individual when we can’t unsex ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since there can be no escape from our sex, there has to be liberation &lt;em&gt;of&lt;/em&gt; our sex, so that its exploitation doesn’t limit our humanity – structural change to remedy the oppression of women as a sex class. This starts with Marie Shear’s definition of feminism – the radical notion that women are people. That as a sex, we are a whole class of human people in our own right, not a variant or a sub-category (non-men), not a state of mind, and not a shifting collection of whichever individuals happen at a given time to have certain working organs or be manifesting particular bodily functions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this is the context for my own perspective on how we need, collectively, to re-imagine menopause. Yes, of course more awareness of symptoms and greater support for colleagues is wonderful. But we need to take on the challenge of how menopause (among other things) represents the fusion of female biology and female exploitation. Periods, pregnancy and menopause are the foundations for the ancient folk archetypes of the maiden, the mother and the crone. The trivialisation of menopause is intertwined with the invisibility of older women, and the contempt in which they are held in society as a whole. We need to understand and manage menopause as an integral part of female experience, not as another ineffable ordeal that women must fight against and overcome in order to entertain the hopeful fiction that they, too, might be fully human.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*I still disagree with aspects of Pateman’s thesis, but for more nuanced reasons that I don’t have space for here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;•·················•·················•&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover photo with kind permission from the wonderful &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/jessdewahls/&quot;&gt;Jess De Wahls&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;style&gt;
.post-full-content {
    background: #ffffff00 !important;
}
&lt;/style&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>UNSEEN</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="diversity of belief" />
      
        <category term="language" />
      
        <category term="why seen" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">As a 47-year-old woman, it’s not surprising that I’m heartened by the increasing visibility and normalisation of menopause – whether I like it or not, that train is pulling into the station some time soon. But the litany of common problems – the brain fog, the sleeplessness, the pains and sweats – that sounds like a bad cosmic joke, that each new chapter of female life must open with a new swathe of physical inconvenience. Is nature itself a misogynist? No wonder most world religions contend that women are being punished for some original sin.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">What gender critical means to me</title>
      <link href="/posts/2023-12-18-what-gender-critical-means-to-me/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What gender critical means to me" />
      <published>2023-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/what-gender-critical-means-to-me</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2023-12-18-what-gender-critical-means-to-me/">&lt;p&gt;After another week of having to explain again to managers and HR staff what gender critical beliefs are and are not, I thought it would be helpful to put together this primer in case it is of use to others. The term ‘gender critical’ covers a range of views and I don’t speak for everyone, and nor am I a spokesperson for SEEN. But I think the views I explain here are fairly representative of those I have met in SEEN.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;1-sex-and-gendergender-identity-are-different-things&quot;&gt;1. Sex and gender/gender identity are different things&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stonewall define transgender as &lt;em&gt;“An umbrella term to describe people whose gender is not the same as, or does not sit comfortably with, the sex they were assigned at birth”&lt;/em&gt;, so they are not the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;2-everyone-has-a-biological-sex&quot;&gt;2. Everyone has a biological sex&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sex, whether you are male or female, is your biology and is observable and measurable. Everyone has a biological sex that is fixed from the point of conception and recorded at birth. A small proportion of people have one of the rare medical conditions known as Differences of Sexual Development (DSD), but people with DSD’s are still male or female.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone (whether or not they believe in the concept of &lt;em&gt;gender identity&lt;/em&gt;, and whatever their gender identity is, if they have one) can experience sexism, bullying and harassment or discrimination on the basis of their sex. This may be the sexism that a woman faces due to stereotypes about her sex, or the sexism a transwoman (someone registered male at birth who considers themselves to have a female gender identity) faces because they do not follow the sex-based stereotypes associated with their sex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sex is a protected characteristic. Sex is also the basis of the protected characteristics of sexual orientation (opposite-, same- or both-sex attracted) and maternity and pregnancy (which only applies to women).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is vital that we are able to talk about sex when relevant to our employment and that our employers provide us all with the sex-based protections in place in law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;3-some-people-believe-they-have-a-gender-identity&quot;&gt;3. Some people believe they have a gender identity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gender identity is defined by Stonewall as &lt;em&gt;“A person’s innate sense of their own gender, whether male, female or something else, which may or may not correspond to the sex assigned at birth.”&lt;/em&gt; Gender identity cannot be observed or measured.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some people believe in the concept of gender identity, and some people do not. Some people that do hold this belief, consider that their gender identity does not match their sex, and they may describe themselves as transgender or non-binary, cisgender, or something else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gender reassignment is a protected characteristic. Someone with the protected characteristic of gender reassignment may hold a Gender Recognition Certificate (GRC), or they may not. Either way, no one should face bullying, harassment or discrimination because their gender identity does not match their sex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Belief in the concept of gender identity may also be a protected belief under the Equality Act. No one should face bullying, harassment or discrimination due to their belief in the concept of gender identity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, a belief in gender identity should not be assumed or imposed on employees. The civil service has a duty to remain neutral both for its staff and for those we serve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;4-some-people-have-gender-critical-beliefs&quot;&gt;4. Some people have Gender Critical beliefs&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those with gender critical beliefs do not subscribe to the concept of gender identity. They think that gender identity must not be conflated with or used to replace sex in law, policy, guidance or elsewhere. If there is a need to segregate men and women for reasons of privacy, dignity, safety or safeguarding it is sex that should be used (and which is permitted under the Equality Act), not self-identified gender identity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gender critical beliefs are a protected belief under the Equality Act. Noone should face bullying, harassment or discrimination due to their lack of belief in the concept of gender identity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I do not hold a belief in gender identity, this does not mean I do not acknowledge the existence of transgender or non-binary people. My lack of Christian faith does not mean I deny the existence of Christians. Of course Christians exist, but their existence does not prove the existence of a Christian God. Equally, my lack of belief in innate gender identity does not mean I deny the existence of transgender or non-binary colleagues. Everyone should be treated with respect. But someone’s beliefs about their own gender identity do not override the protections written into law on the basis of sex, nor my (lack of) belief.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So to me, gender critical beliefs are simply about expecting my employer to apply the sex-based protections afforded to us all in law, and not imposing a belief system on me that I do not share.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;see also &lt;a href=&quot;/myths/#myth-6-intersex-people-are-proof-that-sex-is-not-binary&quot;&gt;SEEN’s position&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>UNSEEN</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="diversity of belief" />
      
        <category term="language" />
      
        <category term="why seen" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">After another week of having to explain again to managers and HR staff what gender critical beliefs are and are not, I thought it would be helpful to put together this primer in case it is of use to others. The term ‘gender critical’ covers a range of views and I don’t speak for everyone, and nor am I a spokesperson for SEEN. But I think the views I explain here are fairly representative of those I have met in SEEN.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Impartiality and Finding Common Ground</title>
      <link href="/posts/2023-11-21-impartiality-and-finding-common-ground/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Impartiality and Finding Common Ground" />
      <published>2023-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/impartiality-and-finding-common-ground</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2023-11-21-impartiality-and-finding-common-ground/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;On 14th November, SEEN was invited to participate in the “Navigating Difference Finding Common Ground” webinar, and interfaith and belief event, which formed part of Faith and Belief Week 2023.  This was our presentation, given by a SEEN co-chair, as a part of the panel.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;•·················•·················•&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’d be the first to admit that SEEN - the Sex Equality and Equity network - is a strange one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve been a cross governmental network for a year, and our journey has certainly been unconventional: at times controversial, sometimes even fractious.  It’s also taught us something about the importance of a fair and demonstrably impartial workplace, and about how we might find common ground when we profoundly disagree.  I’d like to share these thoughts today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But first: a mystery.  We are not the only network underpinned by a clear set of beliefs.  The same is also true of both the Gender and LGBT+ networks.  These are often stated as ‘trans women are women, trans men are men and non-binary identities are valid’.  Conversely, our position can also be stated very briefly as: sex is binary and immutable and matters more than gender.  So why were we the ones that ended up as a ‘faith and belief’ network?   Well, the answer is because until 2019 you could be fired for voicing these views in the workplace.  The now famous &lt;em&gt;Forstater&lt;/em&gt; case changed that, confirming that our views are worthy of respect in a democratic society.  And so - our belief protected - the rest is history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d like to just repeat something again.  &lt;em&gt;Back in 2019 people were being fired for expressing these views.&lt;/em&gt;  And even now it can still be taboo to state what ten years ago would have been utterly unremarkable.  How did this radical shift happen?  We see some of the explanation lying in well-intentioned workplace activism, perpetuated through training, webinars, blog posts and even email signatures; an activism which became so prevalent that our members tell us they felt shamed and even coerced into demonstrating a particular set of beliefs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But does that even matter if this results in a kinder, more diverse and inclusive workplace?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, the first question is whether it really does.  On the surface such workplaces may appear united, but the veneer of harmony presides over deep discomfort and fear.  We don’t think employees should have their thoughts and beliefs policed, or be pushed into demonstrating adherence to an ideology they don’t share.  More importantly, we don’t think anyone benefits from this approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our network can also be understood as a pushback against this enforced homogeny: the idea that ‘kindness’, ‘inclusivity’ and ‘diversity’ come via only one set of beliefs and fall under only one flag.  We don’t think harmony is achieved by making everyone pretend to believe the same thing.  And because we’ve seen these dangers, we have no desire to replace one activism with another.  I’ll even let you into a secret about our end-game.  What we are aiming for is a return to the impartiality which - at its best - characterises the Civil Service.  Then we’ll happily hang up our SEEN lanyards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what’s so great about impartiality?  It sounds cold and indifferent.  But our experience is that in practice it can operate to do something magical.  Impartiality is nonjudgmental and fair.  It accepts that the workplace can’t be made perfect, it will always reflect our wider, complex society.  It recognises that it’s not the role of our employer to forge us into anyone’s vision of what a better human being looks like.   The real world and the people within it are subtle, complex and interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There will always be differences between us.  But genuine impartiality allows for difference and diversity to flourish.  And diversity is a vital part of the Civil Service’s success. Our steering group came together through our shared interest in this issue, but accidentally formed a microcosm of the diversity that we think makes the Civil Service great.  Within our small group we have members of four different faiths (and others of none), those from a range of social and ethnic backgrounds, some who are lesbian or gay and – of course – both men and women.  There are huge differences between us, in outlook, approach, background and personality.  Working with this extraordinary group of people has taught me first hand how true diversity can make a team more than the sum of its parts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But is impartiality enough?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think there needs to be something else as well.  And so, what?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, we are not in a crèche.  We can’t expect our employer to solve all our problems.  And this is where I think us - employees - have an important role to play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I look for a secular solution, that of humanism and its emphasis on a common humanity.  Since forming as a network I’ve talked to many people, and the more I talk, the clearer it becomes that there is more that unites than divides us.  If we sharpen the edges of our identities to the point where one aspect of ourselves is all that matters, then the differences between us seem vast and it becomes easy to mistrust and dislike.  However I believe it is possible to create a work environment where even the most fundamental differences can be overcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, it’s not always necessary to talk about our differences.  I was once in a difficult conversation with a colleague who told me she was frightened I might start talking about my views.  I explained I’d much rather talk about our shared love of the same film director.  Sometimes discretion is the better part of valour.  However, there are times when difficult discussions are relevant.  And then it’s vital to understand that to disagree is not to dehumanise.  To be faced with polite disagreement over your world view is not to be rendered &lt;em&gt;unsafe&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, for all the lip service paid to ‘diversity’ we seem to have lost confidence in the idea that we &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; all be different – really, profoundly different – and still get on.  We seem to have forgotten that, however much we disagree (and even when these are on matters which go to the very core of our being) we can still be civil, maybe even friends.  That may sound impossibly idealistic, but we actually do it all the time.  Here’s an example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some time ago I was on a train.  It was hot and the journey was slow.  People were being incredibly annoying in the way that only people on trains can; music playing, bags on seats, dogs on seats, screaming children, arguing couples, smelly food, annoying sitcoms played without headphones.  Everyone was doing all they could to assert their personal train space and wind everyone else up.  Then in came this guy.  He was drunk, and slightly dangerous.  He started to pick fights and harass the female passengers.  Everyone went quiet, watching his progress, hoping he wouldn’t pick on them next.  Finally when the train stopped in the next station, the police came onboard and took the troublemaker away.  When the train doors shut and we finally moved off, the drunk man had gone but something else had changed.  Instead of a carriage full of people who slightly disliked each other on principle, we were now united: conversation broke out, people laughed, talked and had fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I’m not suggesting the Civil Service would benefit from a drunk maniac with anger management issues blundering through the office chased by the police.  But this incident highlighted to me that, as well as our fundamental need for individual communities and personal identities, there is another need which is one of the strongest of all: and that is to connect with those around us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And for me this is the real opportunity: by demonstrating confident impartiality, our workplace can create a neutral space which allows us - for all our differences - to step forward to work respectfully and civilly together.  And I’m optimistic that if we follow the basic ground rules, we may find we have more in common than we think, and thus work can become a place to make the connections that really enrich us.  And that is surely a win for us all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover photo&lt;/strong&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@charlesdeluvio?utm_content=creditCopyText&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_source=unsplash&quot;&gt;charlesdeluvio&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/photos/human-hand-neon-signage-AT5vuPoi8vc?utm_content=creditCopyText&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_source=unsplash&quot;&gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Elspeth Duemmer Wrigley</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="tolerance" />
      
        <category term="diversity of belief" />
      
        <category term="civil service" />
      
        <category term="network" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">On 14th November, SEEN was invited to participate in the “Navigating Difference Finding Common Ground” webinar, and interfaith and belief event, which formed part of Faith and Belief Week 2023. This was our presentation, given by a SEEN co-chair, as a part of the panel.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Manifestation, misunderstanding and ‘misgendering’</title>
      <link href="/posts/2023-10-16-manifestation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Manifestation, misunderstanding and ‘misgendering’" />
      <published>2023-10-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-10-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/manifestation</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2023-10-16-manifestation/">&lt;p&gt;A frequent area of discussion and dispute around gender critical views is whether and how much they can be expressed (or &lt;em&gt;‘manifested’&lt;/em&gt; to use the legal term) in the workplace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no simple answer to this question as each situation will turn on its own unique facts, but the caselaw is clear that there can be no blanket prohibition on the expression of gender critical views.  There might be circumstances where there is a good reason to curtail the expression of gender critical views (or indeed another protected belief).  However, any actions to curtail any protected belief cannot be taken lightly.  It must have a clear justification and must be proportionate.  A careful consideration of the facts will be needed before making any decision, to minimise legal risk and avoid creating unfairness and inequality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article focuses on what the law currently says on the expression of gender critical beliefs and highlights areas of legal ambiguity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-right-to-freedom-of-thoughts-belief-and-religion&quot;&gt;The right to freedom of thoughts, belief and religion&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The principle that lies behind the right to manifest a protected belief is the right to freedom of thought, belief and religion.  The right to express all protected beliefs in some way is enshrined in Article 9 of the European Convention on Human Rights (&lt;em&gt;“ECHR”&lt;/em&gt;), which includes the right to not only privately hold a belief, but to manifest it publicly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This right has been integrated into the Equality Act 2010 (&lt;em&gt;“Equality Act”&lt;/em&gt;) which makes ‘religion and belief’ a ‘protected characteristic’ under s.4.  The scope of ‘religion and belief’ is defined in s.10 and in caselaw and includes any religion or religious or philosophical belief&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, including a lack of belief.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-expression-of-gender-critical-beliefs&quot;&gt;The expression of gender critical beliefs&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turning now to gender critical views.  When considering if conduct restricting the expression of gender critical beliefs is lawful, there are two tests.  The first is whether gender critical views are ‘protected’ by the Equality Act.  The second is whether the precise way they are being manifested is lawful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;are-gender-critical-beliefs-protected-by-law&quot;&gt;Are gender critical beliefs protected by law?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here the law is settled, and the answer straightforward: yes they are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The test for whether a belief falls under s.10 and qualifies for protection under the Equality Act is set out in the case of &lt;em&gt;Grainger&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;  Gender critical beliefs – the belief that biological sex is real, important and immutable – qualifies for protection under s.10 following the well-known case of &lt;em&gt;Forstater&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;manifestation-of-gender-critical-beliefs&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Manifestation”&lt;/em&gt; of gender critical beliefs&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether a belief is protected is only the first limb to consider.  There is also the question of whether and how a belief can be manifested.   It is here that the law is more complex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start with the question of what ‘manifestation’ actually means.  Legally speaking, the term is broad when applied to beliefs and covers a wide range of ways in which a protected belief is expressed or made known to others.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing the law is clear on is that the right to manifest protected beliefs is extremely important.  As the case of &lt;em&gt;Higgs&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; highlighted (in relation to the Equality Act), the freedom to manifest a protected belief and to express views relating to that belief are &lt;em&gt;“essential rights in any democracy, whether or not the belief in question is popular or mainstream and even if its expression may offend”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is important and worth reflecting on, because it is sometimes suggested that the opposite applies to gender critical views.  Although the belief that biological sex is real, immutable and important is widely held, it is sometimes claimed that this is a controversial view which could cause offence to some people, and it is therefore always inappropriate to express this view in the workplace.  This is not the case.  The Courts have set a high threshold for the restriction of the manifestation of a protected belief, including gender critical beliefs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, while the expression of protected beliefs is regarded as a fundamental democratic right, it can nevertheless be lawfully curtailed in limited circumstances. To understand the circumstances in which this can happen, the first step is to return to where the concept originates, in the ECHR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both Article 9 and Article 10 of the ECHR are &lt;em&gt;qualified&lt;/em&gt; rights, which means they can be restricted provided the following three tests are met.  The restriction in question must be:
prescribed by law;
in the pursuit of a &lt;em&gt;legitimate&lt;/em&gt; aim; and,
necessary in a democratic society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any interference must also be &lt;em&gt;proportionate&lt;/em&gt; (see endnote &lt;a href=&quot;#bank-mellat-v-hmt-2013-uksc-39&quot;&gt;Bank Mellat v HMT 2013&lt;/a&gt;).  The principles to be applied in deciding whether an interference is ‘proportionate’ are set out in detail in the Employment Appeals Tribunal case of &lt;em&gt;Higgs&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;#higgs-v-farmores-school-2023-eat-89&quot;&gt;seen endnote&lt;/a&gt;), in which the Tribunal said that there are a number of tests that need to be met, and that serious thought and consideration should be given to all these factors by any organisation seeking to introduce a policy restricting the manifestation of belief.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is, in short, not a decision to take lightly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-about-some-practical-advice-for-example-on-issues-such-as-misgendering&quot;&gt;What about some practical advice, for example on issues such as misgendering?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The law remains big on principles and tests, and relatively sparse on precise examples, although more cases are slowly testing the parameters of gender critical beliefs and their expression.  However, the Courts have given some indication of the type of conduct that would be a permissible manifestation of a protected belief and what would not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;Forstater&lt;/em&gt;, the Employment Appeal Tribunal (&lt;em&gt;“EAT”&lt;/em&gt;) was clear that &lt;strong&gt;there cannot be a blanket ban on the expression of gender critical beliefs&lt;/strong&gt; (or indeed any protected belief).   We have highlighted this, because there continue to be instances where it is suggested that gender critical beliefs simply don’t have an active and visible place in the workplace.  The law states that they do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite some claims to the contrary, the EAT in the case of &lt;em&gt;Forstater&lt;/em&gt; did not find that it is never okay to misgender in the workplace.  In fact, the EAT concluded that referring to a person by their biological sex, rather than their preferred gender, &lt;em&gt;would &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; necessarily constitute conduct that could justifiably be curtailed&lt;/em&gt;.  Whether it was acceptable or not would depend entirely on the circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Equally importantly, &lt;em&gt;the fact that others might be offended by gender critical views&lt;/em&gt; is entirely subjective and does not, in itself, give rise to any justification to restrict the expression of that belief.  The EAT was very clear that the Claimant (Maya Forstater) could &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; be required to refer to a transwoman as a woman (or face accusations of harassment), as &lt;em&gt;this would constitute a blanket ban on the expression of her belief which could not possibly be proportionate&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:6&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This said, everyone in the workplace (whatever their protected beliefs, or lack thereof) are subject to the same prohibitions on discrimination, victimisation and harassment under the Equality Act.   It is important to state that &lt;em&gt;deliberate and gratuitous ‘misgendering’&lt;/em&gt; (referring to a transgender person as their biological sex, or conversely – and equally – referring to a gender critical person or a person who does not believe in gender identity theory as &lt;em&gt;‘cis’&lt;/em&gt;) &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; constitute harassment.  The same is likely to be true of attempts to exert pressure on colleagues to convert to a particular protected belief&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:7&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:7&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, something that would be as true for those with gender critical beliefs as those who believe passionately in ideas around gender identity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Forstater&lt;/em&gt; is the best-known case on manifestation of gender critical beliefs, but further guidance can be found in two other subsequent cases, Mackareth&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:8&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:8&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and Fahmy&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:9&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:9&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.  More are likely to follow, as case law is developing on this point.  In &lt;em&gt;Fahmy&lt;/em&gt;, the Employment Tribunal found that an employee had been subjected to harassment for holding and expressing gender critical beliefs at work. Other employees had described the Claimant’s gender critical views as &lt;em&gt;“anti-trans”&lt;/em&gt; and compared her beliefs to racism, sexism and other forms of bigotry and the Employment Tribunal found that this response to the Claimant’s gender critical beliefs &lt;em&gt;“went beyond the reasonable expression of a personal opinion in terms which were highly derogatory”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both gender critical beliefs and their manifestation are protected by the law, which means that any limitation imposed on the way in which gender critical views can be manifested must be prescribed by law and necessary for the protection of the rights of others (and meet the additional tests, such as proportionality).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst the law is now settled on whether gender critical beliefs are protected, the question on how far they can be expressed or manifest, remains complex and nuanced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each situation turns on its individual facts and there are no blanket prohibitions or impunities as to exactly how a person may manifest gender critical beliefs or when curtailments will be justified.  However, two things are clear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, anyone who suggests that gender critical beliefs can be held but should not be manifested in the workplace (for whatever reason) is just wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, there is no hierarchy of rights or protected characteristics.  Employers should not make the mistake of prioritising the interests, feelings or perspectives of one protected group or set of beliefs over another, for &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; reason.  This is also true of decisions on when and how protected beliefs can be manifested.  Not only is this a fundamental part of a democratic society, it is essential in an inclusive, diverse and politically impartial Civil Service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover photo by &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@lunarts?utm_content=creditCopyText&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_source=unsplash&quot;&gt;Volodymyr Hryshchenko&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/photos/V5vqWC9gyEU?utm_content=creditCopyText&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_source=unsplash&quot;&gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;•·················•·················•&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;end-notes&quot;&gt;END NOTES&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;bank-mellat-v-hmt-2013-uksc-39&quot;&gt;Bank Mellat v HMT [2013] UKSC 39&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bailii.org/uk/cases/UKSC/2013/39.html&quot;&gt;this case&lt;/a&gt; the Supreme Court identified the correct test for proportionality in this context as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is the objective of the measure sufficiently important to justify the limitation of a protected right?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is the measure rationally connected to the objective?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Could a less intrusive measure have been used without unacceptably compromising the achievement of the objective?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Whether, balancing the severity of the measure’s effects on the rights of the persons to whom it applies against the importance of the objective, to the extent that the measure will contribute to its achievement, the former outweighs the latter.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;higgs-v-farmores-school-2023-eat-89&quot;&gt;Higgs v Farmore’s School [2023] EAT 89&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/employment-appeal-tribunal-decisions/mrs-kristie-higgs-v-1-farmors-school-2-archbishops-council-of-the-church-of-england-2023-eat-89-eat-89&quot;&gt;This case&lt;/a&gt; concerned a Christian employee who had been suspended and subsequently dismissed for gross misconduct by her employer (a school) because she had posted on social media about her views on ‘gender fluidity’ and same sex marriage.  The ET had found that the Claimant had not been discriminated against or harassed because of her protected belief, as there was not a sufficient nexus between her belief and the way in which she had manifested them. On appeal, the EAT found that the ET had taken the wrong approach and has remitted the case back to the ET for a proper determination of whether the Claimant’s dismissal was because of the manifestation of her protected belief or because of a justified objection to the way in which her belief was manifested, i.e. was the dismissal a proportionate response to the manifestation of a protected belief. (At the time of writing the case is ongoing).  In reaching its decision the EAT followed the proportionality test set out in Mellat, and at para 94 set out the following principles to be considered when considering proportionality:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;“foundational nature of the rights”&lt;/em&gt; must be recognised. The freedom to manifest a protected belief and to express views relating to that belief are &lt;em&gt;“essential rights in any democracy, whether or not the belief in question is popular or mainstream and even if its expression may offend”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Where the restriction of a protected belief is justified, the curtailment is due to the objectionable manner of the manifestation, and not the exercise of the right to hold/manifest a protected belief.  In other words, you cannot restrict the right to hold a protected belief, nor to express it.  The only expressions or manifestations that can be restricted are where those manifestations that are objectionable.  (More on what makes a manifestation ‘objectionable’ below).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The question of whether a limitation on the manifestation of a protected belief is justified will always be context-specific and therefore a proportionality assessment must pay careful attention to the individual facts of a case.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The following questions must then be asked:
    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;is the objective the employer seeks to achieve is sufficiently important to justify the limitation of the right in question;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;is the limitation rationally connected to that objective;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;could a less intrusive limitation be imposed without undermining the achievement of the objective in question; and&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;when balancing the severity of the limitation on the rights of the worker concerned against the importance of the objective, does the former outweighs the latter.
 All of these tests must be satisfied if the restriction is to be considered proportionate.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Regard should be had to:
    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;the content of the manifestation;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;the tone used;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;the extent of the manifestation;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;the worker’s understanding of the likely audience;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;the extent and nature of the intrusion on the rights of others, and any consequential impact on the employer’s ability to run its business;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;whether the worker has made clear that the views expressed are personal, or whether they might be seen as representing the views of the employer, and whether that might present a reputational risk;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;whether there is a potential power imbalance given the nature of the worker’s position or role and that of those whose rights are intruded upon;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;the nature of the employer’s business, in particular where there is a potential impact on vulnerable service users or clients;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;whether the limitation imposed is the least intrusive measure open to the employer.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;•·················•·················•&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;style&gt;
.post-full-content {
    background: #ffffffbb !important;
}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;It has been found that philosophical belief can have just as much importance to a person’s life as a religious belief, see &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/employment-appeal-tribunal-decisions/the-general-municipal-and-boilermakers-union-v-mr-keith-henderson-ukeat-0073-14-dm&quot;&gt;General Municipal and Boilermakers Union v Henderson UKEAT/0073/14&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bailii.org/uk/cases/UKEAT/2009/0219_09_0311.html&quot;&gt;Grainger plc and others v Nicholson [2010] IRLR 4&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/employment-appeal-tribunal-decisions/maya-forstater-v-cgd-europe-and-others-ukeat-slash-0105-slash-20-slash-joj&quot;&gt;Forstater v CGD Europe and Others: UKEAT/0105/20/JOJ&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;For conduct to constitute the manifestation of a protected belief, there must be a sufficiently close and direct nexus between the conduct and the underlying belief, though the conduct need not be a mandatory requirement of an established religion for it to qualify (see &lt;a href=&quot;https://hudoc.echr.coe.int/fre#%7B%22itemid%22:%5B%22002-7391%22%5D%7D&quot;&gt;Eweida and others v UK&lt;/a&gt;). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/employment-appeal-tribunal-decisions/mrs-kristie-higgs-v-1-farmors-school-2-archbishops-council-of-the-church-of-england-2023-eat-89-eat-89&quot;&gt;Higgs v Farmore’s School [2023] EAT 89&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The mistake made by the ET in Forstater was to fail to apply the proportionality test.  This led them to (wrongly) conclude that any manifestation of her belief could potentially constitute harassment for the purposes of s.26 of the Equality Act, meaning that there were no circumstances where she could refer to a person by their biological sex and not their preferred gender in all circumstances.  See Forstater para 103-104. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:6&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:7&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;See Wasteney v East London NHS Foundation [2016] 4 WLUK 120). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:7&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:8&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;For instance, in Mackereth the EAT found that the ET had wrongly assumed that a failure to use a service user’s chosen pronoun would in all cases give rise to unlawful discrimination or harassment. Once again it was reiterated: the expression of a protected belief does not in of itself constitute discrimination, victimisation or harassment, and does not of itself trigger justifiable limitations on the expression of that belief. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:8&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:9&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/employment-tribunal-decisions/ms-d-fahmy-v-arts-council-england-6000042-slash-2022&quot;&gt;Fahmy v Arts Council England 2023 WL 04315316&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:9&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>SEEN Network</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="language" />
      
        <category term="diversity of belief" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">A frequent area of discussion and dispute around gender critical views is whether and how much they can be expressed (or ‘manifested’ to use the legal term) in the workplace.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Why SEEN is important to me (v)</title>
      <link href="/posts/2023-03-27-why-is-seen-important-to-me-v/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why SEEN is important to me (v)" />
      <published>2023-03-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-03-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/why-is-seen-important-to-me-v</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2023-03-27-why-is-seen-important-to-me-v/">&lt;p&gt;This wasn’t something I ever saw myself doing, after I came out as a lesbian to my family that loved and accepted me, to walking with Stonewall at London’s Pride Parade. I didn’t know that a new ideology was emerging from internet discussions into general life and into politics. I didn’t see myself as a very political person until I realised what you can lose if you don’t pay attention to the discussions around you. This is why I’m no longer afraid to speak, because I’m now aware of what there is to lose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My life as a lesbian is determined by my sex and the sex of the person I fall in love with. This same-sex attraction is what gays and lesbians have fought to protect in this country, and in countries where my grandparents were born – is still illegal and could get me killed. My elderly, Jamaican grandparents who live in the UK have amazingly accepted me with love—even more challenging for them than me telling them that I was an atheist!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I feel now, in communities expressly for people like me, is a poison of distrust and hate for reasons that are far from reasonable. Apparently now it’s true that my earlier definition of homosexuality is now a statement of hate and a ‘dogwhistle’. It seems like without any balanced discussion, we have now accepted the ideology of gender identity, something I see as similar to adopting the Christian faith of my grandparents without question, because they would feel distress if I didn’t?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gender identity in the workplace forces me to lie, and I like to think that I’m an honest and open person.  Gender identity makes me worry for the boundaries of private spaces such as toilets. Sometimes I go into work sweaty and need to change clothes, and rather than use the small cubicles I quickly switch tops near the sinks. Gender identity puts an extra stress on a lone female, unsure if the toilets will truly be single-sex, and if a male person states his right to use our spaces, we will further worry about what may happen if we show anything but blind faith in the male’s personal belief that he is the same as us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am respectful with my own beliefs, but I do not use religious epithets when talking to a Sunni Muslim colleague, nor pray with my Christian colleague over her lunch. When I tell them I am an atheist I’m not called slurs, but when women say we do not believe in gender ideology we are called “terfs”, bigots and casual violence is promised by either a punch or murder by those of particular strong faith (protest signs in Scotland come to mind). This toxic environment makes one wary of speaking out, which is why I really do think you will not hear many voices like mine, because they are silenced out of fear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really do love my job, I can see the many great ways my career can progress as I learn more. In the end we are trying to be apolitical in our approach to our work with shared goals.  Why would we jeopardise that by forcing people to lie and pretend that biological sex doesn’t matter?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finding SEEN was like a breath of fresh air. It was exactly what was needed; clear information and a perspective to balance out the poisonous atmosphere. They put sex above gender identity and highlight the reality of living in a sexed world by sharing information on female safety and sexist stereotypes or behaviours. I’m also pleased to see them shine a light on forgotten LGB history this February, especially when important figures are set aside or written over to declare their faith to gender ideology. Here I think of a gay man, Malcolm Michaels Jr, known famously as Marsha P Johnson who was an outspoken gay rights activist.  According to Stonewall veteran Fred Sergeant, he was proud of being a non-confirming gay man, and although he had a drag queen act, did not identify as a trans woman, a label that has only been attributed to him by others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SEEN knows this, and as we learn how to engage with each other’s networks respectfully I feel so much more hopeful about the future of the workplace environment. I hope more voices are heard within the Civil Service, and due to the clear divide of politics within LGBT spaces, it is crucial that talks continue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover image:&lt;/strong&gt; “Woman Silhouette” by pixabay is marked with CC0 1.0. To view the terms, visit https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/?ref=openverse.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Mahalia</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="personal experience" />
      
        <category term="lesbian gay and bisexual" />
      
        <category term="diversity of belief" />
      
        <category term="why seen" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">This wasn’t something I ever saw myself doing, after I came out as a lesbian to my family that loved and accepted me, to walking with Stonewall at London’s Pride Parade. I didn’t know that a new ideology was emerging from internet discussions into general life and into politics. I didn’t see myself as a very political person until I realised what you can lose if you don’t pay attention to the discussions around you. This is why I’m no longer afraid to speak, because I’m now aware of what there is to lose.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">On tolerance</title>
      <link href="/posts/2022-11-22-on-tolerance/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On tolerance" />
      <published>2022-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2022-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/on-tolerance</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2022-11-22-on-tolerance/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;reflecting-society&quot;&gt;Reflecting society&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Civil Service has always been a microcosm of British society. At first it was largely white and male, along with the other public and private institutions of the day. But with each new generation the bureaucracy adapted to changing societal norms and became gradually more diverse and representative, with some of the most significant changes happening within our lifetimes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It hasn't been a smooth journey. Progress often mirrors the build-up and release of pressures in tectonic shifts. Legislative and political developments like the Sex Discrimination Act 1975, sexual offences law changes of 1967, 2000 and 2003 (decriminalising homosexuality), the Data Protection Acts of 1984 and 1998, the Stephen Lawrence report in 1999, and the Freedom of Information Act 2000, and others all played important roles in bringing about much needed changes. By the turn of the millennium, all government departments were striving to attain Investors in People accreditation - the then-gold standard for inclusive working practices. Pluralism and tolerance were becoming dominant Civil Service values. Departmental staff networks sprang up everywhere, and could be found representing their organisations at Glastonbury and Pride. There were many issues that needed to be addressed, but the zeitgeist felt new and positive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In recent years something has changed. In 2019 a British woman lost her job for expressing her belief in the importance and nature of biological sex&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, a view never recorded in our history as controversial. Last year a university professor resigned following sustained abuse and harassment by her colleagues and students for having written a book that explored the same philosophical issues&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Stating what many (possibly most) people consider to be basic facts of life is now forbidden in many workplaces, sometimes by human resources codes, but more often by a chilling culture that suppresses substantive discussion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a matter of public debate that we may be witnessing the emergence of a new form of intolerance linked to changing attitudes towards freedom of expression&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. The trend is illustrated in the context of our universities by a survey of UK student opinion in May 2022&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, which found significant increases over the past 6 years in demands for protections from feeling threatened and for banning speakers that cause offence. It seems to mirror a similar shift in attitudes in the US&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;our-launch&quot;&gt;Our launch&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our network celebrates the drive towards greater equality, pluralism and respect for difference over recent decades, and in particular the more tolerant society that this has heralded. We are concerned that this progress is now under threat. Seeing some of the reactions to the launch of SEEN as an officially recognised cross-government staff network has made it clear to us that the Civil Service is not immune to this trend away from mutual tolerance. We have attracted significant criticism and hostility purely for announcing ourselves, and some colleagues have openly discussed getting us banned. Yet our network website (our only communication to date) makes clear our commitments to protection of everyone’s rights, encouraging a diversity of voices, and open and respectful dialogue and tolerance between those with differing beliefs and experiences, as well as the need to respect colleagues’ beliefs (or lack thereof). Some perhaps genuinely believe these are empty words, but they are not. We are the same people you have always worked alongside with mutual respect, and these values are in our DNA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The criticism of SEEN’s launch - which contrasts starkly with the hundreds of supportive messages and membership information requests we have received privately - has almost all focused on the nature of &lt;a href=&quot;/faq/#what-are-seens-values&quot;&gt;our core belief&lt;/a&gt;. It is a belief that our courts have ruled to be “worthy of respect in a democratic society” (and so holds the status of a protected belief under the Equality Act), and is shared by people from all backgrounds, of all political leanings, and by theist, atheist and agnostic alike. This hostile reaction to us has only strengthened our view that, for some in our society, their perceived needs have come to demand the silencing of those who hold beliefs they feel threatened by, regardless of the holders’ stated commitments to tolerance and pluralism. For this reason we would like to use our first blog article to consider tolerance, and why it matters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-paradox-of-tolerance&quot;&gt;The paradox of tolerance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One SEEN-critical comment in particular has stood out from the others by articulating an ostensible justification for silencing us. It referenced a popular philosophical maxim known as the “paradox of tolerance”, attributed to the philosopher Karl Popper, which in its simplest terms states that tolerance without limit will result in intolerance. The specific example Popper gave of those views which should be excluded because of their fundamental intolerance of others was Nazism (which courts have ruled gender critical belief “does not get anywhere near to approaching”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:6&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commonly omitted from such citations of the paradox is the fact that Popper went on to say:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I do not imply, for instance, that we should always suppress the utterance of intolerant philosophies; as long as we can counter them by rational argument and keep them in check by public opinion, suppression would certainly be most unwise. But we should claim the right to suppress them if necessary even by force; for it may easily turn out that they are not prepared to meet us on the level of rational argument, but begin by denouncing all argument &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:7&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:7&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Popper was speaking of philosophies inclined to meet rational argument with “fists or pistols”. A lucid reading of his words makes clear that what SEEN has said does not reflect anything like such a philosophy, let alone merit suppression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, other philosophers like Raphael Cohen-Almagor&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:8&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:8&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; have gone further to argue (again using the example of Nazism) that psychological harm is equal to physical harm. Ideas that cause others distress can, therefore, be legitimately restricted. Some of our critics have made this argument against us, claiming that even a statement of our core belief causes emotional harm and should be withdrawn or taken down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From our perspective there are two problems with this argument. The first is that it ignores the fact that the law protects the reasonable expression&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:9&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:9&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; of a protected religion or belief. The second is this: who gets to decide when a particular speaker, group or people with a particular belief pose a risk of psychological harm so great that they should be kept silent? And how can others be sure the decision is fair? Under Cohen-Almagor’s proposed scenario, judgements on what is acceptable speech seem far more likely to emerge not through consensus but through the dominance of certain perspectives over others. Hence in the context of a policy to prioritise emotional ‘safety’, those holding beliefs perceived as threatening are likely to be disproportionately affected, regardless of their actual commitment to pluralism and tolerance. And the evidence suggests the notion of emotional safety is not impartial: support in our universities for banning speakers from our main political parties is very unequal&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:10&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:10&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of the potential for causing harm, we invite readers to contrast our commitment to pluralism and tolerance with the open hostility we have received from some of our colleagues, which has caused intense distress and anxiety for some members of SEEN. We call upon colleagues who may disagree with our reasonably expressed viewpoints to express their disagreement with respect and professionalism, to tolerate different beliefs, and to call out the use of hostile language. Everyone deserves to be treated with respect and to be able to do their jobs free from bullying, harasment and discrimination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tolerance-in-a-pluralist-society&quot;&gt;Tolerance in a pluralist society&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We do not have to share beliefs in order to tolerate them. We live in a pluralist and diverse society. The beauty of living in a pluralist democracy is that we tolerate and indeed celebrate differences, and we manage to get along, including with those whose beliefs we do not share. A pluralist society allows us all to be free to express our beliefs, within the bounds of the law. For such a society to thrive, as Popper recognised, there must be limits to tolerance. However, these limits are not defined by those who shout the loudest, but ultimately by what is lawful. The Equality Act 2010 provides a legal framework to prevent people acting on their prejudices or disagreements in a way that results in discriminatory treatment of others. It sets out the nine characteristics that are protected by the law&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:11&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:11&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, including the protected characteristic of religion or belief, which is extended to beliefs that must, amongst other criteria, “be worthy of respect in a democratic society, be not incompatible with human dignity and not conflict with the fundamental rights of others”. Harassment of and discrimination against those holding and respectfully expressing such beliefs are examples of genuine intolerance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tolerance-and-expression-within-the-civil-service&quot;&gt;Tolerance and expression within the Civil Service&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Civil Servants we are bound by the Civil Service Code which requires political neutrality. So it is not appropriate for us to express views on matters of political controversy at work; we abide by that restriction and expect others to do likewise. We therefore only assert our right for our views to be heard with tolerance in respect of matters relevant to the workplace. Sometimes it will be necessary to explain the underlying beliefs in order to exercise our rights at work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2022 Civil Service Diversity and Inclusion Strategy&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:12&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:12&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; makes a specific commitment to challenging groupthink and inspiring a greater diversity of thinking. SEEN is committed to working to ensure that departmental policies for human resources and diversity and inclusion, as well as their implementation, reflect this commitment. If you support our &lt;a href=&quot;/faq/#what-is-seens-mission&quot;&gt;mission and values&lt;/a&gt; consider &lt;a href=&quot;/join/&quot;&gt;joining us&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Cover image: &lt;a href=&quot;https://pixabay.com/photos/exhibition-visitors-gallery-viewer-2944064/&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://pixabay.com/service/terms/&quot;&gt;licence&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-57426579&quot;&gt;https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-57426579&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-england-sussex-59084446&quot;&gt;https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-england-sussex-59084446&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/minister-donelan-addresses-policy-exchange&quot;&gt;https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/minister-donelan-addresses-policy-exchange&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hepi.ac.uk/2022/06/23/you-cant-say-that-new-polling-shows-students-want-more-controls-on-free-expression/&quot;&gt;https://www.hepi.ac.uk/2022/06/23/you-cant-say-that-new-polling-shows-students-want-more-controls-on-free-expression/&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2015/09/the-coddling-of-the-american-mind/399356/&quot;&gt;https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2015/09/the-coddling-of-the-american-mind/399356/&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://assets.publishing.service.gov.uk/media/60c1cce1d3bf7f4bd9814e39/Maya_Forstater_v_CGD_Europe_and_others_UKEAT0105_20_JOJ.pdf&quot;&gt;https://assets.publishing.service.gov.uk/media/60c1cce1d3bf7f4bd9814e39/Maya_Forstater_v_CGD_Europe_and_others_UKEAT0105_20_JOJ.pdf&lt;/a&gt; (para 111) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:6&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:7&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/dli.ernet.537231/page/265/mode/2up&quot;&gt;https://archive.org/details/dli.ernet.537231/page/265/mode/2up&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:7&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:8&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Raphael_Cohen-Almagor&amp;amp;oldid=1108658836#Freedom_of_Expression&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Raphael_Cohen-Almagor&amp;amp;oldid=1108658836#Freedom_of_Expression&lt;/a&gt; (and &lt;a href=&quot;https://ora.ox.ac.uk/objects/uuid:e02067a0-ba42-428c-967a-1f3ba11c64bf/download_file?file_format=application%2Fpdf&amp;amp;safe_filename=602327189.pdf&amp;amp;type_of_work=Thesis&quot;&gt;doctoral thesis&lt;/a&gt;) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:8&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:9&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.judiciary.uk/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/Forstater-Press-statement.pdf&quot;&gt;https://www.judiciary.uk/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/Forstater-Press-statement.pdf&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:9&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:10&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hepi.ac.uk/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/You-cant-say-that-What-students-really-think-of-free-speech-on-campus.pdf&quot;&gt;https://www.hepi.ac.uk/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/You-cant-say-that-What-students-really-think-of-free-speech-on-campus.pdf&lt;/a&gt; (p6) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:10&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:11&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/faq/#what-is-the-equality-act-2010-and-what-are-protected-characteristics&quot;&gt;FAQ: What is the Equality Act 2010 and what are protected characteristics?&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:11&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:12&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/civil-service-diversity-and-inclusion-strategy-2022-to-2025/civil-service-diversity-and-inclusion-strategy-2022-to-2025-html&quot;&gt;https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/civil-service-diversity-and-inclusion-strategy-2022-to-2025/civil-service-diversity-and-inclusion-strategy-2022-to-2025-html&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:12&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>SEEN Network</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="network" />
      
        <category term="tolerance" />
      
        <category term="diversity of belief" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Reflecting society</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
