<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/civil-service/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2025-08-26T22:05:27+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/civil-service/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">SEEN | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Sex Equality and Equity Network</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Impartiality and Finding Common Ground</title>
      <link href="/posts/2023-11-21-impartiality-and-finding-common-ground/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Impartiality and Finding Common Ground" />
      <published>2023-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/impartiality-and-finding-common-ground</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2023-11-21-impartiality-and-finding-common-ground/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;On 14th November, SEEN was invited to participate in the “Navigating Difference Finding Common Ground” webinar, and interfaith and belief event, which formed part of Faith and Belief Week 2023.  This was our presentation, given by a SEEN co-chair, as a part of the panel.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;•·················•·················•&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’d be the first to admit that SEEN - the Sex Equality and Equity network - is a strange one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve been a cross governmental network for a year, and our journey has certainly been unconventional: at times controversial, sometimes even fractious.  It’s also taught us something about the importance of a fair and demonstrably impartial workplace, and about how we might find common ground when we profoundly disagree.  I’d like to share these thoughts today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But first: a mystery.  We are not the only network underpinned by a clear set of beliefs.  The same is also true of both the Gender and LGBT+ networks.  These are often stated as ‘trans women are women, trans men are men and non-binary identities are valid’.  Conversely, our position can also be stated very briefly as: sex is binary and immutable and matters more than gender.  So why were we the ones that ended up as a ‘faith and belief’ network?   Well, the answer is because until 2019 you could be fired for voicing these views in the workplace.  The now famous &lt;em&gt;Forstater&lt;/em&gt; case changed that, confirming that our views are worthy of respect in a democratic society.  And so - our belief protected - the rest is history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d like to just repeat something again.  &lt;em&gt;Back in 2019 people were being fired for expressing these views.&lt;/em&gt;  And even now it can still be taboo to state what ten years ago would have been utterly unremarkable.  How did this radical shift happen?  We see some of the explanation lying in well-intentioned workplace activism, perpetuated through training, webinars, blog posts and even email signatures; an activism which became so prevalent that our members tell us they felt shamed and even coerced into demonstrating a particular set of beliefs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But does that even matter if this results in a kinder, more diverse and inclusive workplace?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, the first question is whether it really does.  On the surface such workplaces may appear united, but the veneer of harmony presides over deep discomfort and fear.  We don’t think employees should have their thoughts and beliefs policed, or be pushed into demonstrating adherence to an ideology they don’t share.  More importantly, we don’t think anyone benefits from this approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our network can also be understood as a pushback against this enforced homogeny: the idea that ‘kindness’, ‘inclusivity’ and ‘diversity’ come via only one set of beliefs and fall under only one flag.  We don’t think harmony is achieved by making everyone pretend to believe the same thing.  And because we’ve seen these dangers, we have no desire to replace one activism with another.  I’ll even let you into a secret about our end-game.  What we are aiming for is a return to the impartiality which - at its best - characterises the Civil Service.  Then we’ll happily hang up our SEEN lanyards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what’s so great about impartiality?  It sounds cold and indifferent.  But our experience is that in practice it can operate to do something magical.  Impartiality is nonjudgmental and fair.  It accepts that the workplace can’t be made perfect, it will always reflect our wider, complex society.  It recognises that it’s not the role of our employer to forge us into anyone’s vision of what a better human being looks like.   The real world and the people within it are subtle, complex and interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There will always be differences between us.  But genuine impartiality allows for difference and diversity to flourish.  And diversity is a vital part of the Civil Service’s success. Our steering group came together through our shared interest in this issue, but accidentally formed a microcosm of the diversity that we think makes the Civil Service great.  Within our small group we have members of four different faiths (and others of none), those from a range of social and ethnic backgrounds, some who are lesbian or gay and – of course – both men and women.  There are huge differences between us, in outlook, approach, background and personality.  Working with this extraordinary group of people has taught me first hand how true diversity can make a team more than the sum of its parts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But is impartiality enough?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think there needs to be something else as well.  And so, what?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, we are not in a crèche.  We can’t expect our employer to solve all our problems.  And this is where I think us - employees - have an important role to play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I look for a secular solution, that of humanism and its emphasis on a common humanity.  Since forming as a network I’ve talked to many people, and the more I talk, the clearer it becomes that there is more that unites than divides us.  If we sharpen the edges of our identities to the point where one aspect of ourselves is all that matters, then the differences between us seem vast and it becomes easy to mistrust and dislike.  However I believe it is possible to create a work environment where even the most fundamental differences can be overcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, it’s not always necessary to talk about our differences.  I was once in a difficult conversation with a colleague who told me she was frightened I might start talking about my views.  I explained I’d much rather talk about our shared love of the same film director.  Sometimes discretion is the better part of valour.  However, there are times when difficult discussions are relevant.  And then it’s vital to understand that to disagree is not to dehumanise.  To be faced with polite disagreement over your world view is not to be rendered &lt;em&gt;unsafe&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, for all the lip service paid to ‘diversity’ we seem to have lost confidence in the idea that we &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; all be different – really, profoundly different – and still get on.  We seem to have forgotten that, however much we disagree (and even when these are on matters which go to the very core of our being) we can still be civil, maybe even friends.  That may sound impossibly idealistic, but we actually do it all the time.  Here’s an example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some time ago I was on a train.  It was hot and the journey was slow.  People were being incredibly annoying in the way that only people on trains can; music playing, bags on seats, dogs on seats, screaming children, arguing couples, smelly food, annoying sitcoms played without headphones.  Everyone was doing all they could to assert their personal train space and wind everyone else up.  Then in came this guy.  He was drunk, and slightly dangerous.  He started to pick fights and harass the female passengers.  Everyone went quiet, watching his progress, hoping he wouldn’t pick on them next.  Finally when the train stopped in the next station, the police came onboard and took the troublemaker away.  When the train doors shut and we finally moved off, the drunk man had gone but something else had changed.  Instead of a carriage full of people who slightly disliked each other on principle, we were now united: conversation broke out, people laughed, talked and had fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I’m not suggesting the Civil Service would benefit from a drunk maniac with anger management issues blundering through the office chased by the police.  But this incident highlighted to me that, as well as our fundamental need for individual communities and personal identities, there is another need which is one of the strongest of all: and that is to connect with those around us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And for me this is the real opportunity: by demonstrating confident impartiality, our workplace can create a neutral space which allows us - for all our differences - to step forward to work respectfully and civilly together.  And I’m optimistic that if we follow the basic ground rules, we may find we have more in common than we think, and thus work can become a place to make the connections that really enrich us.  And that is surely a win for us all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover photo&lt;/strong&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@charlesdeluvio?utm_content=creditCopyText&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_source=unsplash&quot;&gt;charlesdeluvio&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/photos/human-hand-neon-signage-AT5vuPoi8vc?utm_content=creditCopyText&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_source=unsplash&quot;&gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Elspeth Duemmer Wrigley</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="tolerance" />
      
        <category term="diversity of belief" />
      
        <category term="civil service" />
      
        <category term="network" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">On 14th November, SEEN was invited to participate in the “Navigating Difference Finding Common Ground” webinar, and interfaith and belief event, which formed part of Faith and Belief Week 2023. This was our presentation, given by a SEEN co-chair, as a part of the panel.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Let’s Talk About Pronouns..</title>
      <link href="/posts/2023-10-18-lets-talk-about-pronouns/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Let’s Talk About Pronouns.." />
      <published>2023-10-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-10-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/lets-talk-about-pronouns</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2023-10-18-lets-talk-about-pronouns/">&lt;p&gt;On the afternoon of Monday, 9th October we approached everyone on our mailing list to ask them what they thought about practices related to the statement of pronouns in email signatures and elsewhere.  One thing was immediately clear: this was something many had been burning to talk about!  Within 3 hours we’d had close to 50 responses, and from there they continued coming in steadily until we received our 100th contribution on Friday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had such a brilliant selection of answers, we’d like to share some of them in full, alongside a general summary and some overall themes. None of the comments included are from the SEEN Steering Group (we’ll follow up with some of our opinions at a later date).  We’ve attributed contributors in the way they’ve asked us to (be that first names, initials or just anonymous). Not all of them reflect views held within SEEN’s steering group, but we wanted to publish a varied selection to promote debate and showcase the diverse perspectives on this issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;impartiality-and-the-cs-code&quot;&gt;Impartiality and the CS Code&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over three quarters of respondents highlighted what they see as the political nature of pronoun declaration and the associated ideology underpinning it (that is, belief in gender identity), with the view that this was not considered appropriate in an impartial Civil Service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some examples of these comments include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;‘It does often feel like we have to show support regardless of if we agree with the cause and in an impartial Civil Service I don’t think that’s right’ – Anonymous, Home Office&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;‘We don’t indicate our affiliation with other ideological beliefs on official emails, e.g. which political or religious ideology we support. It is unnecessary for us to do our jobs and shouldn’t be encouraged as we are public servants who should strive to be as impartial as possible on all matters.’ – Anonymous, DSTL&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;‘As civil servants we are expected to remain politically impartial, a simple rule to which I am careful to adhere. Plastering your beliefs on every email sent out does not imply a political impartiality, quite the opposite.’ – Anonymous, APHA&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;‘Senior managers should be aware of the pressure that this display of partisan support for one side of this highly political issue places on other staff members to avoid expressing non-conforming views.  Senior Civil Servants (in particular) should be scrupulously neutral, and pronoun declarations are anything but.’ – Emma, HMRC&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;‘I see no reason why I should advertise where I stand on an issue which is going to be a political hot potato in the run up to the next election.’ – Gill, MOJ&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These highlight that the adding of pronouns is considered by many to be far from a neutral step, especially when adopted by senior management.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;sexism-womens-rights-and-sex-stereotypes&quot;&gt;Sexism, women’s rights and sex stereotypes&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of our members see stating pronouns as a clear indicator of a belief in gender identity (and that this should always take precedence over sex).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over a third of respondents highlighted how they believed the pushing / attempted enforcement of gender identity beliefs was having a detrimental effect on the rights of women in the workplace. Notably, a number of women in STEM from the MOD highlighted this, including Liz and Clare. Liz said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;‘As a female in engineering, I am normally in the minority.  Although overt sexism within engineering is no way near as bad as it once was, use of pronouns highlights that I’m not in the ‘boys club’ as even now there is a general belief that engineering is not for women.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clare had this to say:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;‘I have experienced a lot of sexism throughout my career in IT and seriously considered going by my gender-neutral middle name before joining the civil service. I decided not to, but I still consider that reinforcing that someone is female exposes them to implicit bias and potential disadvantage. I also think that declaring pronouns is like declaring your star sign, if there was a climate where expressing a lack of belief in horoscopes could lead to a person being disciplined or even fired from their jobs. It’s reliant on a belief and therefore very divisive and because it’s known that some people feel so passionately about it, it’s a reminder that those people could hate you or harbour a grudge against you.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many who highlighted this angle also expressed their concerns about how encouraging the use of pronouns (and thus implying belief in gender identity) was distressing, as it implied a &lt;em&gt;‘right’&lt;/em&gt; way to be a man or a woman, tied to stereotypes of femininity/masculinity, such as &lt;em&gt;‘FF, MoJ’&lt;/em&gt; who said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;‘It promotes an ideology that if you are female who does not [reflect] social roles and stereotypes of femininity you are not a woman, [and] similarly if you are a man who rejects the social roles of masculinity then you are not a man.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;homophobialgbt-concerns&quot;&gt;Homophobia/LGBT concerns&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A number of gay and lesbian members also wrote to express that, in addition to sexism, they believed the practice was also a signpost for homophobia, such as &lt;em&gt;‘Anonymous, DWP’&lt;/em&gt; who said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;‘Lesbians are being banned from creating lesbian only events. As a gay man, listing my pronouns would feel like publicly supporting an ideology that seeks to erase gays and lesbians.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several members also expressed their concerns for those who have gender dysphoria or are struggling with issues around identity, and how the enforcement of this practice may make them uncomfortable, such as &lt;em&gt;‘Anonymous from DEFRA’&lt;/em&gt; who said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;‘I worry that encouraging people to add pronouns to emails or provide them in introductions places undue pressure on those who are still working through issues of gender dysphoria. It’s not work’s place to ‘out’ people in this way.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Others highlighted that while the practice of pronoun declaration made them uncomfortable, they still had great sympathy for those struggling with gender dysphoria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;autism-and-neurodiversity&quot;&gt;Autism and neurodiversity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A number of respondents also highlighted how people with autism or other neurodiverse conditions can struggle with preferred pronouns that do not match a person’s clearly observed sex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;‘Anonymous from Scottish Government’&lt;/em&gt; said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;‘I have always used pronouns in line with my presumption of someone’s sex except where it is clear they wish me to do something different. In that case I tend to default to using their first name repeatedly as using their preferred pronouns makes me feel complicit in a lie which is probably more awkward for me as my autism makes me very reluctant to dissemble.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While &lt;em&gt;‘Kate from DEFRA’&lt;/em&gt; commented:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;‘I also really feel for people with neurodivergence such as autism, I know a lot of folk are worried that they will accidentally misgender someone and with CS buying into the Stonewall narrative that accidentally ‘misgendering’ someone is transphobic I worry that the pronoun pushing will get these folks in trouble and potentially on a disciplinary.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;a-culture-of-fear&quot;&gt;A culture of fear&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many members highlighted the culture of fear that is created around pronoun declaration and associated beliefs about gender identity. Some described having faced direct discrimination and harassment from colleagues for refusing to participate in pronoun declarations to the extent that they are now scared or concerned when they interact with someone who has pronouns in their signature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;‘AG from UK Export Finance’&lt;/em&gt; commented:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;‘it shouldn’t be done… Additionally, the threats when pronouns aren’t included or added by those that want them to be is horrific.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;‘NM from DEFRA’&lt;/em&gt; was one of the many people who expressed the view that it led to exclusion, rather than inclusion:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;‘I feel the use of pronouns in the workplace is unnecessary and alienating to many people. It does not create an inclusive culture, but instead a culture of fear and isolation’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The use of links to external blogs that appeared to push the practice was something also raised by many, particularly &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cultureamp.com/blog/gender-pronouns-in-workplace&quot;&gt;this blog from Culture Amp&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other SEEN members have queried why blogs like the above are allowed, whereas &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.filia.org.uk/latest-news/2021/12/1/should-you-declare-your-pronouns-a-simple-guide&quot;&gt;blogs like this&lt;/a&gt; aren’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;support-for-preferred-pronouns&quot;&gt;Support for preferred pronouns&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the overwhelming response from those who disagreed with the declaration of pronouns, we also received a handful of responses which said they didn’t mind pronouns in other people’s signatures, as long as they weren’t expected to declare pronouns themselves, and as long as they could still accurately describe someone’s sex in situations where relevant.  We also received four contributions strongly in favour of use of pronouns in signatures and work profiles, if necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SEEN welcomes a plurality of views and opinions, and we also look to seek tolerance and understanding between those with differing views.  For these reasons, we have also  included two perspectives in favour of pronouns below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;‘Will from MoJ’&lt;/em&gt; had this to say:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;‘Another potential benefit of having everyone record their pronouns on their profile is that should someone feel the need to challenge whether someone was using the ‘correct’ facilities in the workplace because they were spending too much time in them themselves to mind their own business and return to work, they would be able to confirm how they identify against their profile (if they knew who the individual was) and avoid making a mistake in thinking someone was in a space they shouldn’t have been. If someone was to then bring an issue like this up to management etc to ‘deal with’ they would be able to challenge back about what they themselves were doing in the facilities for so long to be able to notice when they should only be in those facilities to do their business and then return to work, ensuring everyone is protected from those who loiter in the facilities and report them to the police if necessary.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;‘John (they/them) from MoJ’&lt;/em&gt; said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;‘I am non-binary and I include my pronouns in my email signature and it is also configured to appear in Teams via an option in my Global Address List Entry. It allows colleagues to correctly gender me in meetings without me having to state my pronouns regularly or correct them if they initially assume I use different pronouns. This makes me feel much more included, less stressed, and less awkward.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many will have sympathy for John and will choose to add pronouns for the purpose of kindness.  However,  &lt;em&gt;‘Anonymous, DESNZ’&lt;/em&gt; has a different view of the result of such intentions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;My line manager, a pleasant bloke with young children, has ‘pronouns he/him’ after his name on his email signature. Next to it, he has carefully made a hyperlink marked ‘Why do I do this?’, which links to a political blog about ‘allyship’. Whenever an email from him pops up, there also pops up the ‘pronouns he/him’. And every time his name and pronouns pop up on my screen, I get a lurch of dread in my stomach and fight back tears. My lovely, fragile young niece comes into my mind again, I feel helpless, and I can’t concentrate on my work. My teenaged, soon-to-be-adult niece, who has for years struggled with depression, anxiety and obsessive-compulsive disorder. We all helped and supported her as best as we could and hoped maturity and time would work its magic and foster her growing into the strong, healthy young woman we know she can be, just like a million awkward teenagers before her have grown up and worked it out.  Instead, she got caught up in the gender identity movement and is trapped in an alternate universe.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Now she feels ‘special’ and ‘chosen’, rather than just an awkward ugly duckling who got teased by the cool kids. Now she is praised for her ‘bravery’ by the cool kids at her new 6th Form and they tell her the rest of the world is against her and only her ‘allies’ will defend her.   […]&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;We try still to hold her as close as we can and tell her we love her just the way she is, and that she doesn’t need to pretend to be a boy for the world to accept her. We hope we can keep hold of her before she is old enough to buy cross-sex hormones or get on a surgery waiting list to have her breasts chopped off. She threatens both on her darkest days, full of weeping and panic attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Does my line manager know about girls like my niece? Every day, I think, I must talk to him. But what can I say, when our workplace policies allow and encourage ‘pronouns’? He has also been praised as ‘brave’, for being ‘a good ally to vulnerable people’. Does he know how this violent political movement of gender identity, that he so casually promotes with his ‘pronouns’, damages vulnerable girls like my niece? If he doesn’t know, why doesn’t he bother to find out? If he does know, how can he be so callous?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We would like to thank you all for your honesty and engagement in this issue.  Watch out for Part 2 (coming soon).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover by &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@magicetea?utm_content=creditCopyText&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_source=unsplash&quot;&gt;Ice Tea&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/photos/LXQeSfkY660?utm_content=creditCopyText&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_source=unsplash&quot;&gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script&gt;

    document.addEventListener(&quot;DOMContentLoaded&quot;, function () {
        const words = {
            &quot;he&quot;: &quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/He_(pronoun)&quot;,
            &quot;him&quot;: &quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/He_(pronoun)&quot;,
            &quot;his&quot;: &quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/He_(pronoun)&quot;,
            &quot;she&quot;: &quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/She_(pronoun)&quot;,
            &quot;her&quot;: &quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/She_(pronoun)&quot;,
            &quot;hers&quot;: &quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/She_(pronoun)&quot;,
            &quot;they&quot;: &quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/They&quot;,
            &quot;them&quot;: &quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/They&quot;,
            &quot;theirs&quot;: &quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/They&quot;,
            &quot;xe&quot;: &quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neopronoun&quot;,
            &quot;xem&quot;: &quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neopronoun&quot;,
            &quot;xyr&quot;: &quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neopronoun&quot;,
            &quot;ey&quot;: &quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neopronoun&quot;,
            &quot;em&quot;: &quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neopronoun&quot;,
            &quot;ze&quot;: &quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neopronoun&quot;,
            &quot;hir&quot;: &quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neopronoun&quot;,
            &quot;zir&quot;: &quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neopronoun#History&quot;,
            &quot;heer&quot;: &quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neopronoun#History&quot;,
            &quot;zir&quot;: &quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neopronoun#History&quot;
        };
        const wordElements = [];
        var w = window.innerWidth;
        var h = window.innerHeight;
        var post_image = document.getElementById('post-image');

        post_image.offsetHeight
        post_image.offsetLeft
        post_image.offsetTop

        Object.keys(words).forEach(word =&gt; {
            const wordElement = document.createElement(&quot;a&quot;);
            wordElement.className = &quot;word&quot;;
            wordElement.innerText = word;
            wordElement.href = words[word];
            wordElement.target = '_blank';
            wordElement.target = &quot;this link opens in a new window&quot;;
            wordElement.style.left = (w * 0.1) + (Math.random() * w * 0.75) + 'px';
            wordElement.style.top = post_image.offsetTop + 60 + Math.random() * post_image.clientHeight * 0.7 + 'px';
            wordElement.style.color = '#000';
            document.body.appendChild(wordElement);
            wordElements.push(wordElement);
        });

        document.addEventListener(&quot;mousemove&quot;, function (event) {
            const mouseX = event.clientX;
            const mouseY = event.clientY;

            wordElements.forEach(wordElement =&gt; {
                const rect = wordElement.getBoundingClientRect();
                const wordX = rect.left + rect.width / 2;
                const wordY = rect.top + rect.height / 2;

                const deltaX = wordX - mouseX;
                const deltaY = wordY - mouseY;
                const distance = Math.sqrt(deltaX * deltaX + deltaY * deltaY);

                if (distance &lt; 100) {
                    const angle = Math.atan2(deltaY, deltaX);
                    const newX = wordX + Math.cos(angle) * 5;
                    wordElement.style.left = newX - rect.width / 2 + &quot;px&quot;;
                    wordElement.style.top = parseInt(wordElement.style.top) + Math.sin(angle) * 5 + 'px';
                }
            });
        });
    });
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;style&gt;
    .word {
        position: absolute;
        font-size: 40px;
        font-family: seenfont, &quot;Times New Roman&quot;, Georgia, serif;
        background-color: #E9F1DB;
        padding: 20px 14px 18px 14px;
        box-shadow: -3px 7px 3px #000;
        white-space: nowrap;
        z-index: 100;
    }
&lt;/style&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>SEEN Network</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="language" />
      
        <category term="civil service" />
      
        <category term="gender stereotyping" />
      
        <category term="lesbian gay and bisexual" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">On the afternoon of Monday, 9th October we approached everyone on our mailing list to ask them what they thought about practices related to the statement of pronouns in email signatures and elsewhere. One thing was immediately clear: this was something many had been burning to talk about! Within 3 hours we’d had close to 50 responses, and from there they continued coming in steadily until we received our 100th contribution on Friday.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Fahmy v Arts Council England tribunal judgment</title>
      <link href="/posts/2023-09-09-the-fahmy-v-arts-council-england-tribunal-judgment/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Fahmy v Arts Council England tribunal judgment" />
      <published>2023-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/the-fahmy-v-arts-council-england-tribunal-judgment</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2023-09-09-the-fahmy-v-arts-council-england-tribunal-judgment/">&lt;h3 id=&quot;background&quot;&gt;Background&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 21 June 2023, Ms Fahmy won an important &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/employment-tribunal-decisions/ms-d-fahmy-v-arts-council-england-6000042-slash-2022&quot;&gt;employment tribunal&lt;/a&gt; (ET) decision against her former employer, Arts Council England (ACE), the first ET case relating to harassment for gender critical beliefs. ACE is an executive non-departmental public body, and also a registered charity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ms Fahmy was a long-standing employee of ACE and had attended an internal Teams meeting where hostile comments were made about people who hold gender critical beliefs. These comments were made during a work discussion about the award (and removal) of an ACE grant to &lt;a href=&quot;https://lgballiance.org.uk/&quot;&gt;LGB Alliance&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the meeting, Ms Fahmy made comments which made it clear that she holds gender critical beliefs. Following the hostile meeting some of her colleagues circulated a petition with further hostile and intimidating comments which were aimed at all gender critical people, calling them &lt;em&gt;“openly discriminatory transphobic staff”&lt;/em&gt;, and comparing them to racists, while also calling supporters of LGB Alliance &lt;em&gt;“neo-nazis, homophobes and Islamophobes”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In response Ms Fahmy raised a Dignity at Work complaint with ACE asserting that she had been harassed during the meeting. Her internal complaint was not upheld and Ms Fahmy was, wrongly, not given the right to appeal the decision.  Given the circumstances, she felt she could no longer work for ACE and resigned before the final ET hearing took place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a unanimous judgment, the Leeds Employment Tribunal ruled that Ms Fahmy was subjected to harassment for her gender critical beliefs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;treatment-of-gender-critical-beliefs-in-the-public-sector&quot;&gt;Treatment of gender critical beliefs in the public sector.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Comments made by ACE staff members in chat forums were found to have crossed the threshold for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.acas.org.uk/discrimination-and-the-law/harassment&quot;&gt;harassment&lt;/a&gt; when they wrote:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“It is clear that there are members of our own organisation who are happy to be vocally anti-trans and “gender critical”. We shouldn’t have to put up with this any more than we would racist or sexist behaviour. It’s time to stamp out bigotry in the Arts Council in general and that change is to come from the top down and filtered through all departments PS… The mistake imho has come from the lack of clear condemnation of a transphobic organisation and no action being taken against the so-called “gender critical” anonymous who are openly expressing their distaste at the funding being? withdrawn. Much like how our recent antiracism training has illustrated there is an ongoing problem with racism in our ranks that needs to be challenged, this cancer needs to be removed from our organisation. Hatred of others for their differences should not be tolerated.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“… It’s extremely disappointing to see people trying to defend them [LGB Alliance] here of all places”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Tribunal found that the tone and content of these individuals’ emails and comments &lt;em&gt;“went beyond the reasonable expression of a personal opinion in terms which were highly derogatory”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many civil servants will have read and heard similar comments in their own workplace in blogs, forums, training sessions and meetings. SEEN received numerous examples of this sort of language and behaviour in response to our March 2023 Inclusion Survey. 70% of respondents reported that they have either witnessed/experienced bullying, harassment or discrimination (BHD) against staff for having gender critical views or do not feel that their workplace offers a sufficiently respectful and tolerant environment to voice a view that does not align with the belief in gender identity.  38% of respondents reported having themselves witnessed or experienced BHD against staff for having gender critical views (15% didn’t know or preferred not to say).  Of the 47% (142) of respondents that had not witnessed or experienced BHD themselves, only 45% (65) felt their workplace &lt;strong&gt;does&lt;/strong&gt; offer a sufficiently respectful and tolerant environment to voice a view that does not align with the belief in gender identity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This judgment suggests that they are right to be concerned, especially when managers and senior leaders themselves use similar language, or endorse (or ignore) such behaviour by their staff. In Ms Fahmy’s case, Simon Mellor, the ACE Deputy Chief Executive expressed the view in a staff meeting that LGB Alliance &lt;em&gt;“has a history of anti-trans activity”&lt;/em&gt;.  In the words of the judgment, Mellor’s comments &lt;em&gt;“opened the door, for the subsequent petition and comments within that petition. Whether intended or not, it led to the petition”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-the-fahmy-judgment-means&quot;&gt;What the Fahmy judgment means&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Fahmy judgment is not an appeal judgment, and so is therefore not in itself binding.  While it does not introduce any new principles of law it does give an important indication of the kind of comments and conduct likely to constitute bullying and harassment in the workplace of those with the protected characteristic of holding gender critical beliefs.  In this case, such comments included likening gender critical views to hate, transphobia or bigotry, and the suggestion that such lawful views should or will not be tolerated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to note that, although the ACE staff who made the derogatory comments were subsequently disciplined, this did not prevent Ms Fahmy’s claim from succeeding.  Employers have a responsibility to create workplace cultures where such harassment is understood to be unacceptable.   Indeed, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2010/15/section/109&quot;&gt;section 109 of the Equality Act&lt;/a&gt; makes employers liable for what their staff do, unless they have taken reasonable steps to prevent it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is perhaps why the Tribunal was also critical of the ACE Deputy Chief Executive Simon Mellor.  Despite finding that the views he expressed didn’t meet the threshold for harassment, the Tribunal &lt;em&gt;“doubted the wisdom of Simon Mellor providing his personal opinions during a meeting which was available to all members of staff”&lt;/em&gt; and found that it was inappropriate for Mellor to have expressed his personal views and solidarity with one side of the debate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In upholding Ms Fahmy’s claim, the Tribunal found that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The respondent was aware this was a contentious issue. The respondent was aware of the need to update its policies and provide appropriate training with regard to the issue of belief but the Tribunal is not satisfied that the respondent has taken all reasonable steps as required in section 109(4) to prevent its employees from harassing someone with the claimant’s protected characteristic.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is, therefore, incumbent on an employer who knows (or ought to know) that there is contention between competing beliefs held by its staff to ensure that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;its policies reflect the law as it is;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;that training is available to staff, in particular staff who may have to deal with grievances relating to these matters; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to ensure that workplace network activity is conducted with due regard to the protected characteristic of belief.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is also important to note that any approach which seeks to suppress, exclude or prioritise one protected belief over another on the basis that this aligns with organisational values (e.g. purported ‘inclusivity’) or in order to avoid perceived controversy, is unlikely to be found to be lawful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;With thanks from SEEN to one of our members, who kindly summarised the above case for use in our blog.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover image&lt;/strong&gt;: Equality law by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nyphotographic.com/&quot;&gt;Nick Youngson&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a rel=&quot;license&quot; href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/&quot;&gt;CC BY-SA 3.0&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://pix4free.org/&quot;&gt;Pix4free&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>SEEN Network</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="civil service" />
      
        <category term="equality act 2010" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Background</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Understanding our sex-based rights and protections at work</title>
      <link href="/posts/2023-02-17-understanding-our-sex-based-rights-and-protections-at-work/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Understanding our sex-based rights and protections at work" />
      <published>2023-02-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-02-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/understanding-our-sex-based-rights-and-protections-at-work</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2023-02-17-understanding-our-sex-based-rights-and-protections-at-work/">&lt;p&gt;We hear often from colleagues concerned that HR teams, management and staff training providers have made mistakes when they talk about equality law, and especially about sex-based rights and protections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve been given examples of mistakes in relation to women’s issues, including pregnancy and maternity.  Many of our members are lesbian, gay or bisexual and have told us their concerns regarding misleading language about sexual orientation.  Another common error we have seen is where policies or training incorrectly use the words ‘gender’ or ‘gender identity’ when they actually mean ‘sex’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sex-based rights and protections matter for everyone, so it’s important that everyone gets the law and language correct, or rights can be put at risk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone wants to get the law right, so if you find confusing or misleading workplace policies, staff training or communications, it’s a good idea to highlight these so that HR can check and, if necessary, make corrections.  In particular, when any policy or communication concerns the Equality Act 2010, the correct legal language should be used, including the correct names of all the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.equalityhumanrights.com/en/equality-act/protected-characteristics&quot;&gt;nine protected characteristics&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don’t need to be an expert to reach out to your HR team and management if you think something has gone wrong in a workplace policy, training or communication. Any member of staff can set out concerns and ask them for a chat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you belong to a union, you can also tell your union what has happened and ask them to help you, including to talk to your HR team or management.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And don’t forget that union branch annual general meetings and national conferences are coming up very soon. Union members make union policies at these meetings, so if there is a policy you care about, make sure you take part and make your voice count.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Staff networks like SEEN are brilliant for information, support and friendship between colleagues, but only unions have an official right to be consulted by employers and only unions can provide you with representation and legal advice. So if you’re not already a member of a union, why not join one and ask them what they are doing to improve sex equality and equity in the civil service and protect sex-based rights?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please do also continue to &lt;a href=&quot;/contact/&quot;&gt;share your experiences with us&lt;/a&gt; so that we can better understand what support you need. We love to hear from you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can find clear information about sex-based rights, protections and equality and human rights law, including the Equality Act 2010 (and in particular the public sector equality duty (PSED), on the website of the Equality and Human Rights Commission (EHRC), the UK’s independent watchdog on equality and human rights law. Here are some useful links:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.equalityhumanrights.com/en&quot;&gt;EHRC homepage&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.equalityhumanrights.com/en/equality-act/equality-act-2010&quot;&gt;Equality Act 2010&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.equalityhumanrights.com/en/equality-act/know-your-rights&quot;&gt;Equality Act - know your rights&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.equalityhumanrights.com/en/advice-and-guidance/public-sector-equality-duty&quot;&gt;Public sector equality duty&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.equalityhumanrights.com/en/equality-act/protected-characteristics&quot;&gt;Protected characteristics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.equalityhumanrights.com/en/advice-and-guidance/sex-discrimination&quot;&gt;Sex discrimination&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.equalityhumanrights.com/en/our-work/managing-pregnancy-and-maternity-workplace&quot;&gt;Managing pregnancy and maternity workplace&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.equalityhumanrights.com/en/advice-and-guidance/sexual-orientation-discrimination&quot;&gt;Sexual orientation discrimination&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Other links:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/public-sector-equality-duty&quot;&gt;Ministry of Justice - Public Sector Equality Duty&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/letter-to-ministers-on-public-sector-equality-duty-assessments/letter-to-ministers-on-public-sector-equality-duty-assessments&quot;&gt;Minister for Equalities letter of 10 December 2021 to ministers on Public Sector Equality Duty assessments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>SEEN Network</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="civil service" />
      
        <category term="equality act 2010" />
      
        <category term="sex based rights" />
      
        <category term="ehrc" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">We hear often from colleagues concerned that HR teams, management and staff training providers have made mistakes when they talk about equality law, and especially about sex-based rights and protections.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
