<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/personal-experience/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2025-08-26T22:05:27+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/personal-experience/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">SEEN | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Sex Equality and Equity Network</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">SEEN in Northern Ireland</title>
      <link href="/posts/2024-11-18-seen-in-northern-ireland/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="SEEN in Northern Ireland" />
      <published>2024-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2024-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/seen-in-northern-ireland</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2024-11-18-seen-in-northern-ireland/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A member of SEEN based in Northern Ireland provides some reflections on the setting up of a SEEN in Northern Ireland group, and meeting other members of SEEN based in Northern Ireland for the first time.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was towards the end of last year that I first learned about SEEN. And, as the kids say, I finally felt “seen”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with many civil servants, I was increasingly concerned about the promotion of policies based on the concept of gender identity, rather than the protected characteristic of sex, across staff networks. Not to mention the proliferation of practices in relation to identity politics, such as pronouns in email signatures, and the general sense that “diversity and inclusion” meant submission to a strict set of beliefs which I did not share. Bring my “whole self” to work? How could I do that when social media told the horrid tale of what happened to those who were vocal about their belief in the importance of basic biology? It seemed that, wherever you looked, people were bullied – and worse – for raising concerns about the impact of ideas based on gender identity on the sex-based rights of women, as well as on gay rights and the safeguarding of children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet at the time I felt that there was no choice but to suck it up - friends and family warned me against putting my head above the parapet for fear of repercussions, both social and professional. I had resigned myself to biting my tongue and tolerating the avalanche of material promoting ideas based on gender identity politics, until one night on X I saw a post about SEEN.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not an exaggeration to say that SEEN has been a revelation for me. The very fact of knowing that there were hundreds of colleagues out there who share my beliefs and concerns was comfort in itself. But when I dug into the articles on the SEEN website, and got a sense of how genuinely tolerant, civil and professional the network is, I knew I wanted to get involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The journey to establishing a SEEN NI Chapter has been a fulfilling one. I began by speaking with SEEN leaders in other departments, who put me in touch with other NI-based civil servants who had come across the network in a similar manner to me. I met with them one by one, formed connections, and we now have a thriving band of gender critical folk who keep each other sane via coffees and lively chats. What started as a tentative exercise - we joked about creeping around like members of the French resistance - has evolved into a forum in which we can share views, highlight successes, and encourage each other to stand up for what we believe in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without the support of the SEEN NI cohort, for example, I wouldn’t have had the courage to hold a meeting with HR and D&amp;amp;I seniors to raise concerns about our department’s adherence to the Civil Service Code in the context of Pride Month. Or to challenge the views of a stakeholder who was dismissive of gender critical beliefs. In the SEEN NI group, despite our different backgrounds, experiences and politics, we have each other’s backs when it comes to combating overreach and disinformation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there is no doubt that our voices are being heard. As other bloggers have noted, progress can be slow and frustrating at times, but SEEN has taught me what can be achieved when rational, reasonable and tolerant people get together. So I would encourage any civil servant in Northern Ireland who shares our beliefs to get in touch. You’ll have a warm welcome in SEEN NI - to adopt a term that has been weaponised elsewhere, it truly is a “safe space”!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you are a member of SEEN and interested in finding more about the SEEN in Northern Ireland group, or if you would like to find out more about Chapters of SEEN in general, keep an eye out for email correspondence via the SEEN mailing list for contact details.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you are a civil servant and would like to join SEEN please submit your membership request via &lt;a href=&quot;https://seen-network.uk/join/&quot;&gt;our ‘join us’ page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover photo&lt;/strong&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@wwarby?utm_content=creditCopyText&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_source=unsplash&quot;&gt;William Warby&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/photos/a-black-and-white-photo-of-a-rocky-beach-_K1qXCM8yKg?utm_content=creditCopyText&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_source=unsplash&quot;&gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>UNSEEN</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="personal experience" />
      
        <category term="why seen" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">A member of SEEN based in Northern Ireland provides some reflections on the setting up of a SEEN in Northern Ireland group, and meeting other members of SEEN based in Northern Ireland for the first time.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">SEEN in Scotland</title>
      <link href="/posts/2024-11-07-seen-in-scotland/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="SEEN in Scotland" />
      <published>2024-11-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2024-11-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/seen-in-scotland</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2024-11-07-seen-in-scotland/">&lt;p&gt;A member of SEEN based in Scotland provides some reflections on the setting up of a SEEN in Scotland Group, and meeting other members of SEEN based in Scotland for the first time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chilling, silencing, fear and hurt were common themes at the first meeting to establish a Scotland Group of members of SEEN, along with frustration that such emotions are provoked for holding what are in reality widely held and evidence-based beliefs – that biological sex is real, immutable and in many cases important. The group was also surprisingly diverse, containing a mixture of ages, both sexes, and a wide range of perspectives and routes which had drawn them first to this issue and then to get involved in SEEN.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it was this backdrop which made the meeting a little odd – like a reluctantly clandestine and random group blind date. However, it is also what made the meeting feel so positive and productive. An active step to find a voice, connect with others, and make a difference.  Our discussions focussed on ways that the culture of “no debate” is impacting colleagues both in a personal sense and on the performance of the civil service as a whole. From a personal perspective it is clear that the “bring your whole self to work” ethos does not apply if that includes having concerns around the impact of implementing policies based on belief in the concept of gender identity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The group shared their experiences of feeling unable to talk about family issues at work or expressing honest concerns around mixed sex facilities which made them feel vulnerable. This was all compounded by a feeling that unions would not support them in upholding the lawful provision of single-sex facilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More widely, there was significant concern around the impact on quality of work and professional standards in the workplace, such as the ability to freely interrogate policy, taking a balanced approach to consultation on the collection and recording of data, and taking a truly evidence-based approach to decision making. While there are obvious examples of recent legislation in Scotland to which this applies, I was surprised to learn how far reaching the effect has been with implications for so many policy areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SEEN now has over 900 members across the UK and while our numbers remain small in Scotland they are growing. If you are a Scotland-based civil servant and you share these concerns I urge you to find your voice and get involved. By signing up you contribute anonymously through surveys and research. You can also choose to connect with others and get more involved in the Scotland Group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need a voice at the table and with more members our voice will be strengthened and our fear reduced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you are a member of SEEN and interested in finding more about the SEEN in Scotland Group, or if you would like to find out more about Chapters of SEEN in general, keep an eye out for email correspondence via the SEEN mailing list for contact details.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you are a civil servant and would like to join SEEN please submit your membership request via &lt;a href=&quot;https://seen-network.uk/join/&quot;&gt;our ‘join us’ page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover photo&lt;/strong&gt; with kind permission from a SEEN member. All rights reserved.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>UNSEEN</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="personal experience" />
      
        <category term="why seen" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">A member of SEEN based in Scotland provides some reflections on the setting up of a SEEN in Scotland Group, and meeting other members of SEEN based in Scotland for the first time.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Violence against women - A personal account</title>
      <link href="/posts/2023-11-27-idevaw-a-personal-account/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Violence against women - A personal account" />
      <published>2023-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/idevaw-a-personal-account</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2023-11-27-idevaw-a-personal-account/">&lt;p&gt;I am not a victim, but I have been hurt by men. I won’t recount every time as the pain and fear crouches within me ready to pounce at any given opportunity. I am a woman who has served at the altar of men, perpetuating the entitlement that men can do as they please, whenever they please but no more, I am saying no.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I left my abuser; I did what everyone says a good mother should do or you are hurting your children, but the abuse never stops. Fear and intimidation permeate my everyday life, I live in a constant state of flight or fight. I was told my life would be better without him, I would be happy, and I guess I don’t have to put up with walking on eggshells every day as to whether he will explode like broken glass showering everyone and anything in the vicinity with sharp and dangerous shards. I don’t have to cover my children’s ears or usher them out of the room when he was screaming or throwing things. I don’t have him towering over me whilst I cower, but happiness I fear is something I will never know whilst he is still in my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I must share my children with my abuser, who is emboldened by the courts who claim that they believe you, but children need to see their fathers. Every time they are with my abuser I sink into a depression, a dark cloud shrouds everything I do, colours are less vivid, nothing is shiny, it is all dull and I feel a weight all over me, a black dog sits in wait for me snarling his ugly teeth as I anticipate a call where he has finally snapped and hurt or killed my children. I can’t breathe until they are finally at home in the safety of my embrace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t want to hear ‘not all men’ because so many men have enabled my abuser, and his continued abuse. I don’t want to continue to read the horrific statistics that another woman has been killed at the hands of a known male. I don’t want sexist tropes doled out at the pub under the guise of ‘banter’. I don’t want strangling normalised and seen as ‘rough sex’ and if you do not consent then you are ‘vanilla’ and boring. I do not want to hear that it’s not a gendered problem. This is an epidemic of violence against women. I am lucky, I had the financial resources to leave, many women do not, due to societal expectations that women are the primary carers for children and so give up their careers or go part time and then are stuck unable to leave their abusers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am scared every day; I am losing the battle but the resources I need I am fearful to use as these are now mixed sex. I am told that I must ignore my own instincts and violate my own boundaries to be kind but where is the kindness and empathy towards me and women like me? The courts don’t care, the police don’t care, and many agencies and charities set up to support women like me no longer care. So, I will bask in my fear and in the continued abuse because what else can I do? I am kind, I am kind to everyone around me, but no one cares about my problems because I have done what everyone says a good mother should do, I left my abuser. I am saying no to male entitlement, but I am screaming into the void.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://niaendingviolence.org.uk/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;nia&lt;/strong&gt; - niaendingviolence.org.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is one of a series of four blogs SEEN is publishing to mark the International Day for the Elimination of Violence against Women 2023. &lt;a href=&quot;/posts/2023-11-25-ending-violence-against-women/&quot;&gt;See here&lt;/a&gt; for the others.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover photo&lt;/strong&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/unwomen/51737051738&quot;&gt;UN Women&lt;/a&gt; on Flickr (&lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.0/&quot;&gt;licence&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>UNSEEN</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="violence against women and girls" />
      
        <category term="personal experience" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">I am not a victim, but I have been hurt by men. I won’t recount every time as the pain and fear crouches within me ready to pounce at any given opportunity. I am a woman who has served at the altar of men, perpetuating the entitlement that men can do as they please, whenever they please but no more, I am saying no.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Why SEEN is important to me (vii)</title>
      <link href="/posts/2023-07-19-why-is-seen-important-to-me-vii/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why SEEN is important to me (vii)" />
      <published>2023-07-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-07-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/why-is-seen-important-to-me-vii</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2023-07-19-why-is-seen-important-to-me-vii/">&lt;p&gt;Bring your whole self to work is what my employer tells me. Unless of course you happen to believe like I do that sex is binary and fixed from conception. In that case I am allowed to hold that belief (thank you &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.judiciary.uk/judgments/forstater-v-cgd-europe-and-ors/&quot;&gt;Maya&lt;/a&gt;), but not to express it plainly in case it causes offense to those who believe that the concept of innate gender identity is more important in all cases than biological sex, or somehow denies their identity.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;But what about my identity?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When my employer asks for my gender but not my sex, or asks for my gender without giving me the option to say that I do not believe in an innate gender, this denies my identity. My sex is important to me. My sex has shaped my life. During my career I have experienced sexism, disadvantage and discrimination due to my sex and I have had to fight against the stereotypes imposed upon me due to my sex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When my employer asks me to state whether I identify as a woman, this denies my identity. To use woman in this way is to change it from a definition based on sex, to one based on gender identity. I am not a woman because I have womanly thoughts and feelings which are separate and distinct from manly thoughts and feelings - and if you think I am you need to reconsider as this is the very definition of sexism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When my employer allows me to be referred to as cis-gendered, this denies my identity. I am not a woman because my personality happens to align with the stereotypical expectations that society places on me due to my sex, any more than I would not be a woman if my personality did not. And my personality, like that of everyone else I have ever met, is a mix of those traits that society ascribes to be feminine and masculine because stereotypes are nonsense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am a woman because my sex is female. But knowing my sex tells you nothing about me except what my sex is. It does not tell you about my personality, my likes and dislikes, my strengths and weaknesses. There is no trait, characteristic, thought or feeling that I share with all other women on this planet and which is distinct from those shared by men, other than our biology. So I say again, I am a woman because my sex is female.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are all afforded protections in law to prevent us from suffering from discrimination and harassment or to preserve our privacy and dignity because of our sex. But as it stands my employer has no record of my sex and has replaced sex with gender and that is why SEEN is so important to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover image&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/photos/DRzYMtae-vA&quot;&gt;Nadine Shaabana&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/license&quot;&gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>UNSEEN</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="personal experience" />
      
        <category term="language" />
      
        <category term="gender stereotyping" />
      
        <category term="why seen" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Bring your whole self to work is what my employer tells me. Unless of course you happen to believe like I do that sex is binary and fixed from conception. In that case I am allowed to hold that belief (thank you Maya), but not to express it plainly in case it causes offense to those who believe that the concept of innate gender identity is more important in all cases than biological sex, or somehow denies their identity.But what about my identity?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Why SEEN is important to me (v)</title>
      <link href="/posts/2023-03-27-why-is-seen-important-to-me-v/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why SEEN is important to me (v)" />
      <published>2023-03-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-03-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/why-is-seen-important-to-me-v</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2023-03-27-why-is-seen-important-to-me-v/">&lt;p&gt;This wasn’t something I ever saw myself doing, after I came out as a lesbian to my family that loved and accepted me, to walking with Stonewall at London’s Pride Parade. I didn’t know that a new ideology was emerging from internet discussions into general life and into politics. I didn’t see myself as a very political person until I realised what you can lose if you don’t pay attention to the discussions around you. This is why I’m no longer afraid to speak, because I’m now aware of what there is to lose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My life as a lesbian is determined by my sex and the sex of the person I fall in love with. This same-sex attraction is what gays and lesbians have fought to protect in this country, and in countries where my grandparents were born – is still illegal and could get me killed. My elderly, Jamaican grandparents who live in the UK have amazingly accepted me with love—even more challenging for them than me telling them that I was an atheist!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I feel now, in communities expressly for people like me, is a poison of distrust and hate for reasons that are far from reasonable. Apparently now it’s true that my earlier definition of homosexuality is now a statement of hate and a ‘dogwhistle’. It seems like without any balanced discussion, we have now accepted the ideology of gender identity, something I see as similar to adopting the Christian faith of my grandparents without question, because they would feel distress if I didn’t?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gender identity in the workplace forces me to lie, and I like to think that I’m an honest and open person.  Gender identity makes me worry for the boundaries of private spaces such as toilets. Sometimes I go into work sweaty and need to change clothes, and rather than use the small cubicles I quickly switch tops near the sinks. Gender identity puts an extra stress on a lone female, unsure if the toilets will truly be single-sex, and if a male person states his right to use our spaces, we will further worry about what may happen if we show anything but blind faith in the male’s personal belief that he is the same as us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am respectful with my own beliefs, but I do not use religious epithets when talking to a Sunni Muslim colleague, nor pray with my Christian colleague over her lunch. When I tell them I am an atheist I’m not called slurs, but when women say we do not believe in gender ideology we are called “terfs”, bigots and casual violence is promised by either a punch or murder by those of particular strong faith (protest signs in Scotland come to mind). This toxic environment makes one wary of speaking out, which is why I really do think you will not hear many voices like mine, because they are silenced out of fear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really do love my job, I can see the many great ways my career can progress as I learn more. In the end we are trying to be apolitical in our approach to our work with shared goals.  Why would we jeopardise that by forcing people to lie and pretend that biological sex doesn’t matter?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finding SEEN was like a breath of fresh air. It was exactly what was needed; clear information and a perspective to balance out the poisonous atmosphere. They put sex above gender identity and highlight the reality of living in a sexed world by sharing information on female safety and sexist stereotypes or behaviours. I’m also pleased to see them shine a light on forgotten LGB history this February, especially when important figures are set aside or written over to declare their faith to gender ideology. Here I think of a gay man, Malcolm Michaels Jr, known famously as Marsha P Johnson who was an outspoken gay rights activist.  According to Stonewall veteran Fred Sergeant, he was proud of being a non-confirming gay man, and although he had a drag queen act, did not identify as a trans woman, a label that has only been attributed to him by others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SEEN knows this, and as we learn how to engage with each other’s networks respectfully I feel so much more hopeful about the future of the workplace environment. I hope more voices are heard within the Civil Service, and due to the clear divide of politics within LGBT spaces, it is crucial that talks continue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover image:&lt;/strong&gt; “Woman Silhouette” by pixabay is marked with CC0 1.0. To view the terms, visit https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/?ref=openverse.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Mahalia</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="personal experience" />
      
        <category term="lesbian gay and bisexual" />
      
        <category term="diversity of belief" />
      
        <category term="why seen" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">This wasn’t something I ever saw myself doing, after I came out as a lesbian to my family that loved and accepted me, to walking with Stonewall at London’s Pride Parade. I didn’t know that a new ideology was emerging from internet discussions into general life and into politics. I didn’t see myself as a very political person until I realised what you can lose if you don’t pay attention to the discussions around you. This is why I’m no longer afraid to speak, because I’m now aware of what there is to lose.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">An interview with Ritchie Herron for Detrans Awareness Day</title>
      <link href="/posts/2023-03-12-detrans-awareness-day/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An interview with Ritchie Herron for Detrans Awareness Day" />
      <published>2023-03-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-03-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/detrans-awareness-day</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2023-03-12-detrans-awareness-day/">&lt;p&gt;‘Detransitioners’ are people who have taken social or medical steps to change their gender but who later decide they feel more comfortable with their birth sex. Detransitioners are diverse and have varied and complex histories to tell, and we must respect how each one tells their own story and how they would like to be supported, including at work. We are platforming one SEEN member today to tell his own story today, to mark Detransition Awareness Day 2023.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to read more about detransition and detransitioners’ stories, here are some resources:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://genspect.org/&quot;&gt;genspect.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://post-trans.com/&quot;&gt;post-trans.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.detransawareness.org/&quot;&gt;detransawareness.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-chat-with-ritchie-herron&quot;&gt;A chat with Ritchie Herron&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Detrans awareness day this year, SEEN Steering Group member Jimmy spoke to one of our SEEN members, Ritchie Herron, about transitioning and detransitioning and how this affected him in the workplace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;NB: Ritchie has asked us to flag up a trigger warning on this article for colleagues, specifically transgender colleagues, that may find discussion of ‘detransition’ upsetting. Ritchie has advised that the last thing he wants to do is to upset or hurt anyone.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jimmy:&lt;/strong&gt; For Detrans Awareness Day this year (12&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; March) one of our members wanted to talk about his lived experience as a Civil Servant and how his transition and subsequent detransition affected his working life. His name is Ritchie Herron. Ritchie, can you tell us briefly about your history with the Civil Service?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ritchie:&lt;/strong&gt; Yes, thanks for having me along to share my story. I started in the Civil Service in 2006 a few months after my 19&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; birthday. I was fresh faced and just out of college! I began working in a contact centre, an AO role. I was in that role for a long time, 14 years! I got a promotion to EO in 2020 and moved to HR in a business support role, then last year – April 2022 – I got a promotion to HEO, to my current role in potential risks posed by new and emerging technologies. I’m already looking at and working towards my next promotion, I’m really driven now and just going for it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jimmy:&lt;/strong&gt; So working for the Civil Service for almost 20 years, has it overall been a positive experience for you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ritchie:&lt;/strong&gt; My department has been an extremely supportive employer in a number of areas. Funnily enough, just today I was diagnosed with autism, which is something I suspected I had for a long time. I started enquiring about getting an assessment around 2019 I think, but due to lockdown this was significantly delayed. But I think since I started, the managers I’ve had and the staff I’ve worked with, even though they didn’t know I was autistic – and neither did I – they’ve always been incredibly sympathetic and understanding with regards to my clear social awkwardness in certain situations, and known it's not just because I’ve been deliberately difficult! I mean seriously – sometimes I would have absolutely no boundaries in work and would just say exactly what was on my mind! I wouldn’t be rude but, I remember one time talking to a customer and he said ‘Oh I’ve been married for 21 years,’ and I said ‘Really? Do you regret being married for 21 years?’ No filter!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then after a while my mental health started really deteriorating and I started having meltdowns in work, and these meltdowns started to get more and more frequent. I had a really good manager though who was very understanding, even though dealing with me could be difficult. And then I transitioned…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I changed my name from Richard to Abby, initially just a social transition but then aged about 26 I started medical transition – oestrogen and so on. I’m not going to lie – I was an absolute chaotic mess for about 4 years. My behaviour at work got worse, as all the previous issues and awkward social situations I had I now blamed on ‘transphobia’. Seriously – if anyone disagreed with me at work or tried to address my poor behaviours I argued that they were being transphobic. In my defence though I was going through a lot – I had a lot of medical appointments to do with my transition. My direct managers didn’t know how to manage me but their senior manager was really good and used to ask me serious probing questions like ‘do you think you’ve not got a lot of control in your personal life, but you do here, and so that’s leading you to act out at work’, but he used to say it a very measured and sensitive way, so he was really good with me… and then I went through the full medical transition including surgery, and so I had a lot of time off both for the surgery and the after-care… but I realise now a lot of the issues I were going through were actually linked to other things – general poor mental health, OCD, and as I now know – autism. But when I was going through the treatment it gave me a feeling of belonging, that this is the right answer for me for this reason.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I was calmer in work, I wasn’t kicking off all the time anymore. Because of the severity of the surgery and the medication it just… dulled everything. I had no energy. I wasn’t argumentative because I just had no energy. People would say to me ‘you seem so much better’ but I wasn’t, I just seemed that way because I couldn’t act out like I did before because my body had been through so much, been so heavily taxed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jimmy:&lt;/strong&gt; So you’d been in the Civil Service about… 6 or so years before you started to medically transition?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ritchie:&lt;/strong&gt; Medically transition, I think 8 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jimmy:&lt;/strong&gt; 8 years… so without putting words into your mouth, it seems like when you did transition at least you felt on the whole that your senior management were supportive, even though you were going through a lot?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ritchie:&lt;/strong&gt; That was later down the line. Initially nobody knew what to do with me. Then they brought in… I’ll just say a staff network that operates across government. They brought in this staff network to consult with on how to handle me, and to be honest this network just told my seniors that I can pretty much do what I want (!). And don’t get me wrong – there was a good policy around transgender staff but… in practice where I worked, HR had no actual experience of implementing this, but also there were aspects of the policy I didn’t want to follow. So I do feel like I’d put them in a difficult position because I’d put them in a brand new position they’d never been in before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jimmy:&lt;/strong&gt; So no-one in your area had ever transitioned at work before? Is that what you mean?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ritchie:&lt;/strong&gt; No, that’s not it – the reason is I effectively went against the established policy – as I said above. So at this time the local policy was that if you wanted to transition, you privately spoke to your management and HR. Then what you’d do is stage a fake resignation – just tell your colleagues you are quitting. Then you’d be moved to a new area, which you’d start under your new name and new identity, effectively so as to not ‘out’ you as transgender to your colleagues. But I refused to do that, I decided what I wanted to do and I just told everyone – all my colleagues, and I didn’t want to transfer somewhere else I wanted to stay where I was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jimmy:&lt;/strong&gt; So they had a process in place to protect the privacy of staff who were transitioning… but you just preferred to be out there, publicly!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ritchie:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah, I didn’t want to be secretive, at the time I felt I was living my true self and I wanted to be proud of that, to my colleagues and friends in work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jimmy:&lt;/strong&gt; I would be interested to know, from your perspective, as I appreciate that there are staff and throughout the wider Civil Service, who will transition and will be happy with their transition and consider it has been the best option to live their life to the fullest. So with that in mind I’d be interested in how your experience in work went when you were identifying as transgender. Was it difficult for you? Do you think you experienced genuine harassment or discrimination from your colleagues?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ritchie:&lt;/strong&gt; My immediate colleagues on the whole were great, but you know how it is. There was a lot of hearsay and gossip at first when I transitioned. But also… At first I didn’t really know how to dress or style myself. I had short hair and stubble… I didn’t look like a woman at all! And that drew a lot of attention to the point where people would literally come to – to what I would call a floorplate safari to come and see me! So they’d pretend they had a reason to be there, and they’d usually come in twos or threes, with a tour guide who would point me out, and they’d walk past, get slower and just clearly stop and stare at me. And on the rare occasions when I’d have to go to other floors or areas, I’d see people pointing and laughing at me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A friend of mine at the time told me I was just being paranoid, but we were walking together somewhere in work one time, and there was this lass around my age, stood there looking really disgusted and just looking at me, and she called over a colleague and just started aggressively pointing and gesturing towards me. And then my friend just said ‘Jesus, I’m so sorry for telling you that you were just being paranoid’. So it was quite bad at the beginning. But then I found this group, this staff network I mentioned before – and they empowered me, but in a really bad way. And that’s when I started saying everything was transphobic, even when it clearly wasn’t. So because of that it made people really reserved and scared around me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jimmy:&lt;/strong&gt; So even though you may have been given bad advice or encouraged in a bad way by this group, it actually seems that outside of your immediate team it wasn’t a very friendly or welcoming environment for you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ritchie:&lt;/strong&gt; It wasn’t, no. I did get quite stressed out by some of the things that were going on and how I was being treated and stared at. I had a lot of medical appointments at this time, which was great, as I could use them then as an escape. I just wanted to be out of there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jimmy:&lt;/strong&gt; What’s really interesting to me here when you talk about your journey, is that at first you said you wanted to stay where you were and be proud and happy, but then… it seems like that changed and you weren’t happy in work anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ritchie:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah… being happy and proud didn’t last very long to be honest. I think I was quite naïve. And then – it was actually lockdown when I felt I flourished in work! My progression has all happened since lockdown – 2 promotions! And I think that was due to being outside of the work environment. Being at home it was much easier for me to focus and actually just get on with work. I thrived away from the office – absolutely thrived, and I know a lot of people found lockdown really difficult, but for me it was perfect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But yeah at the start – especially the first year and a half, I actually found work diabolically difficult. Just for some additional background, I actually was a really late bloomer – I don’t think puberty really hit in for me until I was about 17, and I honestly feel like when I started on the anti-androgen treatment I was still developing. So then after that first year and a half or so at least then… my body hair had stopped growing and then I started learning how to dress more 'like a woman', I grew my hair out. And I think my face is quite androgynous anyway, like if you didn’t know as long as I dress and present the right way you could easily believe I was female. So effectively I’m saying I started to ‘pass’. So after 2 years or so of treatment, I could see an old colleague in work and they wouldn’t recognise me, and I also had voice coaching so I could ‘do the voice’ too, and I’d be like ‘Oh hi Paddy, how are you today’ and they’d be like ‘who the f*** are you!?’… oh sorry you probably can’t put that in! So what I’m saying is eventually I was able to blend in. But then, people would come and see me for another reason, I’d be out of control, when I’d got through the initial phase and was in the ‘everything is transphobic’ stage I’d be back to kicking off, I’d be really explosive, and people would come see me to see me explode.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jimmy:&lt;/strong&gt; What I’d like to ask you now Ritchie, since we’re talking to you specifically for Detrans Awareness Day, is at what point you decided that transition was not right for you, and you wanted to detransition. Actually, before you answer that – you mentioned earlier it was when working from home during lockdown that you really started to flourish, was it during this period that you realised you wanted to detransition?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ritchie:&lt;/strong&gt; It was, but at that point, I was already disconnected from the trans community, because at this point I had become what they call a ‘trans-medicalist’, which is when you think someone is only trans when they medically transition – take hormones and so-on, which is funny in a way as years earlier one of the arguments I’d had with the cross government staff network I was involved in was that I wanted to support non-binary staff, but at that time they didn’t want to do that. Oh, by the way, I actually want it on record that I was removed from that network when I detransitioned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I was getting on well, working from home, then in March 2021, someone in work put up a post about Detrans Awareness Day. It was actually a gay man who did this. But I kicked off, massively, I said this is hate speech – I complained about him, I got the union involved. I didn’t actually read about what Detrans Awareness Day was or what it was about – I just saw the words and thought this has to be some antagonistic move to hurt trans people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But even though I was doing and saying this, I already had doubts about my transition, mainly fuelled by the surgery and its aftereffects. I mean – I had major surgery in 2018. You can probably guess what the surgery was, without me going into graphic details. And I mean I had doubts, not just because of the issues and health problems I had directly as a result of the surgery. I started to realise that a lot of the issues I had that led me to transition were actually down to other factors – OCD, spending too much time in online communities, bullying, and what I suspected was autism. There were a lot of issues that made transition seem like an appealing option to me, and I realised this too late. So I’d seen that Detrans Awareness Day post, and I was very very reactive, but then about 6 months later I just thought, I need to look into this properly. I’m going to disprove all this ‘TERFy’ nonsense, and I can do this because I’m smart… because I’m the smartest trans person alive (laughs).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I started reading up on Detrans Awareness Day and detransitioners in general. And you know that South Park meme that’s based on the ‘aaand it’s gone’ and it says ‘I’m gonna read into this 'TERF' stuff… aaand I’m one of them’. Literally – that was me! I was reading all these stories from detransitioners and I realised – there was some deep truth in this. I started reading up a lot on the male side – on the stories of male detransitioners. I started reading stories of people around my age, who have similar thoughts and feelings, and it really resonated with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then in late 2021 I thought I need to do more than just read other people’s stories, I need to talk to people that have been through this. I couldn’t talk about these feelings in trans spaces, because the other trans people would get very defensive, but it meant it felt like there was no one I could talk to, no one, until I found the Detrans Community. Talking to them made me realise there was another option. I’d thought before that to be a man you had to be a manly man and that wasn’t me, I’m not a manly man, I’m a bit camp, I’m attracted to men…. I wasn’t super feminine but I definitely wasn’t masculine. Before I didn’t want to be seen as male because I didn’t want to be seen as a ‘manly man’. I really started unpacking where my gender dysphoria came from, and I thought ‘maybe I don’t have to live this way anymore’. So I cut my hair and instantly I thought ‘yeah I’m just not doing this anymore’ and that was it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jimmy:&lt;/strong&gt; Thanks Ritchie, so before we finish today I’d like to ask – from the point you decided to detransition or to ‘stop living this way’ as you said, what was it like then from a work perspective? How supportive was work when you detransitioned?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ritchie:&lt;/strong&gt; So as this was happening – I’d actually had an interview ‘as Abby’ and was successful and got my HEO role. So when I got the email from my new management I just said ‘By the way I’m changing my name to Ritchie’, and they’ve just been awesome about the whole situation. But they did scramble a bit as they said ‘Oh we’ve been telling people we’ve got two new fabulous women coming in’ so I just said ‘it’s fine you’re still getting two new fabulous people!’ So my new management and actually my old managers and team were all great too, but what happened in the LGBT group my department was another story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this wasn’t the cross-government network I mentioned earlier, this was the departmental LGBT network and I was actually vice chair. What I did was – because I know how the Detrans issue had affected me before – I made a very very tactical decision to say ‘I’m stepping down, I’ve got a few health issues’. And that wasn’t a lie – I have quite a few health issues from surgery and hormones as I think I mentioned earlier. And it’s not that I don’t still support my trans colleagues because I do, I just don’t have the energy and I don’t feel as strongly about the overall cause anymore. And I didn’t make a big deal when I changed my name – I even had a few people contact me and say ‘I don’t know if you know this Abby but your name’s showing as Ritchie and you might want to get that fixed’ and I’d just say ‘nah, Ritchie’s a great name isn’t it?’ and just not make a big deal out of it. But then I told one of the network leads and – I don’t want to say their name but – they said ‘well you’ve lost my support, we don’t need this anti-trans rhetoric’, just because I was talking about my detransition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But remember that guy I told you about earlier that I complained about for sharing that Detrans Awareness Day post? I don’t know what happened to him but I did write to his management and HR then and said ‘I want to withdraw all complaints I’ve made about him, I’m deeply regretful, I’m sorry I put him through this process’. I did all I could to clear his name. He’s not a vindictive guy, he’s so softly spoken, he’s the nicest man you’ll ever meet, just a nice caring individual. But I know I’d seen that one word ‘Detrans’ and I flipped. So that’s why I stepped down from the LGBT network too, I didn’t want to upset my trans colleagues because I know how I’d felt. So now I just stay away from those networks and any LGBT stuff at work, I just don’t get involved, don’t comment. Well OK, maybe I sometimes make comments about putting pronouns in signatures because I strongly feel that that shouldn’t be mandated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jimmy:&lt;/strong&gt; OK so Ritchie I wanted to ask you something quickly again before we finish, because this actually raises an interesting point to me what you’ve just said. I’m a gay man and I’ve spoken quite a bit about how I don’t feel welcome in the LGBT networks across the Civil Service now, and how they don’t want me to have a voice…. So I know you’re saying that you felt you needed to remove yourself from that environment so as not to upset your other LGBTQ colleagues, because what you’re saying would not be welcome in these networks, so aren’t you effectively being excluded by them?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ritchie:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah, of course. But, you know my opinions are my opinions and if you had told me three years ago I would have called myself a transphobic bigot! I guess I recognise though that I can jump to extremes because I’ve got an extremely obsessive nature. But, you know, I’m glad I detransitioned. It’s probably the only obsession I’ve had that hasn’t destroyed me in some way. I’ve had a lot of growth and development from this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jimmy:&lt;/strong&gt; So finally, do you think there’s anything your department or the wider Civil Service can do to support detransitioners more? And I appreciate that’s quite a big question if you can’t answer it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ritchie:&lt;/strong&gt; It’s worth noting here, I think, that detransitioners are still covered under the protected characteristic of gender reassignment in the Equality Act. If you look at the wording it includes ‘anyone who has undergone a process to change their gender…’. So then in internal policy around transition and gender reassignment, you should still be allowed the time off for medical appointments. Fun fact – it’s still the same policy I’m covered under when I need this. And that’s all been confirmed by work. So from a policy side I think we’re relatively good, although I can imagine there may be confusion and uncertainty from some managers and HR staff. So policy side its fine, but support side…. Despite the fact that like I said my managers have been great… it’s still a long way to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jimmy:&lt;/strong&gt; People in work, HR and D&amp;amp;I teams need to listen to people like you and other detransitioners I think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ritchie:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah they do but…. They are not coming from a malicious place. They are trying to protect what they see as a vulnerable minority and they sometimes see me and those like me as ‘bad’ because of what we’re saying and doing. But we’re not bad, and the world isn’t black and white. There’s shades of grey – people need to start thinking of the nuance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jimmy:&lt;/strong&gt; Thanks Ritchie, you’ve shared a lot with us today but also I’d like to say it’s no secret that you’ve become something of a public figure, and have spoken out and done a number of interviews where you try to raise awareness of detransitioners and their stories. I know a lot of the wider issues that you’ve not talked about today as we’ve mainly focused on work, you have talked about in great detail elsewhere. So are there any particular interviews you’d like to signpost so people can find out more about your experience?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ritchie:&lt;/strong&gt; [Blair] &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Gj3qA2A_z3w&quot;&gt;White&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5_cNVkvz7ZM&quot;&gt;Viva Frei&lt;/a&gt; – they were really in depth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jimmy:&lt;/strong&gt; Thanks Ritchie I think it’s really important for people to hear some of your wider experiences and in more detail, and I – I feel like I know so much about you! Not from when we’ve talked before but from all the interviews with you I’ve watched and listened to, and from reading &lt;a href=&quot;https://tullipr.substack.com&quot;&gt;your substack&lt;/a&gt;! But thanks Ritchie, thanks for your time today and we’re really glad to have given you this opportunity to discuss your lived experience specifically with your colleagues across the Civil Service. Is there any final message you’d like to leave us with!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ritchie:&lt;/strong&gt; Just to say, thanks for having me, and JK Rowling is based! &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Cover image: “more foggy road” by Sarah Olmstead, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/esoterica/1369925080&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/2.0/&quot;&gt;licence&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.urbandictionary.com/define.php?term=based&quot;&gt;https://www.urbandictionary.com/define.php?term=based&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ritchie</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="personal experience" />
      
        <category term="detransition" />
      
        <category term="lesbian gay and bisexual" />
      
        <category term="coming of age" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">‘Detransitioners’ are people who have taken social or medical steps to change their gender but who later decide they feel more comfortable with their birth sex. Detransitioners are diverse and have varied and complex histories to tell, and we must respect how each one tells their own story and how they would like to be supported, including at work. We are platforming one SEEN member today to tell his own story today, to mark Detransition Awareness Day 2023.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">International Women’s Day 2023</title>
      <link href="/posts/2023-03-08-international-womens-day/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="International Women’s Day 2023" />
      <published>2023-03-08T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-03-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/international-womens-day</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2023-03-08-international-womens-day/">&lt;p&gt;At my mixed-sex primary school, our playground consisted simply of one big rectangle made of concrete. The playground didn’t have any lines marked on it, and it had no goal posts. And yet every playtime and lunchtime, it became a football pitch for the boys, the goals marked by their grubby jumpers. God help you if you were a boy who didn’t like football, but that’s another story. We girls gathered around the edges, chatting, skipping, cartwheeling, or playing endless games of catch. If we strayed onto the football pitch, the boys met us with shouts and shoves. When the football got kicked out, we were expected to toss it back to the boys in the right direction.  Occasionally a particularly bolshy girl (future feminists of the UK? You know who you are, ladies) would boot the football away into the car-park and then all hell would break loose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We girls grumbled to each other, but it never occurred to us to complain to the teachers. That was just the way it was. Anyway, what would we say? Our child’s sense of fairness couldn’t explain in words what intuitively angered us. There was no school rule that girls weren’t allowed to play anywhere on the playground. There was no school rule against us joining the boys to play football (although I never saw a girl dare, even those of us who enjoyed football outside school). It was just natural that the boys should be entitled to use all the playground, because they needed it to play football. The rules were the same for everyone and so it was fair.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These days we might call our playground rules &lt;em&gt;‘gender blind’&lt;/em&gt;, or that coy phrase, &lt;em&gt;‘gender neutral’&lt;/em&gt;. ‘Gender neutral’ must be good because it means we treat males and females the same and thereby ensure there is no sexism and therefore equality… right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was thinking about our school playground while reflecting on this year’s civil service theme for International Women’s Day: &lt;em&gt;‘equity’&lt;/em&gt;. Equity is our middle name here at SEEN and a key value for us, so we think a lot about what equity means and what needs to be done to achieve it. Equality and equity are complementary concepts of fairness, appropriate to different circumstances. Ensuring equity at work and in wider society sometimes requires treating women and men differently, according to our different rights and needs. The rules might be applied equally but there may still be unfairness, so how do we deal with this?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grown-up life has often seemed to me very like our school playground. Yes, women are allowed to walk around town just like men do, but some men still decide to shout at us and shove us for taking up space. Yes, women are allowed to be in the digital town square of Twitter just like men are, but we’d better be prepared to cope with rape threats, death threats and cyber stalking. Yes, women are allowed to get good jobs, but we still end up being a minority in many of the best-paid professions and getting paid less in almost every profession.  This is especially so if and when we take on that extra job for which there can never be ‘gender neutrality’: pregnancy and motherhood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are no rules specifying any of this inequity, and actually in the UK we now have laws against much of it. But women and girls still continue to be treated unfairly because of our sex. Our reality is not ‘gender neutral’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;True equity means that all of us, women and men, need to work to change our culture in all the small and big ways which will enable women and girls to take up space and thrive in the same way that we allow to men and boys. Until then, true equality remains an illusion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please &lt;a href=&quot;/contact/&quot;&gt;write to us&lt;/a&gt; at SEEN and let us know your experiences of barriers to women in your public service workplace, and what you think can be done to improve equity for women staff. We hope later to publish some of your experiences, with your agreement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally… please join us in taking 3 minutes right now to celebrate International Women’s Day with us and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZrVLL7soS1U&quot;&gt;the wonderful Helen Reddy singing &lt;em&gt;“I am Woman, Hear me Roar”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. We send love and solidarity to all our SEEN members and supporters. Please roar along!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/ZrVLL7soS1U&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Related SEEN articles you may have missed&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Teenage girls and neurodiversity - &lt;a href=&quot;/posts/2023-02-27-why-is-seen-important-to-me-iv/&quot;&gt;https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-02-27-why-is-seen-important-to-me-iv/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Being a woman - &lt;a href=&quot;/posts/2023-01-25-why-is-seen-important-to-me-iii/&quot;&gt;https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-01-25-why-is-seen-important-to-me-iii/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Violence against women - &lt;a href=&quot;/posts/2022-11-25-ending-violence-against-women/&quot;&gt;https://seen-network.uk/posts/2022-11-25-ending-violence-against-women/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover image:&lt;/strong&gt; “Students take a break from school on the playground” by World Bank Photo Collection is licensed under CC BY-NC-ND 2.0. To view a copy of this license, visit https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd-nc/2.0/jp/?ref=openverse.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>UNSEEN</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="personal experience" />
      
        <category term="equality" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">At my mixed-sex primary school, our playground consisted simply of one big rectangle made of concrete. The playground didn’t have any lines marked on it, and it had no goal posts. And yet every playtime and lunchtime, it became a football pitch for the boys, the goals marked by their grubby jumpers. God help you if you were a boy who didn’t like football, but that’s another story. We girls gathered around the edges, chatting, skipping, cartwheeling, or playing endless games of catch. If we strayed onto the football pitch, the boys met us with shouts and shoves. When the football got kicked out, we were expected to toss it back to the boys in the right direction. Occasionally a particularly bolshy girl (future feminists of the UK? You know who you are, ladies) would boot the football away into the car-park and then all hell would break loose.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Why SEEN is important to me (iv)</title>
      <link href="/posts/2023-02-27-why-is-seen-important-to-me-iv/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why SEEN is important to me (iv)" />
      <published>2023-02-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-02-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/why-is-seen-important-to-me-iv</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2023-02-27-why-is-seen-important-to-me-iv/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[This post is the last of &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/launch-speeches/&quot;&gt;four speeches by SEEN members&lt;/a&gt; from our launch event in October. The author wishes to remain anonymous.]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most people have a favourite Harry Potter character.  For some it’s Hermione, others perhaps Dumbledore.  I’ve always been a Luna Lovegood fan.  I liked the fact she floats slightly off synch and doesn’t care for others’ approval.  I liked the fact that she speaks the truth.  I like the fact that she doesn’t mind that she doesn’t fit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used to mind that I didn’t fit.  In fact, there used to be a lot of things that I minded; a lot of things I wanted to change, thinking that if these changed everything else would fit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was at school that I first used to think about cutting off my breasts: one after the other, until my chest was flat again, back to the pre-fall perfection of childhood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was at school that I discovered that the horror of menstruation could be curtailed if I restricted my food intake enough to trick my body into thinking I was starting to starve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end I kept the cutting to my wrists, and my thoughts to myself.  But they were there, these secret desires to strip myself of this unwanted unfolding into a womanhood I never wanted, but which still came: uninvited with its horrors.  I thought without this everything would be better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so, these changes were a matter of intense misery.  So much so that by the time I left school it was a long time since I’d considered myself capable of happiness.  I accepted this was my lot.  I was just unlucky that my body and brain didn’t fit.  Most unluckily of all, I had to navigate this in silence and in solitude.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did not realise then what I know now: how lucky I was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t appreciate how lucky I was not to be promised  the one thing that I really wanted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t understand how lucky I was that no one told me that there was a way out.  For no one told me there might be a way to return first to childhood; or at very least to stop the fall and from there have time to think and (if I wanted) to start again.  No one told me I could then become one of the real people: one of the men.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No one answered my prayers, gave me a reason to stop hurting myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I was lucky because no one let me think that because I didn’t wear little dresses to go out and disco, but preferred standing with the other DJ boys at the drum and bass night in hoodies and combats, meant anything more than the fact that I really appreciated my breakbeats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I knew I didn’t fit in, that I was awkward and perpetually out of tune.  But I was lucky because no one pointed a way to how I could be made to fit: confirmed and curtailed me through drugs and surgery that promised to make me feel ‘right’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a horrible time at school.  It was miserable.  I hated my adolescence and puberty so much I still don’t talk about them.  But I know now I was lucky because never once was I told anything but the truth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center; font-size: 1.5em;&quot;&gt;*&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am older.  Many things have changed.  I’ve found my own way to navigate the complex dance between being female and expectations of femininity.  I have forgiven my body and found gratitude in what it can do.  I better understand my mind and can present as normal for almost two hours at a time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also have a nephew and I recognise something in him that I once knew in myself. He’s lovely, he’s a rare jewel of a human being, not quite of this earth, half angel.  But he’s autistic odd, like me.  He does a lovely turn to Lady Gaga, makes machines and sits inside them looking into the silver-plated looking glass that belonged to an old aunt.  For a while he begged to have his limbs replaced with metal ones so he could become a cyborg.  Recently he’s started sometimes telling me he wants to become a girl, apparently he wants to go to Rainbows with his sister.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These days people prick up their ears at such a combination.  And there are many ways his parents could frame this behaviour.  But if they were to follow the educational resources recommended at his school, they’d quickly interpret these signs to mean that he was trapped in the wrong body and we should affirm his identity as an imperative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily they, like me, are not so sure that there are wrong bodies, any more than there is wrong skin colour or wrong brains.  There are people and they are diverse, and this diversity is complex and glorious.  But being different doesn’t mean wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am glad they don’t share these teaching resources with him.  I am glad no one has told him that his personality means that his body needs changing to fit. I am glad no one has told him he cannot ‘be himself’ without lifelong medication and permanent surgical damage to his body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some boys are sensitive and want to hang out with girls and wear dresses.  That doesn’t mean they need ‘fixing’.   They need to be made welcome and feel celebrated as they are.  I am glad he is being made to feel welcome as who he is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center; font-size: 1.5em;&quot;&gt;*&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like many of you, I’ve been through the wars and having been through the wars I want to protect.  I am determined to protect those I love; those I don’t know but who I recognise as like me; and those who are not like me but I recognise are vulnerable.  I want to protect others so that they have the opportunity to grow up to be the rare, non-conforming, unconventional humans they deserve to become.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not here out of hate, or out of anger, or out of fear.  I’m here because the truth matters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No one should lie, even if those lies are designed to be kind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No one – especially children – should ever be encouraged to believe the lie that they can change sex, and that damaging their bodies will take away their unhappiness.  Lies are complex structures that require constant complex shoring up.  And however hard we try, everyone eventually comes to understand that they have been lied to, and that is a terrible thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of all the kindness that I have received in life, gentleness and honesty are among those I most cherish.  And we owe the most vulnerable the respect of honesty, of speaking the truth.  Everyone deserves that gift.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover image:&lt;/strong&gt;  “Thinking woman” by pacogaitero is licensed under CC BY-NC-SA 2.0. To view a copy of this license, visit https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/2.0/?ref=openverse.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>UNSEEN</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="personal experience" />
      
        <category term="neurodiverse" />
      
        <category term="coming of age" />
      
        <category term="launch speeches" />
      
        <category term="why seen" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">[This post is the last of four speeches by SEEN members from our launch event in October. The author wishes to remain anonymous.]</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Why SEEN is important to me (iii)</title>
      <link href="/posts/2023-01-25-why-is-seen-important-to-me-iii/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why SEEN is important to me (iii)" />
      <published>2023-01-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-01-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/why-is-seen-important-to-me-iii</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2023-01-25-why-is-seen-important-to-me-iii/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[This post is the third of &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/launch-speeches/&quot;&gt;four speeches by SEEN members&lt;/a&gt; from our launch event in October.]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-loss-of-the-word-woman&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Loss of the Word Woman&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to speak about language – primarily the loss of the word ‘woman’ to describe an adult human female  - and its emotional impact on me. Language matters and the loss of our words hurt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve seen a quiet dismantling over the past few years across our public institutions (including the Civil Service) of sex-based language. By ‘quiet’ I mean that it’s happened without any consultation with the group it primarily impacts – women. It starts by replacing the word ‘sex’ (the material fact of being male or female) with the word ‘gender’ (the social roles and stereotypes associated with either sex) and ends with the word ‘woman’ being routinely separated from our female bodies or reproductive functions, and suddenly we find ourselves referred to as cervix-havers, menstruators, birthing parents, lactators, bodies with vaginas, pregnant people or ‘people experiencing the menopause’. These examples aren’t one-offs - they are now seen regularly in NHS information campaigns, women’s health charities, corporate advertising, Civil Service policies, networks and newsletters, and mainstream media news reports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The phenomenon isn’t restricted to the UK. Women’s Declaration International&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, which reaffirms women and girls’ sex-based rights as set out in CEDAW (Convention on the Elimination of Discrimination against Women) recognises that in relation to protecting women’s sex based rights including reproductive rights, protection from male violence against women, participation in sports and the need for single-sex spaces, we are unable to safeguard women’s rights effectively while at the same time, twisting our language to include men.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The words ‘gender neutral’ and ‘inclusive’ might sound positive and well-intentioned and may be intended as a way to avoid hurting anyone’s feelings, but in considering the feelings of one group  - those who find sexed language problematic - we give real pain to another group.  When women say that erasing the words we use to describe ourselves and our reality is painful, (and we do say this) why are we not listened to?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me tell you about my feelings.  When I see or hear any of these female body-part or reproductive function terms such as ‘pregnant people’ instead of ‘pregnant women’, or ‘anyone with a cervix aged 25-64 ’ instead of ‘women aged 25-64’ I experience distress and rage, my heart rate speeds up, my chest tightens, and I feel nauseous. I consciously calm myself before I decide whether to ignore it or to challenge with a &lt;em&gt;‘We are women. Call us women.’&lt;/em&gt; There’s a real emotional cost either way – ignore it and I lose self-respect and feel I lack courage; challenge it and I know I will either be ignored, or receive a dismissive &lt;em&gt;‘this organisation uses inclusive language’&lt;/em&gt; response, which implies it’s my reaction that’s out of kilter, or that my concern is not valid or that my views are fringe. Challenging in a public space can sometimes mean being called unkind, hateful, out-of-touch, or even fascist. Such accusations might be made out of a misguided desire to be kind and accommodating to others but they are often intended to ostracise, alienate and instil fear.  They prevent reasonable discourse and aim instead to silence, to shame and to control. And it works – I know many women who say nothing out of fear. And all this just for believing that adult females should be called women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So where does my anger at this language, which has surprised me by its strength, come from and why does it matter?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was brought up to be a feminist  by a single mother. She would say the personal is political. My emotion doesn’t come out of nowhere. I was a child in the 60s and 70s and learned from a young age that women have had to fight to achieve social and political equality with men, that our biological reproductive role, and vulnerability to male violence, mean that we sometimes require additional legal protections and safe spaces to achieve equality and that one of the reasons girls and women have struggled to achieve parity with men is that men control language. ‘Man’ in the Bible includes ‘Woman’ or does it? The ‘Rights of Man’ – to vote, to speak, to own property, to organise politically &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; include women but it often did not. Whether we were included or excluded was sometimes hard to discern and out of our control. Women were invisible, subsumed by the male default, and separately defined only in relation to men. Our names belonged to our fathers, then our husbands and our history became harder to trace. We began to understand this and for a few short decades that coincide with my life, we started to reclaim female language, history and experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, in a sudden reversal of progress, that I and many others did not foresee, the word ‘woman’ is routinely used to mean – not an adult human who is female, as understood by humanity for thousands of years and as defined in the Equality Act 2010 - but to mean anyone of either sex who says they’re a woman. So women as a separately defined sex class are, if not invisible, then blurred and ill-defined. This hurts because the words woman along with girl, mother, daughter and sister are precious. I remember the charity SANDS - which supports anyone affected by the death of a baby - putting out a communication on social media which did not use the word ‘mother’ once, instead saying ‘parent’ or ‘birthing parent’. This was done in the name of ‘inclusion’. The number of responses from bereaved women anguished at not being called ‘mothers’ was heart-breaking and led SANDS to back down and apologise to those women. Such ability to listen to the strength of this emotion and reflect seems sadly to be rare. Women now have to lobby and complain to each individual organisation, employer and charity just to persuade them to use the word ‘women’ and even then it usually falls on deaf ears which teaches us a lesson. It teaches us that the opinions and feelings of women matter very little to institutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our mothers and grandmothers achieved so much, and social and political parity appeared to be within sight by the 1980s. And now this. We are at risk of losing the language which describes our sex as based in material reality. If that happens, we will have no collective means to describe our female experience or to combat inequality. I despair when I hear the fight to retain abortion rights in the US framed as the ‘rights of people capable of becoming pregnant’. Imagine if the suffragettes had been hamstrung by language that was so inclusive that instead of “Votes For Women!” they’d felt obliged to say ‘Votes for people with a cervix!’  A battle cannot be won without clear and ringing language - ‘A Vindication of The Rights of Woman’!&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; We find ourselves now having to fight just to protect and define the word ‘woman’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are tempted to think that language has changed simply to reflect a more inclusive and equal society, ask yourself why you rarely, if ever, see men referred to either by the NHS or the Civil Service as ‘prostate owners’ or ‘sperm providers.’ They are just called men! Why? In one recent newsletter in my own civil service department  I saw that one staff event referred to &lt;em&gt;‘people going through the menopause’&lt;/em&gt;, and another event on the same page referred to &lt;em&gt;‘men’s mental health.’&lt;/em&gt; Particularly ironic when mental health issues are experienced by both men and women and the menopause exclusively by women. We are experiencing a new and insidious form of sexism and exclusion that comes disguised as inclusion and kindness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I see invisibility shrouding women one short generation after the battle for sex equality seemed to be all over bar the shouting. I say sex equality, never gender equality. I, like millions of women, have experienced girlhood, female puberty, womanhood, pregnancy, childbirth, motherhood, breastfeeding and menopause. These are all experiences exclusive to the female sex. I attended the traumatic and frightening birth of one grandson. My daughter and I knew what being a woman meant during that night and day. It is real. It is not an identity, a feeling or a costume.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Calling women birthing parents, menstruators and ‘people going through the menopause’, is not only dehumanising and insulting but it has the catastrophic psychological effect of dividing women from each other. What does a menstruator have in common with a ‘person experiencing the menopause’ or with a 70-year-old cervix-haver or with a birthing parent? Unless we can say without any qualification that ‘of course they are all women’, the effect is that they have nothing in common other than their humanity which we share with boys and men, and we have broken the cherished link that all girls and women, young and old, mothers or childless, and with or without various reproductive experiences, have in common with each other as we pass from childhood to old age and which we do not share with any boy or man.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want SEEN to be a place in the Civil Service where women can say all of this without fear of censure and to remind every HR department and policy maker to think carefully about whether reducing women and girls to a multiplicity of body parts and functions is kind or inclusive at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover image:&lt;/strong&gt;  “Thinking woman” by pacogaitero is licensed under CC BY-NC-SA 2.0. To view a copy of this license, visit https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/2.0/?ref=openverse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.womensdeclaration.com/&quot;&gt;https://www.womensdeclaration.com/&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.womensdeclaration.com/en/about/use-language/&quot;&gt;https://www.womensdeclaration.com/en/about/use-language/&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Wollstonecraft, Mary, 1759-1797. A Vindication of the Rights of Woman: with Strictures on Political and Moral Subjects. London :Printed for J. Johnson, 1792. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Louise</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="personal experience" />
      
        <category term="language" />
      
        <category term="launch speeches" />
      
        <category term="why seen" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">[This post is the third of four speeches by SEEN members from our launch event in October.]</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Why SEEN is important to me (ii)</title>
      <link href="/posts/2023-01-10-why-is-seen-important-to-me-ii/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why SEEN is important to me (ii)" />
      <published>2023-01-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-01-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/why-is-seen-important-to-me-ii</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2023-01-10-why-is-seen-important-to-me-ii/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[This post is the second of &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/launch-speeches/&quot;&gt;four speeches by SEEN members&lt;/a&gt; from our launch event in October. Named individuals are anonymised.]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good afternoon everyone, I am one of the Co-Chairs of the new Network.  It gives me great pleasure, on behalf of myself, my-Co-Chairs and the rest of our steering group, to welcome you all today to the first meeting of the new Civil Service Sex Equality and Equity Network and I’d like to thank you all for coming.  I’ve opened and chaired meetings with that form of words on many occasions, but it has rarely been so whole-heartedly true as it is today.  This gathering and the formation of this network is something that a group of us have been looking forward to for quite a while.  We have all, for different reasons, felt that there has been a gap in the activities that take place to promote diversity in the Civil Service in that they do not recognise the existence and legitimacy of those of us who consider that there will always be circumstances where sex is important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quite a number of us are lawyers, and we all start from the position that civil servants should uphold the law in all our dealings.  The central focus of our network will be on the sex-based rights and protections that the law provides.  As we state in our constitution: “we will focus on challenging sex discrimination, and upholding rights and protections that relate to sex (including the protections provided to those with the protected characteristics of sex and sexual orientation).  We recognise that ensuring sex equality and equity sometimes requires treating women and men differently, according to our different rights”.  Because the law is so central to what we stand for, we are fortunate enough to have a lawyer who specialises in discrimination law, here this afternoon to give a brief introduction to some of the legal provisions that create and support sex-based rights and protections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are also committed to the protected belief (covered by the protected characteristic of religion and belief in the Equality Act 2010) that biological sex is binary and immutable, that biological sex matters for both women and men in our everyday lives, including for many of our rights and needs in the workplace, and that biological sex must not be conflated with the concepts of gender identity or gender.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What will this mean in practice in terms of the goals we will pursue as a network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It means, for example, that we will push for the Civil Service to collect accurate and meaningful data on the protected characteristic of sex.  Because of the importance of data in understanding inequalities and acting to achieve sex equality, we have also invited a colleague who specialises in statistics, to speak briefly on this topic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also means that we will advocate for workplace policies and practices that contain clear sex-based language, where relevant.  To this end, we are also fortunate to be hearing from one of my colleagues on the topic of language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, in addition to a clear understanding and application of the law, data and language, an understanding of our network would not be complete without an appreciation of the experiences which have drawn many of us to have an interest in this field.  So, you will also hear testimonies from other SEEN members as to why the formation of this network is important to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll give you may own - rather mundane - personal story in a moment, but I wanted to start by explaining a bit more about why we have set up this network and what we hope it will achieve.  I hope most of you will be able to relate to our motivation and support what we want to accomplish.  We have deliberately kept the guest list for this event small and largely limited to people who have contacted us because they wanted to be part of something like this, so that we have the confidence to share experiences here.  But we have some guests who are involved in Diversity and Inclusion in the civil service and hope those guests will also understand and support what we are trying to do in the interests of promoting greater diversity and inclusion in the civil service.  By encouraging a range of voices to speak up and create an open and respectful dialogue, we aim to achieve greater tolerance between those with differing beliefs and experiences and ‘foster good relations between people who share particular protected characteristic and those who do not’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone should have their legal rights and interests properly respected and protected in the workplace.  We recognise that this includes those who disagree with us.  Conversely, just because others may disagree with our protected beliefs, this is not an excuse to vilify us or try to restrict the exercise of our legal rights.  We will strongly resist such an approach.  Amongst our aims is to promote understanding between people with different beliefs and ensure that the civil service properly caters for those who hold all of them, balancing them where necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We very much hope that all those aims will be achieved by this network coming into existence and we intend to make good use of the voice that the network will give us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will now turn briefly to the personal and explain why I care so much about this.  There are three main reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, because I regard the substitution of sex with gender identity in relation to equality aims as a retrograde step for women’s rights.  When I was starting out on my career, my father told me that he was worried about the cost of educating girls and that if I incurred debts in the course of my training, it would give me a ‘negative dowry’, a very sexist and demeaning viewpoint which I did not allow to throw me off course.  Then my uncle, who was a solicitor, told me that he would offer a training contract to my husband, and not to me, because being a trainee solicitor involved lots of ‘out-door work’ and so was not suitable work for a woman! We’ve collectively proved him wrong, more than 50% of solicitors are now women and that percentage is even higher in the civil service.  I have personally proved him wrong by having a successful career as a lawyer.  Both of these views were based on harmful stereotypes in relation to the role of women in society.  I am concerned that an insistence on the idea that everyone has an innate gender identity is a way of allowing those types of stereotype, which until a few years ago I thought were well on the way to being eradicated, back into society by the back door.  The concept of gender identity, whilst proponents describe it as an internal feeling, is difficult to separate from societal expectations of how each sex is expected to behave.  As someone who does not consider I have a gender identity, the idea that if I do not conform to the societal expectations for my sex, I may actually be of a different sex or even gender, seems highly regressive.  If this serves to reinforce, rather than rid us of such unhelpful stereotypes, the consequences for the equality of women, and indeed for all gender non-conforming people, for equity in our society to the benefit of both sexes seem to me to be highly damaging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, I care because of the impact on single-sex services for women.  In my spare time I was for many years the chair of the board of a charity running a women’s refuge.  In the course of that work, I met and my organisation helped many severely traumatised women and their children by providing a safe refuge and a service provided by women and for women, taking advantage of an exception in what is now the Equality Act 2010.  Refuge services are a strong example of the importance of sex-based rights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst of course not all men are abusers, it is surely contrary to a tradition of recognising the need for single sex provision in this are, to up to date evidence on perpetrators and victims and to much good-practice in trauma-informed health care to require female victims of male abuse and their children to live in close proximity to biological male victims, no matter how they identify.  Any traumatised victim is likely to feel unsafe and more traumatised in such an environment, and where biological sex dictates having different needs in any event, such a practice would have been likely to undermine the effectiveness of the service our charity provided (particularly given such services could instead be provided more effectively in separate facilities).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This issue is not directly relevant to the work of this network which will focus on where they are important in our Civil Service workplaces, but it is part of what motivates me to care about this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I also care about the impact of the difficulty of speaking up about sex-based rights on my gay and neurodiverse colleagues and friends, but I’ll let colleagues speak to that shortly.  Please be aware that they cover some sensitive topics in a frank fashion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I’ve set out why we are setting up this network and given you a flavour of my personal motivation.  Some of my colleagues are now going to address specific aspects of our aims and offer you an insight into their motivations.  We’ll take a brief break for networking in the middle of the speaker slots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you have heard from them we’d like to lead a more participative session about the network and its plans.  We’ll try to answer questions but please don’t ask for more personal information from our speakers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, a note about context.  We want our network to recognise freedom of speech and hope you will feel comfortable to share your views.  I am sure you will all express yourselves sensitively though and bear in mind that this is a meeting of an official civil service network and so we need to abide by the Civil Service Code and conduct ourselves accordingly as I am sure you will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover image:&lt;/strong&gt;  “Thinking woman” by pacogaitero is licensed under CC BY-NC-SA 2.0. To view a copy of this license, visit https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/2.0/?ref=openverse.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Mary</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="personal experience" />
      
        <category term="sex discrimination" />
      
        <category term="gender stereotyping" />
      
        <category term="launch speeches" />
      
        <category term="why seen" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">[This post is the second of four speeches by SEEN members from our launch event in October. Named individuals are anonymised.]</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
