<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/violence-against-women-and-girls/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2025-08-26T22:05:27+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/violence-against-women-and-girls/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">SEEN | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Sex Equality and Equity Network</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Elimination of violence against women and girls</title>
      <link href="/posts/2024-11-27-idevaw-2024/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Elimination of violence against women and girls" />
      <published>2024-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2024-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/idevaw-2024</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2024-11-27-idevaw-2024/">&lt;p&gt;Our duty and our honour: what can we as public servants do to stop violence against women and girls?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Entrenched patriarchy at almost every level of society, combined with a rise in misogyny that permeates the physical and online world, is denying thousands of women and girls across the UK the right to live in safety, free from fear and violence.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;  &lt;em&gt;- Reem Alsalem, the UN Special Rapporteur on violence against women and girls, London, 21 February 2024&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;November is a solemn month. Darkness, cold, heaviness, fatigue. We trudge through dead leaves and deadlines. On the 11th November, the knell of Remembrance Day forces us to visualise the horror of violence and the long reach of grief. Slog through two more weeks and we reach the 25th November, the International Day for the Elimination of Violence Against Women and Girls. Whether it’s the split second of the bomb explosion or the slower stealth of the thousand acts of violence which can cripple women’s lives, we remember how fragile we humans are. And we try to puzzle out again that insane equation: the enormous effort and love we give to birth and raise every human compared to how easily a life can be destroyed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this time of remembering, colleagues and I have been reflecting also about why we became public servants. It comes down to this: we love life. In the dark of November, let’s remember the honour we have in being entrusted to take care of the people of the UK. And so, we look forward with hope to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.un.org/en/observances/ending-violence-against-women-day&quot;&gt;sixteen days of world action&lt;/a&gt; for women and girls that the 25th November begins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us use this opportunity to focus our minds on what I believe should be integral to our ethics as public servants: that we must consciously work for the rights, safety and dignity of women and girls. As Reem Alsalem set out so forensically in her recent UN report (link below), the UK has come far in establishing rights for women, at least on paper, and yet, in 2024, we can look around us any day and despair. We still live in a society where male violence against women and girls, in all its many forms, is widespread and often taken for granted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, we think first about the violence at home, which may come from our fathers, husbands or brothers, and we remember the violence from the stranger in the street. But our culture where violence against women and girls, usually from males, is tolerated, is also shaped by our state structures and our roles, as public servants, within those structures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We as public servants take thousands of policy and operational decisions every week which form what happens in our schools, our hospitals, our laws, our job centres, our immigration systems, our social security systems, our police, our prisons and probation services, our care homes, our housing estates, our family courts, our women’s refuges, our foreign aid. The decisions we make can deter or enable male violence. Our institutions and systems can be structures of care and safety, or they can condemn women and girls to more insecurity and fear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None of us looks lovingly at a new baby girl and imagines she will grow up to be the girl sexually assaulted by the boys in her class at school, the teenager forced into prostitution to pay her rent, the mother struggling to raise her children while sinking deeper into debt or having her children taken away because she can’t protect them from her violent boyfriend, the woman in prison with a drug addiction or suicidal in a mental hospital because she can’t cope with her traumatic memories. Or is she just that quiet little woman in the office whom you barely notice, who lives a small life scared by her own shadow, wondering when a man will rape her again?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We as public servants must insist on noticing that quiet little woman, and all the other women and girls who live and die under violence. We refuse to accept violence as normal. It is our duty and our honour as public servants, whether male or female, to see violence and to act on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let’s not just view equality for women and girls as another tick box on an equality impact assessment, that we go through the motions with ‘because of that PSED training’. There can never be equality for women and girls while we continue to build  misogyny and violence into our culture. Today and every day, let every one of us look at how we do our jobs and see what we can do better for women and girls and so make our society better for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We hope you will find some inspiration from the links below, including the good example of our colleagues at the Youth Justice Board. Over the next fortnight, on the SEEN website and ‘X’, we will highlight more of the positive work being done by our colleagues: please do contact us with links to examples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Links:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/government/news/white-ribbon-day-2024-a-call-to-action-for-men-and-boys&quot;&gt;https://www.gov.uk/government/news/white-ribbon-day-2024-a-call-to-action-for-men-and-boys&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ohchr.org/en/press-releases/2024/02/no-time-lose-uk-declares-violence-against-women-national-threat-un-expert&quot;&gt;https://www.ohchr.org/en/press-releases/2024/02/no-time-lose-uk-declares-violence-against-women-national-threat-un-expert&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.unwomen.org/en/what-we-do/ending-violence-against-women/unite&quot;&gt;https://www.unwomen.org/en/what-we-do/ending-violence-against-women/unite&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.endviolenceagainstwomen.org.uk/about/&quot;&gt;https://www.endviolenceagainstwomen.org.uk/about/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see here our articles for IDEVAWG from 2023 and 2022:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-11-25-ending-violence-against-women/&quot;&gt;https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-11-25-ending-violence-against-women/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://seen-network.uk/posts/2022-11-25-ending-violence-against-women/&quot;&gt;https://seen-network.uk/posts/2022-11-25-ending-violence-against-women/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover art&lt;/strong&gt; from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.un.org/en/observances/ending-violence-against-women-day/background&quot;&gt;United Nations&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>UNSEEN</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="violence against women and girls" />
      
        <category term="sex discrimination" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Our duty and our honour: what can we as public servants do to stop violence against women and girls?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Violence against women and girls - language matters</title>
      <link href="/posts/2023-11-28-idevaw-language-matters/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Violence against women and girls - language matters" />
      <published>2023-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/idevaw-language-matters</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2023-11-28-idevaw-language-matters/">&lt;p&gt;Language matters when we talk about violence against women and girls. In the last 15 years we have seen the word woman not being used, replaced with the word people or non-man, or replaced with dehumanising body-part terms such as cervix havers, chestfeeders, pregnant people or menstruators.  Attempting to eradicate biological sex by not naming women as women doesn’t make all the nasty, horrible things disappear and it does not give equality to women. The violence and rapes still happen it just means it is harder to measure something that is not defined. When it comes to violence against women and girls if we cannot name those who are being violated it makes it very difficult to defend them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A couple of years ago a local campaign near me decided to drop the word woman and use the higher level term ‘gender-based violence’ to highlight violence against women and girls. (Gender-based violence covers violence against males and females.) Fantastic branded signs adorned our bus stops and public buildings but no one knew what the campaign was about. It was a waste of resources and money. By taking out the word woman the campaign had forgotten who the victims were - women and why they were victims - because of their sex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prison statistics for England and Wales show that 99% of sexual offenders are male&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and we know that 88% of those offended against in such cases are female.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;  These figures are replicated around the world.  We cannot deny the biological difference here, men are the perpetrators, females are the victims. In the UK rape can only be committed by males.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; When a man rapes a woman he does so because of her biology not because of what she is referred to as. Women are oppressed and violated on the basis of their sex and to deny they have a sex by not using the word woman is gaslighting, which is another form of abuse. A male human is capable of killing a woman with his bare hands and we know that in the UK three women a week are murdered by a man.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pornography is having a massive impact on violence against women and girls. Over 88% of pornography scenes show sexual violence towards women.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Strangulation, beating and rape are the norm in pornography. One in three children have watched ‘hardcore’ pornography by the age of 12.  We are in an era where violence against women and girls is being normalised at an early age in the palm of our children’s hands. Boys are learning that girls can be objectified, humiliated, and attacked physically and sexually. Both boys and girls are learning that it is ‘normal’ for sex to hurt and that violence during sex is ‘normal’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we want to reduce violence against women and girls we have to use sex based language. To acknowledge biological sex matters and language matters helps us name the problem and find solutions. We have to be honest with our children about the harms of pornography and have conversations with them at a much younger age. We have to give them the language to reject the use of pornography so our boys can grow into adult men who can have a functioning sex life and our girls do not live in fear of their next sexual encounter. If women and girls are to achieve equality we have to significantly reduce violence against them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is one of a series of four blogs SEEN is publishing to mark the International Day for the Elimination of Violence against Women 2023. &lt;a href=&quot;/posts/2023-11-25-ending-violence-against-women/&quot;&gt;See here&lt;/a&gt; for the others.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover photo&lt;/strong&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/unwomen/51737051738&quot;&gt;UN Women&lt;/a&gt; on Flickr (&lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.0/&quot;&gt;licence&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/government/collections/offender-management-statistics-quarterly&quot;&gt;MOJ: Offender management statistics quarterly for October 2023&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ons.gov.uk/peoplepopulationandcommunity/crimeandjustice/articles/sexualoffencesinenglandandwales/yearendingmarch2017&quot;&gt;ONS: Sexual offences in England and Wales: year ending March 2017&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2003/42/part/1/crossheading/rape&quot;&gt;Sexual Offences Act 2003&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://culturereframed.org/the-crisis/&quot;&gt;culturereframed.org: The porn crisis&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>UNSEEN</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="violence against women and girls" />
      
        <category term="language" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Language matters when we talk about violence against women and girls. In the last 15 years we have seen the word woman not being used, replaced with the word people or non-man, or replaced with dehumanising body-part terms such as cervix havers, chestfeeders, pregnant people or menstruators. Attempting to eradicate biological sex by not naming women as women doesn’t make all the nasty, horrible things disappear and it does not give equality to women. The violence and rapes still happen it just means it is harder to measure something that is not defined. When it comes to violence against women and girls if we cannot name those who are being violated it makes it very difficult to defend them.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Violence against women - A personal account</title>
      <link href="/posts/2023-11-27-idevaw-a-personal-account/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Violence against women - A personal account" />
      <published>2023-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/idevaw-a-personal-account</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2023-11-27-idevaw-a-personal-account/">&lt;p&gt;I am not a victim, but I have been hurt by men. I won’t recount every time as the pain and fear crouches within me ready to pounce at any given opportunity. I am a woman who has served at the altar of men, perpetuating the entitlement that men can do as they please, whenever they please but no more, I am saying no.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I left my abuser; I did what everyone says a good mother should do or you are hurting your children, but the abuse never stops. Fear and intimidation permeate my everyday life, I live in a constant state of flight or fight. I was told my life would be better without him, I would be happy, and I guess I don’t have to put up with walking on eggshells every day as to whether he will explode like broken glass showering everyone and anything in the vicinity with sharp and dangerous shards. I don’t have to cover my children’s ears or usher them out of the room when he was screaming or throwing things. I don’t have him towering over me whilst I cower, but happiness I fear is something I will never know whilst he is still in my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I must share my children with my abuser, who is emboldened by the courts who claim that they believe you, but children need to see their fathers. Every time they are with my abuser I sink into a depression, a dark cloud shrouds everything I do, colours are less vivid, nothing is shiny, it is all dull and I feel a weight all over me, a black dog sits in wait for me snarling his ugly teeth as I anticipate a call where he has finally snapped and hurt or killed my children. I can’t breathe until they are finally at home in the safety of my embrace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t want to hear ‘not all men’ because so many men have enabled my abuser, and his continued abuse. I don’t want to continue to read the horrific statistics that another woman has been killed at the hands of a known male. I don’t want sexist tropes doled out at the pub under the guise of ‘banter’. I don’t want strangling normalised and seen as ‘rough sex’ and if you do not consent then you are ‘vanilla’ and boring. I do not want to hear that it’s not a gendered problem. This is an epidemic of violence against women. I am lucky, I had the financial resources to leave, many women do not, due to societal expectations that women are the primary carers for children and so give up their careers or go part time and then are stuck unable to leave their abusers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am scared every day; I am losing the battle but the resources I need I am fearful to use as these are now mixed sex. I am told that I must ignore my own instincts and violate my own boundaries to be kind but where is the kindness and empathy towards me and women like me? The courts don’t care, the police don’t care, and many agencies and charities set up to support women like me no longer care. So, I will bask in my fear and in the continued abuse because what else can I do? I am kind, I am kind to everyone around me, but no one cares about my problems because I have done what everyone says a good mother should do, I left my abuser. I am saying no to male entitlement, but I am screaming into the void.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://niaendingviolence.org.uk/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;nia&lt;/strong&gt; - niaendingviolence.org.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is one of a series of four blogs SEEN is publishing to mark the International Day for the Elimination of Violence against Women 2023. &lt;a href=&quot;/posts/2023-11-25-ending-violence-against-women/&quot;&gt;See here&lt;/a&gt; for the others.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover photo&lt;/strong&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/unwomen/51737051738&quot;&gt;UN Women&lt;/a&gt; on Flickr (&lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.0/&quot;&gt;licence&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>UNSEEN</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="violence against women and girls" />
      
        <category term="personal experience" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">I am not a victim, but I have been hurt by men. I won’t recount every time as the pain and fear crouches within me ready to pounce at any given opportunity. I am a woman who has served at the altar of men, perpetuating the entitlement that men can do as they please, whenever they please but no more, I am saying no.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Violence against women. The judicial system is trying – is it succeeding?</title>
      <link href="/posts/2023-11-26-idevaw-is-the-judicial-system-succeeding/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Violence against women. The judicial system is trying – is it succeeding?" />
      <published>2023-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/idevaw-is-the-judicial-system-succeeding</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2023-11-26-idevaw-is-the-judicial-system-succeeding/">&lt;p&gt;I have been a magistrate for over thirty years and prior to that was a special constable.  During those decades views on domestic violence, specifically violence against women have changed considerably – but there is still a long way to go.  In the past, the model was largely the ‘Andy Capp’ cartoon featured in the Daily Mirror from 1957.  Women were subservient, best placed in the home with a single role to provide for all mens’ needs.  The cartoon strip thrived on Florence Capp being unprepared for tea on the table at 5pm sharp and Andy’s violent response to it.  The view of police and the wider judiciary was - then and until recently - largely that if he hit her, she obviously deserved it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have advanced significantly.  The courts have moved from a model where violence in a domestic context was a mitigating factor reducing the assailant’s sentence, to one where it is a serious aggravating factor, resulting in a higher sentence for any comparable level of violence.  Victim shaming at court was previously prevalent (‘she asked for it’ or ‘she provoked him’) to a current regime where most judges (me included) will stop any attempt by a defence advocate to blame or shame the victim.  The system isn’t perfect and there is still quite a way to go to ensure the judiciary supports women in that context, without prejudicing the rights of the accused to a proper defence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Support for women who are victims, or potential victims of violence varies across the country and is afforded a different priority, principally by different Police and Crime Commissioners, the elected policing budget holders in each area in England and Wales.  In Cambridgeshire for example, the commissioner funds the “Bobby Scheme”, a local charity (of which I am a trustee) formed in 2000 which works with vulnerable victims of crime and has long had a particular focus on women caught in, or likely to be caught in domestic violence.  The charity will support victims after an incident perhaps by replacing locks, providing alarms and so on, through to construction of a full panic room, also working proactively on the recommendations of police, social services or others.  Frequently the Samaritans refer women to us.  We have never had to turn down a request for support for want of funds.  Unfortunately there are only a small number of such schemes nationally (about six) and support for victims varies widely, relying on local authorities and charities to fund and provide support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A major challenge which I regularly observe at court is that the defendants accused of violence towards women don’t see that there is any issue.  At a trial I heard within the last month, the male defendant  had hit the female complainant multiple times resulting in severe cuts and bruises and also a broken nose, with enduring physical and emotional pain.  He could not see that he had done anything wrong, as she had (he said) grossly over-reacted to his cheating on her.  Under cross-examination he volunteered that if she had cheated on him, he might have killed her.  Alas that outcome is all too common.  Estimates vary but the current view is that at least two women die each week as a result of male perpetrated violence.  In the case of my trial, although she has recovered from the physical damage, he will have some time in prison to think about what he has done.  Unfortunately, I am not convinced that he will emerge at the end of his sentence as a changed and reformed man.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://niaendingviolence.org.uk/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;nia&lt;/strong&gt; - niaendingviolence.org.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://refuge.org.uk/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Refuge&lt;/strong&gt; - refuge.org.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is one of a series of four blogs SEEN is publishing to mark the International Day for the Elimination of Violence against Women 2023. &lt;a href=&quot;/posts/2023-11-25-ending-violence-against-women/&quot;&gt;See here&lt;/a&gt; for the others.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover photo&lt;/strong&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/unwomen/51737051738&quot;&gt;UN Women&lt;/a&gt; on Flickr (&lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.0/&quot;&gt;licence&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>benjamyn</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="violence against women and girls" />
      
        <category term="sex discrimination" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">I have been a magistrate for over thirty years and prior to that was a special constable. During those decades views on domestic violence, specifically violence against women have changed considerably – but there is still a long way to go. In the past, the model was largely the ‘Andy Capp’ cartoon featured in the Daily Mirror from 1957. Women were subservient, best placed in the home with a single role to provide for all mens’ needs. The cartoon strip thrived on Florence Capp being unprepared for tea on the table at 5pm sharp and Andy’s violent response to it. The view of police and the wider judiciary was - then and until recently - largely that if he hit her, she obviously deserved it.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Violence Against Women &amp;amp; Girls – 16 days of activism</title>
      <link href="/posts/2023-11-25-idevaw-16-days-of-activism/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Violence Against Women &amp; Girls – 16 days of activism" />
      <published>2023-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/idevaw-16-days-of-activism</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2023-11-25-idevaw-16-days-of-activism/">&lt;p&gt;November 25 is the UN’s &lt;em&gt;International Day for the Elimination of Violence Against Women&lt;/em&gt; (IDEVAW).Between then and &lt;em&gt;International Human Rights Day&lt;/em&gt; on 10 December, the UN is calling for &lt;em&gt;16 days of activism&lt;/em&gt; &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; to raise awareness and seek solutions to this oldest and most pervasive of problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Violence against women, by men, is endemic, both globally and very close to home (often literally). In 2020 in the UK, 110 women were killed by men &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; – a level of femicide that has remained consistent over time. In general, a woman is killed by a man in the UK every 3 days, every single year – most commonly a man she knows, or is related to, and most often in her own or someone else’s home. Moreover, rape conviction rates in the UK are at an historic low, and ONS figures show that 73% of UK domestic abuse victims in 2020/21 were female.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don’t have to be a statistician to recognise that the fact 98% of sexual violence is committed by male people doesn’t mean that 98% of male people commit sexual violence. But if we insist that violence against women is just the sum of horrible but isolated things done to some unlucky female people by a minority of damaged male people, we can’t begin to understand the bigger question of why this violence is so overwhelmingly gendered. Gender, after all, is understood by radical-minded feminists as the means by which patriarchal societies enforce the oppression of female people – by designating women a subordinate class, and using gendered norms to maintain male hegemony.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Male violence, then, commonly functions to enforce gender conformity, ie the subordination of women and the entrenchment of masculine entitlement. Aggression against gay and transgender people, for example, is commonly rooted in the perceived threat of non-conformity. Misogyny itself is deeply entwined with a thwarted sense of male entitlement – many terrorist attackers have a history as domestic abusers, and mass shootings and incel atrocities have often started with the killing of female relatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seen as a weapon of patriarchy, it’s clear that systemic violence against women is not limited to physical abuse, rape and murder. Violence and oppression against female people are also meted out in more insidious ways that are no less effective at keeping women as a sex class disempowered and therefore subordinated. Sometimes the silencing and banishment of women is very literal, if brutal – forced veiling, guardianship and disenfranchisement, for example. But oppression also works through cultural and social mechanisms – two thirds of the world’s illiterate population is female&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, and this is linked to the prevalence of child marriage of girls. This isn’t limited to the developing world – five US states have no minimum age for marriage, with a parental or judicial waiver, and marriage to an underage girl is a defence against statutory rape in most US states. &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Bodily exploitation through prostitution or surrogacy might not be done at knifepoint, but its framing as a commercial transaction makes explicit the status of female bodies as a patriarchal resource.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A woman doesn’t have to be personally attacked or exploited to be a victim of patriarchal violence – throughout history, female people as a class have suffered from the stranglehold of gender norms, which deem brains, spirit and self-determination to be incompatible with being a woman. Some women may have famously slipped the net though a male pseudonym, an amanuensis or even a full male identity, if they could convince enough people to go along with it. But for most women, this wasn’t an option – and yet the gendered expectations placed on female people by patriarchy can be intolerable. When they are, women’s and girls’ distress has been weaponised against them – women have been institutionalised for hysteria, given lobotomies and drugged up on tranquilisers when they have failed to comply with gendered subordination. Girls’ higher rates of dysmorphia, self-harm and eating disorders point to the struggles of growing up in a patriarchal society where a female body can feel like a prison – who wouldn’t want to escape?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So to eliminate violence against women, it isn’t enough to find and stop the minority of individual men who beat, rape and kill. Violence against women describes the systematic oppression and subordination of female people as a class, though its presentation takes many forms. By recognising this, we are better able to challenge it by changing the shape of our societies, rather than tackling one bad man at a time, and wondering why this keeps happening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/posts/2023-11-25-ending-violence-against-women/&quot;&gt;See here&lt;/a&gt; for our other posts for IDEVAW 2023.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover photo&lt;/strong&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/unwomen/51737051738&quot;&gt;UN Women&lt;/a&gt; on Flickr (&lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.0/&quot;&gt;licence&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.unwomen.org/en/what-we-do/ending-violence-against-women/unite/16-days-of-activism&quot;&gt;UN Women: 16 days of activism&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;femicidecensus.org&quot;&gt;femicidecensus.org&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://uis.unesco.org/sites/default/files/documents/fs32-adult-and-youth-literacy-2015-en_0.pdf&quot;&gt;UNESCO: Adult and Youth Literacy Factsheet 2015&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.unchainedatlast.org/united-states-child-marriage-problem-study-findings-april-2021/&quot;&gt;unchainedatlast.org&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>UNSEEN</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="violence against women and girls" />
      
        <category term="sex discrimination" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">November 25 is the UN’s International Day for the Elimination of Violence Against Women (IDEVAW).Between then and International Human Rights Day on 10 December, the UN is calling for 16 days of activism 1 to raise awareness and seek solutions to this oldest and most pervasive of problems. UN Women: 16 days of activism &amp;#8617;</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Ending violence against women and girls</title>
      <link href="/posts/2023-11-25-ending-violence-against-women/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ending violence against women and girls" />
      <published>2023-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/ending-violence-against-women</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2023-11-25-ending-violence-against-women/">&lt;p&gt;For this year’s &lt;em&gt;International Day for the Elimination of Violence against Women&lt;/em&gt; SEEN is publishing articles today and over the next few days by four of our general members (outside our network leadership team), three of whom must remain anonymous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trigger warning:&lt;/strong&gt; As these blogs are to mark the IDEVAW, they necessarily refer to violence against women including domestic abuse, rape and femicide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;1--16-days-of-activism&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/posts/2023-11-25-idevaw-16-days-of-activism/&quot;&gt;#1  &lt;em&gt;“16 days of activism”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our first post sets out some of the very sobering facts around this &lt;em&gt;“oldest and most pervasive of problems”&lt;/em&gt;, and delves into its societal context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;2--the-judicial-system-is-trying--is-it-succeeding&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/posts/2023-11-26-idevaw-is-the-judicial-system-succeeding/&quot;&gt;#2  &lt;em&gt;“The judicial system is trying – is it succeeding?”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Benjamyn Damazer in Department for Business &amp;amp; Trade reflects on the shifts he has witnessed in his long experience as a magistrate and special constable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;3--a-personal-account&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/posts/2023-11-27-idevaw-a-personal-account/&quot;&gt;#3  &lt;em&gt;“A personal account”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A SEEN member shares the powerful and moving story of her experience survivng an abusive relationship, and its ongoing impact on her life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;4-language-matters&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/posts/2023-11-28-idevaw-language-matters/&quot;&gt;#4 &lt;em&gt;“Language matters”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final post examines the recent trend towards censoring sex-based language - in particular &lt;em&gt;‘woman’&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;‘women’&lt;/em&gt; - and how this hinders efforts to end violence against women and girls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover photo&lt;/strong&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/unwomen/51737051738&quot;&gt;UN Women&lt;/a&gt; on Flickr (&lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.0/&quot;&gt;licence&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>SEEN Network</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="violence against women and girls" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">For this year’s International Day for the Elimination of Violence against Women SEEN is publishing articles today and over the next few days by four of our general members (outside our network leadership team), three of whom must remain anonymous.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Zero tolerance for Female Genital Mutilation</title>
      <link href="/posts/2023-02-06-zero-tolerance-for-fgm/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Zero tolerance for Female Genital Mutilation" />
      <published>2023-02-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-02-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/zero-tolerance-for-fgm</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2023-02-06-zero-tolerance-for-fgm/">&lt;p&gt;6th February is the UN’s International Day of Zero Tolerance for Female Genital Mutilation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Female genital mutilation (FGM) refers to all procedures involving cutting a girl or woman’s genitals to mark or remove some or all her external genitalia, including her clitoris, or to stitch her vaginal opening together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite being internationally recognized as an extreme human rights violation against women and girls, it is estimated that at least 200 million girls and women worldwide have suffered FGM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FGM is one of many harmful practices against girls and women which are rooted in deep inequality between the sexes and discrimination against females because of their bodies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FGM is not supported by any religious doctrine, but evolved as a social convention amongst some cultures as a direct way to control girls’ and women’s sexuality. FGM is also likely to destroy a woman’s capacity for sexual pleasure, which is also the intention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FGM has reduced but still persists across the world, particularly but not only in Africa, Asia and the Middle East. Many diaspora communities have continued to practice FGM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FGM can cause severe bleeding and death. If the girl survives, she is likely to suffer physical and mental trauma for her lifetime, including difficulty and pain in urinating and menstruating and in having sex. A girl or woman who has undergone FGM has a much increased risk of being seriously injured or dying during childbirth, and of her baby dying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A minority of FGM is now done under medical supervision, which some people believe to be safer and more acceptable. However, the World Health Organization strongly urges healthcare providers not to perform FGM in any circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FGM has been illegal across the whole UK since 1985 and it’s also now illegal for a girl to be taken outside of the UK to be subjected to FGM. However, some UK girls are still at risk from FGM. Government agencies, schools and charities across the UK work to identify and safeguard girls who may be at risk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Girls and women who have undergone FGM are often in pain  and ashamed and need support to seek help. &lt;strong&gt;Remember that you are not alone.&lt;/strong&gt; There are women doctors and nurses across the UK who will give you expert care for your medical and psychological health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are links to the sources for the information above. You can also use these sources to learn more and get support for yourself or a girl or woman you know who may be at risk of FGM or who has suffered from FGM:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.unicef.org/protection/female-genital-mutilation&quot;&gt;https://www.unicef.org/protection/female-genital-mutilation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/female-genital-mutilation-resource-pack/female-genital-mutilation-resource-pack&quot;&gt;https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/female-genital-mutilation-resource-pack/female-genital-mutilation-resource-pack&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.saverauk.co.uk/information-support/about-savera-uk/&quot;&gt;https://www.saverauk.co.uk/information-support/about-savera-uk/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.filia.org.uk/latest-news/2020/11/27/hibo-wardere-one-womans-fight-against-fgm&quot;&gt;https://www.filia.org.uk/latest-news/2020/11/27/hibo-wardere-one-womans-fight-against-fgm&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/female-genital-mutilation&quot;&gt;https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/female-genital-mutilation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover image:&lt;/strong&gt;  “International Day for zero tolerance against Female Genital Mutilation” by ALDE Group is licensed under CC BY-ND 2.0. To view a copy of this license, visit https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.0/?ref=openverse.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>SEEN Network</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="violence against women and girls" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">6th February is the UN’s International Day of Zero Tolerance for Female Genital Mutilation.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Ending violence against women</title>
      <link href="/posts/2022-11-25-ending-violence-against-women/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ending violence against women" />
      <published>2022-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2022-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/ending-violence-against-women</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2022-11-25-ending-violence-against-women/">&lt;p&gt;We like to think that in the UK we have equality between the sexes now. On the statute book, we mostly do. But can we ever be equal while women and girls live our lives in fear of violence from men? Do we even think about this? Or have we just accepted that male violence against women and girls has always been normal and always will be? Women and girls plan our daily lives in anticipation of sexual assault, rape and beating. Is it an instinct we are born with, because of our female sex, that comes with our female reproductive system? Or does it begin that day our mother first tells us to watch out for strange men (what does she mean?), or the day we watch the 5 o’clock news after cartoon-time and see the photo of a woman murdered by her husband?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Outside home, we’re busy making mental calculations and risk assessments. We scan the landscape more expertly than any sat-nav. Should I cycle the scenic route to work by the canal, or take my chances on the main road with the traffic and pollution? Should I stay at the office drinks when my female colleagues have left already? Should I risk the night bus or get a taxi home, when I can’t really spare the money? Should I take that beautiful forest hike alone, or stick to the busy park where I can see other women?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s not pretend: we are always thinking, does the man who followed me off the bus intend to rape me? Do men know how much we watch them and think about them?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We yearn for freedom and adventure, but often women and girls feel safer at home. Except when we don’t feel safer at home. Because we know, for all our fear when we’re out and about, that most violence against us comes from men we know and even love.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re not quoting any statistics in this piece, because we know that women and girls massively under-report violence, especially rape and other sexual assault. We keep our reports for late-night confidences to a female friend, when keeping our secrets becomes too intolerable a burden to carry alone. Was it my fault, we ask her? I chose the forest hike. I chose to go back to his place after dinner. I chose to marry him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re called over-cautious, paranoid, irrational, man-hating, hysterical. We seek out the safe spaces where only women and girls gather, because we know we can feel free there. We accompany our children to public toilets, even as they protest they’re too old, because we know what can happen. We sit up late on Saturday night to drive to collect our adult daughters from a party, because we know what can happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know it probably won’t happen today and we worry we’re being over-protective. But we also know if it’s not our child today, it will be another woman’s child. Why take the risk when we will try whatever we can to protect our children and every child?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;there-can-be-no-equality-between-the-sexes-until-women-and-girls-can-live-without-fear-of-male-violence&quot;&gt;There can be no equality between the sexes until women and girls can live without fear of male violence.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What can we do? We can start by never calling a woman or girl hysterical because of her rational fear of male violence. Instead, let’s think about why she is afraid and what part we all play in making our culture dangerous for women and girls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is written for the annual International Day for the Elimination of Violence against Women and Girls, 25 November.  To mark the day, here are some practical suggestions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Donate to women’s refuges and other charities which support women and children escaping violence.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Learn how to intervene when you witness violence - &lt;a href=&quot;https://rapecrisis.org.uk/get-informed/what-to-do-if-you-see-sexual-violence/&quot;&gt;https://rapecrisis.org.uk/get-informed/what-to-do-if-you-see-sexual-violence/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Join men against male violence with White Ribbon UK - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.whiteribbon.org.uk/&quot;&gt;https://www.whiteribbon.org.uk/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover image:&lt;/strong&gt; “GA72 - EU and UN launch Spotlight Initiative to eliminate violence against women and girls” by UN Women Gallery is licensed under CC BY-NC-ND 2.0. To view a copy of this license, visit https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd-nc/2.0/jp/?ref=openverse.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>UNSEEN</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="personal experience" />
      
        <category term="violence against women and girls" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">We like to think that in the UK we have equality between the sexes now. On the statute book, we mostly do. But can we ever be equal while women and girls live our lives in fear of violence from men? Do we even think about this? Or have we just accepted that male violence against women and girls has always been normal and always will be? Women and girls plan our daily lives in anticipation of sexual assault, rape and beating. Is it an instinct we are born with, because of our female sex, that comes with our female reproductive system? Or does it begin that day our mother first tells us to watch out for strange men (what does she mean?), or the day we watch the 5 o’clock news after cartoon-time and see the photo of a woman murdered by her husband?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
