<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/unseen/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2025-08-26T22:05:27+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/unseen/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">SEEN | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Sex Equality and Equity Network</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Elimination of violence against women and girls</title>
      <link href="/posts/2024-11-27-idevaw-2024/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Elimination of violence against women and girls" />
      <published>2024-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2024-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/idevaw-2024</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2024-11-27-idevaw-2024/">&lt;p&gt;Our duty and our honour: what can we as public servants do to stop violence against women and girls?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Entrenched patriarchy at almost every level of society, combined with a rise in misogyny that permeates the physical and online world, is denying thousands of women and girls across the UK the right to live in safety, free from fear and violence.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;  &lt;em&gt;- Reem Alsalem, the UN Special Rapporteur on violence against women and girls, London, 21 February 2024&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;November is a solemn month. Darkness, cold, heaviness, fatigue. We trudge through dead leaves and deadlines. On the 11th November, the knell of Remembrance Day forces us to visualise the horror of violence and the long reach of grief. Slog through two more weeks and we reach the 25th November, the International Day for the Elimination of Violence Against Women and Girls. Whether it’s the split second of the bomb explosion or the slower stealth of the thousand acts of violence which can cripple women’s lives, we remember how fragile we humans are. And we try to puzzle out again that insane equation: the enormous effort and love we give to birth and raise every human compared to how easily a life can be destroyed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this time of remembering, colleagues and I have been reflecting also about why we became public servants. It comes down to this: we love life. In the dark of November, let’s remember the honour we have in being entrusted to take care of the people of the UK. And so, we look forward with hope to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.un.org/en/observances/ending-violence-against-women-day&quot;&gt;sixteen days of world action&lt;/a&gt; for women and girls that the 25th November begins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us use this opportunity to focus our minds on what I believe should be integral to our ethics as public servants: that we must consciously work for the rights, safety and dignity of women and girls. As Reem Alsalem set out so forensically in her recent UN report (link below), the UK has come far in establishing rights for women, at least on paper, and yet, in 2024, we can look around us any day and despair. We still live in a society where male violence against women and girls, in all its many forms, is widespread and often taken for granted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, we think first about the violence at home, which may come from our fathers, husbands or brothers, and we remember the violence from the stranger in the street. But our culture where violence against women and girls, usually from males, is tolerated, is also shaped by our state structures and our roles, as public servants, within those structures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We as public servants take thousands of policy and operational decisions every week which form what happens in our schools, our hospitals, our laws, our job centres, our immigration systems, our social security systems, our police, our prisons and probation services, our care homes, our housing estates, our family courts, our women’s refuges, our foreign aid. The decisions we make can deter or enable male violence. Our institutions and systems can be structures of care and safety, or they can condemn women and girls to more insecurity and fear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None of us looks lovingly at a new baby girl and imagines she will grow up to be the girl sexually assaulted by the boys in her class at school, the teenager forced into prostitution to pay her rent, the mother struggling to raise her children while sinking deeper into debt or having her children taken away because she can’t protect them from her violent boyfriend, the woman in prison with a drug addiction or suicidal in a mental hospital because she can’t cope with her traumatic memories. Or is she just that quiet little woman in the office whom you barely notice, who lives a small life scared by her own shadow, wondering when a man will rape her again?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We as public servants must insist on noticing that quiet little woman, and all the other women and girls who live and die under violence. We refuse to accept violence as normal. It is our duty and our honour as public servants, whether male or female, to see violence and to act on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let’s not just view equality for women and girls as another tick box on an equality impact assessment, that we go through the motions with ‘because of that PSED training’. There can never be equality for women and girls while we continue to build  misogyny and violence into our culture. Today and every day, let every one of us look at how we do our jobs and see what we can do better for women and girls and so make our society better for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We hope you will find some inspiration from the links below, including the good example of our colleagues at the Youth Justice Board. Over the next fortnight, on the SEEN website and ‘X’, we will highlight more of the positive work being done by our colleagues: please do contact us with links to examples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Links:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/government/news/white-ribbon-day-2024-a-call-to-action-for-men-and-boys&quot;&gt;https://www.gov.uk/government/news/white-ribbon-day-2024-a-call-to-action-for-men-and-boys&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ohchr.org/en/press-releases/2024/02/no-time-lose-uk-declares-violence-against-women-national-threat-un-expert&quot;&gt;https://www.ohchr.org/en/press-releases/2024/02/no-time-lose-uk-declares-violence-against-women-national-threat-un-expert&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.unwomen.org/en/what-we-do/ending-violence-against-women/unite&quot;&gt;https://www.unwomen.org/en/what-we-do/ending-violence-against-women/unite&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.endviolenceagainstwomen.org.uk/about/&quot;&gt;https://www.endviolenceagainstwomen.org.uk/about/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see here our articles for IDEVAWG from 2023 and 2022:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-11-25-ending-violence-against-women/&quot;&gt;https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-11-25-ending-violence-against-women/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://seen-network.uk/posts/2022-11-25-ending-violence-against-women/&quot;&gt;https://seen-network.uk/posts/2022-11-25-ending-violence-against-women/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover art&lt;/strong&gt; from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.un.org/en/observances/ending-violence-against-women-day/background&quot;&gt;United Nations&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>UNSEEN</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="violence against women and girls" />
      
        <category term="sex discrimination" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Our duty and our honour: what can we as public servants do to stop violence against women and girls?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">SEEN in Northern Ireland</title>
      <link href="/posts/2024-11-18-seen-in-northern-ireland/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="SEEN in Northern Ireland" />
      <published>2024-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2024-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/seen-in-northern-ireland</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2024-11-18-seen-in-northern-ireland/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A member of SEEN based in Northern Ireland provides some reflections on the setting up of a SEEN in Northern Ireland group, and meeting other members of SEEN based in Northern Ireland for the first time.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was towards the end of last year that I first learned about SEEN. And, as the kids say, I finally felt “seen”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with many civil servants, I was increasingly concerned about the promotion of policies based on the concept of gender identity, rather than the protected characteristic of sex, across staff networks. Not to mention the proliferation of practices in relation to identity politics, such as pronouns in email signatures, and the general sense that “diversity and inclusion” meant submission to a strict set of beliefs which I did not share. Bring my “whole self” to work? How could I do that when social media told the horrid tale of what happened to those who were vocal about their belief in the importance of basic biology? It seemed that, wherever you looked, people were bullied – and worse – for raising concerns about the impact of ideas based on gender identity on the sex-based rights of women, as well as on gay rights and the safeguarding of children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet at the time I felt that there was no choice but to suck it up - friends and family warned me against putting my head above the parapet for fear of repercussions, both social and professional. I had resigned myself to biting my tongue and tolerating the avalanche of material promoting ideas based on gender identity politics, until one night on X I saw a post about SEEN.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not an exaggeration to say that SEEN has been a revelation for me. The very fact of knowing that there were hundreds of colleagues out there who share my beliefs and concerns was comfort in itself. But when I dug into the articles on the SEEN website, and got a sense of how genuinely tolerant, civil and professional the network is, I knew I wanted to get involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The journey to establishing a SEEN NI Chapter has been a fulfilling one. I began by speaking with SEEN leaders in other departments, who put me in touch with other NI-based civil servants who had come across the network in a similar manner to me. I met with them one by one, formed connections, and we now have a thriving band of gender critical folk who keep each other sane via coffees and lively chats. What started as a tentative exercise - we joked about creeping around like members of the French resistance - has evolved into a forum in which we can share views, highlight successes, and encourage each other to stand up for what we believe in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without the support of the SEEN NI cohort, for example, I wouldn’t have had the courage to hold a meeting with HR and D&amp;amp;I seniors to raise concerns about our department’s adherence to the Civil Service Code in the context of Pride Month. Or to challenge the views of a stakeholder who was dismissive of gender critical beliefs. In the SEEN NI group, despite our different backgrounds, experiences and politics, we have each other’s backs when it comes to combating overreach and disinformation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there is no doubt that our voices are being heard. As other bloggers have noted, progress can be slow and frustrating at times, but SEEN has taught me what can be achieved when rational, reasonable and tolerant people get together. So I would encourage any civil servant in Northern Ireland who shares our beliefs to get in touch. You’ll have a warm welcome in SEEN NI - to adopt a term that has been weaponised elsewhere, it truly is a “safe space”!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you are a member of SEEN and interested in finding more about the SEEN in Northern Ireland group, or if you would like to find out more about Chapters of SEEN in general, keep an eye out for email correspondence via the SEEN mailing list for contact details.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you are a civil servant and would like to join SEEN please submit your membership request via &lt;a href=&quot;https://seen-network.uk/join/&quot;&gt;our ‘join us’ page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover photo&lt;/strong&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@wwarby?utm_content=creditCopyText&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_source=unsplash&quot;&gt;William Warby&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/photos/a-black-and-white-photo-of-a-rocky-beach-_K1qXCM8yKg?utm_content=creditCopyText&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_source=unsplash&quot;&gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>UNSEEN</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="personal experience" />
      
        <category term="why seen" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">A member of SEEN based in Northern Ireland provides some reflections on the setting up of a SEEN in Northern Ireland group, and meeting other members of SEEN based in Northern Ireland for the first time.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">SEEN in Scotland</title>
      <link href="/posts/2024-11-07-seen-in-scotland/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="SEEN in Scotland" />
      <published>2024-11-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2024-11-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/seen-in-scotland</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2024-11-07-seen-in-scotland/">&lt;p&gt;A member of SEEN based in Scotland provides some reflections on the setting up of a SEEN in Scotland Group, and meeting other members of SEEN based in Scotland for the first time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chilling, silencing, fear and hurt were common themes at the first meeting to establish a Scotland Group of members of SEEN, along with frustration that such emotions are provoked for holding what are in reality widely held and evidence-based beliefs – that biological sex is real, immutable and in many cases important. The group was also surprisingly diverse, containing a mixture of ages, both sexes, and a wide range of perspectives and routes which had drawn them first to this issue and then to get involved in SEEN.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it was this backdrop which made the meeting a little odd – like a reluctantly clandestine and random group blind date. However, it is also what made the meeting feel so positive and productive. An active step to find a voice, connect with others, and make a difference.  Our discussions focussed on ways that the culture of “no debate” is impacting colleagues both in a personal sense and on the performance of the civil service as a whole. From a personal perspective it is clear that the “bring your whole self to work” ethos does not apply if that includes having concerns around the impact of implementing policies based on belief in the concept of gender identity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The group shared their experiences of feeling unable to talk about family issues at work or expressing honest concerns around mixed sex facilities which made them feel vulnerable. This was all compounded by a feeling that unions would not support them in upholding the lawful provision of single-sex facilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More widely, there was significant concern around the impact on quality of work and professional standards in the workplace, such as the ability to freely interrogate policy, taking a balanced approach to consultation on the collection and recording of data, and taking a truly evidence-based approach to decision making. While there are obvious examples of recent legislation in Scotland to which this applies, I was surprised to learn how far reaching the effect has been with implications for so many policy areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SEEN now has over 900 members across the UK and while our numbers remain small in Scotland they are growing. If you are a Scotland-based civil servant and you share these concerns I urge you to find your voice and get involved. By signing up you contribute anonymously through surveys and research. You can also choose to connect with others and get more involved in the Scotland Group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need a voice at the table and with more members our voice will be strengthened and our fear reduced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you are a member of SEEN and interested in finding more about the SEEN in Scotland Group, or if you would like to find out more about Chapters of SEEN in general, keep an eye out for email correspondence via the SEEN mailing list for contact details.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you are a civil servant and would like to join SEEN please submit your membership request via &lt;a href=&quot;https://seen-network.uk/join/&quot;&gt;our ‘join us’ page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover photo&lt;/strong&gt; with kind permission from a SEEN member. All rights reserved.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>UNSEEN</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="personal experience" />
      
        <category term="why seen" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">A member of SEEN based in Scotland provides some reflections on the setting up of a SEEN in Scotland Group, and meeting other members of SEEN based in Scotland for the first time.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Women in the Olympic Games: From Paris 1900 to Paris 2024</title>
      <link href="/posts/2024-07-26-olympics/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Women in the Olympic Games: From Paris 1900 to Paris 2024" />
      <published>2024-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2024-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/olympics</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2024-07-26-olympics/">&lt;p&gt;The Olympic Games have long been a symbol of human excellence, unity, and the relentless pursuit of athletic achievement. However, the journey to equality between men and women within this prestigious event has been a winding path, filled with significant milestones and pioneering figures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Women were excluded from the first modern Olympic Games in 1896 because its founder thought that their participation would be inappropriate. And in the Ancient Olympic Games, women were barred from competing and married women were barred altogether or thrown off a mountain as punishment for illegal attendance.Women in Ancient Greece started their own Olympics, called the Heraean Games, which honoured the Greek goddess Hera.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the first inclusion of female athletes in Paris 1900 to the equal numbers achieved in Paris 2024, the evolution of female participation in the Olympics is a testament to progress and perseverance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;paris-1900-a-historic-beginning&quot;&gt;Paris 1900: A Historic Beginning&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 1900 Paris Olympic Games marked a pivotal moment in the history of sports, as it was the first time women were allowed to compete. This inclusion was not a straightforward triumph but rather a nuanced and often overlooked part of the Games. Out of the 997 athletes who participated, only 22 were women, competing in just five sports: tennis, sailing, croquet, equestrianism, and golf.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most notable figures from these Games was Hélène de Pourtalès, a Swiss sailor. On 22nd of May 1900, de Pourtaès boarded the yacht Lerina as part of the Swiss crew that won the first of two 1-2 ton class regattas that would take place at the Paris 1900 Games. She then became the first ever woman to participate at the Olympics and the first woman to win a medal at the Olympics. Her crew returned in silver medal position the following day in the second 1-2 ton regatta, making her also the first female multiple medallist in history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-evolution-of-female-participation&quot;&gt;The Evolution of Female Participation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The years following 1900 saw a gradual but steady increase in female participation in the Olympic Games. Each successive Games witnessed more women competing in a broader range of sports. The introduction of women’s swimming events in Stockholm 1912 and then women’s athletics and gymnastics in Amsterdam 1928 were significant steps forwards. By the mid-20th Century, the momentum for equality between the sexes in the Olympics was undeniable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The late 20th and early 21st centuries saw the International Olympic Committee (IOC) making more concerted efforts to promote the inclusion of women. Initiatives were introduced to increase the number of sports and events available to female athletes. The 2012 London Olympics were particularly notable, as they were the first Games where women competed in all the sports on the Olympic program. Additionally, the number of female athletes reached 44% of the total participants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;paris-2024-a-milestone&quot;&gt;Paris 2024: A Milestone&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2024 Paris Olympic Games are set to be a historic event, as they will feature an equal number of male and female athletes for the first time in Olympic history. This milestone represents a culmination of over a century of efforts to achieve equality between women and men in sport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paris 2024 will see approximately 10,500 athletes, with an equal split between men and women. This achievement is not just a numerical triumph but a profound statement on the importance of equality and equity in sports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-road-ahead&quot;&gt;The Road Ahead&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While reaching equality in male and female athlete numbers is a significant achievement, the journey towards true equality in sports continues. Efforts must persist to ensure equal representation in coaching, leadership, and decision-making positions within the Olympics and the wider sporting communities. In particular, significant action is required to address the inequality in senior decision making positions in international sport organisations. For example, only 30% of the world’s largest sports federations were chaired by women in 2023. Addressing disparities in media coverage, sponsorship, and funding between male and female athletes remains a critical area for progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most pressing barriers for women in sport today is the persistent problem of sexual harassment and abuse, which not only undermines the dignity and safety of female athletes, but impedes their progress and participation. Creating a safe and respectful environment for all athletes is critical to achieve true equality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The journey is far from over, but with each step, we move closer to a future where every athlete, regardless of their sex, can pursue their Olympic dreams on equal terms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many thanks to the following articles which I used in the research for this piece:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;UNESCO Report&lt;/em&gt; | &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.unesco.org/en/articles/unesco-report-women-and-girls-access-sport-still-lagging-far-behind&quot;&gt;UNESCO Report: Women and girls access to sport still lagging far behind&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Atlas Obscura&lt;/em&gt; | &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.atlasobscura.com/articles/when-ancient-greece-barred-women-from-even-watching-the-games-they-started-their-own-olympics&quot;&gt;When Ancient Greece Banned Women From Olympics, They Started Their Own&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;UN Women&lt;/em&gt; | &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.unwomen.org/en/paris-2024-olympics-new-era-for-women-in-sport&quot;&gt;Paris 2024 Olympics: A new era for women in sport&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Olympics.com&lt;/em&gt; | &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://olympics.com/en/news/five-historic-firsts-for-female-olympians&quot;&gt;International Women’s Day: Five historic firsts for female Olympians&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover photo&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Prospero_Piatti_-_Giochi_Erei_(1901).jpg&quot;&gt;Wikipedia Public Domain&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>UNSEEN</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sport" />
      
        <category term="equality" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The Olympic Games have long been a symbol of human excellence, unity, and the relentless pursuit of athletic achievement. However, the journey to equality between men and women within this prestigious event has been a winding path, filled with significant milestones and pioneering figures.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">James Barry: female pioneer</title>
      <link href="/posts/2024-03-03-james-barry-female-pioneer/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="James Barry: female pioneer" />
      <published>2024-03-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2024-03-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/james-barry-female-pioneer</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2024-03-03-james-barry-female-pioneer/">&lt;p&gt;“So tell me”, my first history professor liked to start, after hearing my latest essay, “what have you left out, and how have you filled the gaps?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chose to study history at university because I loved stories. My mum would tell you I loved history from an early age, but I didn’t really, I just liked stories, and history happened to be chock full of tales: tall ones, fairy ones, and true ones alike. Undergraduate history, though, started out a little…dry. Term 1 was historiography, or “the writing of history”. How dull, I thought, how tedious. I’m here to dive into a world of stories, not to philosophise about how different types of historians tell them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was (obviously) completely wrong. My tutor expertly got us to unpick the exciting idea that in telling history, one makes choices. A list of facts is an encyclopaedia, but history weaves a picture and crucially should start a conversation: you look at the evidence, you infer, and you draw conclusions. And then you discuss, because there’s no ‘one way’, and certainly not a precisely objective way, of doing those things. The process can be unconscious – some bits of the past might particularly chime, or have meaning to you – or it can be highly political, wielding history as a weapon to shore up a particular vision of the present. How we see history reflects how we see the world, and also what we want to shape the world to be. So when we’re telling historical stories, what we leave in and out, and how we fill the inevitable gaps in evidence are choices, and not neutral ones. It is personal, and it is political. What kind of historian are you? What lens are you looking through towards the past? Or, if you prefer musicals to history, let Lin Miranda Manual be the tutor: who tells your story?&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where one starts and ends with the story of Dr James Barry is straightforward enough: a girl was born in the late 18th century, and dies in 1865. In between times, though, what do you include, and what do you leave out?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can start with the facts, so far as they are known. Margaret Bulkley was born in Cork, Ireland, around about 1790. Her mother, Mary Anne, took her to London around 1806. This was almost certainly to claim an inheritance from her brother, the artist James Barry, who had died without leaving a will. From here, Margaret disappears, but in 1809 Mary Anne travelled to Edinburgh with a previously unknown nephew, James Barry, who enrolled in Edinburgh University medical school. After graduation, Royal College of Surgeons exams, and some time in London hospitals, James was appointed as a surgeon in the British army in 1815. What followed was a glittering army medical career around different parts of the British Empire - including one of the few c-sections of the time that left both mother and baby alive, and culminating as the prestigious inspector general of hospitals for the army - a smattering of scandal, an infamous and hot-headed meeting with Florence Nightingale, and a reputation for a bad temper, a good heart, and a zealously reforming approach to public health. And then on death – despite leaving instructions to be buried without the traditional laying out and washing - a twist: the discovery that Dr James Barry had “a perfect female body”.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What are we to make of this story? An increasingly popular telling of it in recent years is that Dr James Barry was a transgender, non-binary, or queer pioneer. The Guardian, covering Historic England’s 2016 “Pride of Place” project to recognise LGBT+ history, hailed Barry as a “Secret Victorian Transgender Surgeon”.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Search for historical tours of Edinburgh, and a local tour company offers a blog to mark transgender day of visibility to “shine a light” on James, “a trans man who worked for the British army”.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; One biography of Barry argues that she may have had androgen insensitivity syndrome (a difference of sexual development, or DSD).&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The National Archives, in a resource for teachers to use as a lesson plan with children aged 11-16, rejects any debate, stating:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“He chose to exclusively live and identify as a man, having been assigned female at birth….. ‘Transgender’, meaning someone whose gender identity differs from the sex that they were assigned at birth, was not a term used in the 1800s. However, research has highlighted the significance of James Barry as a transgender man in the history of medicine as both a pioneer and reformer.” &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:6&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To take my tutor’s questions: what do these hot historical takes leave out, and how do they fill the gaps? We could start with the date. James was born around 80 years before the first women (the Edinburgh Seven) were admitted to a British medical school in 1869 (Elizabeth Garrett Anderson qualified in 1865 through private study: this route was then immediately closed to other women). Even after the Edinburgh Seven’s long fight for admission was won, the battles continued: their arrival prompted a notorious student riot, many professors refused to teach the seven women, and Edinburgh later decided the whole thing was a mistake and refused to award them the degrees they had earnt.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:7&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:7&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; No chance, then, for a girl like Margaret Bulkley to study medicine 80 years earlier in 1809 - other than by cutting off her long hair, shaving a few years off her cited age, and claiming to be male.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We could also look at her life. We could consider her prospects as a girl of limited means, in a struggling family, at a time when options for women were deeply constrained. We could look, perhaps, at the evidence and suggestion that she was raped when a young teenager, giving birth to a baby in secret who was then brought up as her sister: who experiencing that trauma might not want to identify out of womanhood into the relative safety of a man with status, doing things, going places? From what we can tell of her early life, Margaret appears to be a clever, confident girl, hemmed in by her sex and class - writing to her brother, “Were I not a girl, I would be a soldier!”.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:8&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:8&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; She left no account of herself that sets out her motivations: we can only infer from tiny slivers of evidence.. What do you make of her travelling with a trunk full of hidden women’s fashion plates from magazines? Or that the original plan might have been to study medicine in Edinburgh as a man for a few years, but then live and practise as a doctor in Venezuela, as a woman?&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:9&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:9&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frequently in the case of James Barry, the lens through which the story is currently told is firmly based in gender ideology. Even when tellings of her story try to tread a ‘neutral’ line, they end up tying themselves in knots: the University of Edinburgh’s historic alumni page posits the lengthy, fence sitting, “to give Barry the full respect they are due, and to refer to them by the correct gender, it would be useful to know if they considered themselves to be a man, or if they identified as a woman all along”.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:10&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:10&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Two of her biographers manage to state both that, “James Barry identified as a man and was indisputably transgender”, but also was “not a trans man in the full modern sense of that term”; and that Barry “enjoyed living as a man”, but “was never fully comfortable in his masculine identity”. At the end of this slightly mangled thought process, they conclude that, “had Margaret Bulkley been born in 1989…it’s likely she wouldn’t have transitioned but it’s possible that she would have lived as nonbinary”.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:11&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:11&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Right. There is no room, it seems, to examine her achievements just as one of those boring old binary women. Debate and discussion, based on evidence, is at the heart of history, but the National Archives constructs a ‘No Debate’ lesson plan, admonishing teachers and pupils that, “his biological sex became a matter of discussion…(after his death)…Such an intrusion into a person’s personal life is completely unacceptable today”.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:12&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:12&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I read different accounts of Barry’s life, it reminds me of the controversy in 2022 when the Globe theatre in London announced a production about Joan of Arc, “reimagining” her as non-binary. As Victoria Smith wrote in The Critic at the time,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“In this reading, Joan is no longer an exceptional woman; by being exceptional, she is no longer a woman at all.” &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:13&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:13&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To become a doctor more than half a century before women were formally admitted to medical schools, to have a successful career in the army 130 years before women were recognised as a permanent part of the British armed forces&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:14&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:14&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, and to carve out a life outside the confines of sexist gender roles at a point in history when women were fundamentally constrained by them, is an extraordinary achievement by any measure. The personal toll of it – not least in the difficulty in forming close relationships, but also in living the opposite of an ‘authentic life’ – must have been substantial: to maintain it undiscovered, until your death, would have required immense determination and courage. And so, naturally, it has to be taken away. Not an extraordinary woman at all, not someone proving what women were capable of in extremis: someone, instead, who opted out of womanhood altogether.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a political choice to claim James Barry as transgender or non-binary, and to use masculine or neutral pronouns for her. It is a censorious political choice to attempt to shut down historians proposing other interpretations, that focus on other motivations, or look at the context in which she forged a life for herself, over a possible interpretation of gender identity. That people so frequently do so (and present it as progress) makes me uncomfortable as a historian: as a woman and a feminist, it makes me angry. History is full of women pretending to be men, or aping male clothes and behaviour, both temporarily and permanently. They did it for reasons of safety, ambition, opportunity, money, necessity, and personal fulfilment. I don’t know whether any of them would recognise a modern concept of gender identity, and neither, of course, does any historian claiming them to be trans or non-binary. I don’t think it is, as the University of Edinburgh and the National Archives suggest, disrespectful to refer to James Barry as a woman: I think it’s far more disrespectful to co-opt her for a political movement that seeks to prioritise gender identity over sex, and erases as it does so both the achievements of women, and a long history of gender non-conformity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I said earlier that history was a conversation. My contribution to that conversation is this: we should say, loudly, and with admiration, that James Barry was a woman. We should tell our daughters: look, even in the most constrained of circumstances, look what women can do. Look what women can achieve. And how wonderful that you, 21st century girl, no longer need to opt out of womanhood to be any kind of pioneer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;•·················•·················•&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover photo&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Barry_(surgeon)#/media/File:James_Barry.jpg&quot;&gt;Wikipedia Public Domain&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ppXigfLHZog&amp;amp;t=198s&quot;&gt;“Who Lives, Who Dies, Who Tells Your Story” from HAMILTON (youtube.com)&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Dr James Barry: A Woman Ahead of Her Time, Dr Michael du Preez and Jeremy Dronfield &lt;a href=&quot;https://oneworld-publications.com/work/dr-james-barry/&quot;&gt;Dr James Barry - Oneworld (oneworld-publications.com)&lt;/a&gt;; The Secret Life of Dr James Barry, Rachel Holmes &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloomsbury.com/uk/secret-life-of-dr-james-barry-9781408891575/&quot;&gt;The Secret Life of Dr James Barry: Victorian England’s Most Eminent Surgeon: Rachel Holmes: Bloomsbury Publishing&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/society/2017/jul/25/secret-transgender-victorian-surgeon-feted-by-heritage-england&quot;&gt;Secret transgender Victorian surgeon feted by Historic England - Transgender - The Guardian&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mercattours.com/blog-post/lgbtq-history-james-barry&quot;&gt;LGBTQ+ History: The Story of James Barry (mercattours.com)&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloomsbury.com/uk/secret-life-of-dr-james-barry-9781408891575/&quot;&gt;The Secret Life of Dr James Barry: Victorian England’s Most Eminent Surgeon: Rachel Holmes: Bloomsbury Publishing&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/education/resources/dr-james-barry/&quot;&gt;Dr James Barry - The National Archives&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:6&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:7&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-scotland-edinburgh-east-fife-47814747&quot;&gt;Edinburgh seven doctors to graduate after 150 years - BBC News&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:7&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:8&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;du Preez and Dronfield, ibid &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:8&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:9&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;du Preez and Dronfield, ibid &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:9&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:10&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ed.ac.uk/medicine-vet-medicine/about/history/historic-alumni/james-barry&quot;&gt;James Barry - The University of Edinburgh&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:10&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:11&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kingshealthpartners.org/latest/3265-guest-article-dr-james-barry-and-the-united-hospitals-by-jeremy-dronfield&quot;&gt;The Bulkley-Barry-Cooper Professorship​ King’s Health Partners (kingshealthpartners.org)&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:11&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:12&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/education/resources/dr-james-barry/&quot;&gt;Dr James Barry - The National Archives&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:12&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:13&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://thecritic.co.uk/transing-joan/&quot;&gt;Transing Joan - Victoria Smith - The Critic Magazine&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:13&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:14&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nam.ac.uk/explore/timeline-women-army&quot;&gt;A timeline of women in the Army - National Army Museum (nam.ac.uk)&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:14&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>UNSEEN</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="appropriation of female achievement" />
      
        <category term="biography" />
      
        <category term="language" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“So tell me”, my first history professor liked to start, after hearing my latest essay, “what have you left out, and how have you filled the gaps?”</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Menopause: A radical perspective</title>
      <link href="/posts/2024-01-17-menopause-a-radical-perspective/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Menopause: A radical perspective" />
      <published>2024-01-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2024-01-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/menopause-a-radical-perspective</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2024-01-17-menopause-a-radical-perspective/">&lt;p&gt;As a 47-year-old woman, it’s not surprising that I’m heartened by the increasing visibility and normalisation of menopause – whether I like it or not, that train is pulling into the station some time soon. But the litany of common problems – the brain fog, the sleeplessness, the pains and sweats – that sounds like a bad cosmic joke, that each new chapter of female life must open with a new swathe of physical inconvenience. Is nature itself a misogynist? No wonder most world religions contend that women are being punished for some original sin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who would want to be a girl? No matter how much my mum insisted slightly desperately that ‘being a girl is just as good as being a boy,’ it just didn’t ring true. How can it be as good? I’m doomed to be weaker, and fatter! I could be attacked, or raped. I have to deal with periods, I could get pregnant. If I ever want a child I’ll &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; to get pregnant. Women get paid less, taken less seriously, expected to shave their legs and wear make-up to look ‘normal’. Name me just one thing that is better for girls! See!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a teenager I was grimly determined to compensate for my bad luck at the sex lottery, the cruel roulette that had put an X chromosome in the way of my human self-actualisation. On my grandparents’ farm I hefted haybales on my own, not one-between-two like mere aunties and mums. I wore trousers with my Venture Scouts uniform, and hauled a superabundance of sanitary products and painkillers on all-day hikes. At school I marched the other way whenever I saw creepy Mr Richards, who addressed all the girls while looking directly at their breasts. I tried, repeatedly, to explain to priapic teenage boys in pub car parks that I thought we were friends. At university I wore a bristling leather jacket and made it clear I could walk home on my own, thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was studying political philosophy, especially the development of post-Enlightenment concepts of the ‘political individual’, who could consent to mutual obligations rather than owing duty to a lord. Foundational thinkers such as Locke and Rousseau had banished women as a sex to the ‘private sphere’, on the basis that they were by nature too emotional, too unruly, to partake in public life (and, presumably, because otherwise there would be no-one to clean the houses and raise the children of the Great Men).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While writing my dissertation, I came across feminist political theorist Carole Pateman. Pateman’s thesis was that the Great Men didn’t &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; exclude women from political personhood out of prejudice and expediency. Rather, the individual they defined had specifically male characteristics which women could not share. Pateman wrote that “the body of the ‘individual’ is very different from women’s bodies. His body is tightly enclosed within boundaries, but women’s bodies are permeable, their contours change shape and they are subject to cyclical processes. All these differences are summed up in the natural bodily process of birth.” I thought this was reductive nonsense. What if women don’t &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; shifting contours and cyclical processes? What if they would like to reproduce (if at all) on an equal basis with men? It seemed a bit embarrassing that these middle-aged feminists were wanging on about some female birth-giving energy or whatever – wouldn’t it be better to stop framing all that icky, painful business as ‘female’, so that it didn’t hold individual women back from their potential? It seemed obvious to me that the solution was not, as Pateman recommended, to create two political actors, one of each sex, but to make sure the political individual was neutral, unsexed, to accommodate all shades of glorious human diversity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I moved through my 20s, though, my sex continued, stubbornly, to affect my life. I wasn’t doing feminine things – hell, I wasn’t even doing specifically female things like having periods or, god forbid, children. And yet I still had to think differently, act differently to men, to navigate my reality – the man who flashed at me as I walked home from the Tube station, or the one who found it funny to follow me along the dark road, didn’t seem to know or care what I felt about my boundaries, permeable or otherwise. I started to become less resentful of my own bad luck to be female, and more angry at how a supposedly liberal society treated female people in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ‘ladette’ feminism of the 90s emphasised personal freedom and equity – individual women having the same choices and opportunities as men, without being judged to a different standard. But that liberal feminism didn’t explain to me the root cause of women’s mistreatment – even in Cool Britannia, there didn’t seem to be a choice I could make that would give me men’s freedoms, so how could more ‘choices’ help the women of Afghanistan, Somalia or Nepal?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was radical (‘of the root’) feminist analysis that finally, to me, made sense of the global systematic oppression of female people. Drawing on Marxist thinking, radical feminism uses class analysis, where a class is a set of people (or things) that meet specific criteria. Importantly, something that is true of the class doesn’t need to be true of all the individual members of that class. For example, the class ‘homo sapiens’, defined as all living humans, has two eyes – it doesn’t tend to have two eyes, or generally have two eyes; it has two eyes. That doesn’t mean that all humans have two eyes, or that anyone with just one eye is not human, or that the purpose or destiny of humans is to have eyes. In all sexually dimorphic species, the female is defined as the kind of organism that produces large gametes (e.g. eggs). So it’s the class of female humans which gestates young and gives birth – that doesn’t mean all female humans give birth, or that anyone who doesn’t give birth isn’t female, or that giving birth is the purpose or destiny of female humans. But it does mean female humans as a class can be, and are, exploited and subordinated in patriarchal systems – regardless of any individual woman’s real or perceived personal characteristics or reproductive status. That’s precisely why there isn’t an opt-out, no matter how much I might have wanted one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Class analysis allows you to see the wood for the trees and examine powerful structures in society without getting distracted by individual variations. It loses some value when the class is porous or can’t be clearly defined – that’s one of the reasons why I’m not a political Marxist or even a socialist (which I’m sure would disappoint my Great Uncle ‘Red’ Eddie, firebrand of the General Strike). My lefty interventionist liberalism reflects my optimism that no-one is fixed forever into a particular socio-economic category. We won’t need to liberate the labouring class if we can effectively abolish it – or at the very least provide means of escape. The same isn’t true of sex class – regardless of our identity, personality or social presentation, it’s not possible in humans to change the material condition of our sex. Glorious human diversity takes place within and across sex classes, and there is powerful intersectionality with other characteristics. But Pateman was right*, in that there’s no point unsexing the political individual when we can’t unsex ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since there can be no escape from our sex, there has to be liberation &lt;em&gt;of&lt;/em&gt; our sex, so that its exploitation doesn’t limit our humanity – structural change to remedy the oppression of women as a sex class. This starts with Marie Shear’s definition of feminism – the radical notion that women are people. That as a sex, we are a whole class of human people in our own right, not a variant or a sub-category (non-men), not a state of mind, and not a shifting collection of whichever individuals happen at a given time to have certain working organs or be manifesting particular bodily functions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this is the context for my own perspective on how we need, collectively, to re-imagine menopause. Yes, of course more awareness of symptoms and greater support for colleagues is wonderful. But we need to take on the challenge of how menopause (among other things) represents the fusion of female biology and female exploitation. Periods, pregnancy and menopause are the foundations for the ancient folk archetypes of the maiden, the mother and the crone. The trivialisation of menopause is intertwined with the invisibility of older women, and the contempt in which they are held in society as a whole. We need to understand and manage menopause as an integral part of female experience, not as another ineffable ordeal that women must fight against and overcome in order to entertain the hopeful fiction that they, too, might be fully human.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*I still disagree with aspects of Pateman’s thesis, but for more nuanced reasons that I don’t have space for here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;•·················•·················•&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover photo with kind permission from the wonderful &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/jessdewahls/&quot;&gt;Jess De Wahls&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;style&gt;
.post-full-content {
    background: #ffffff00 !important;
}
&lt;/style&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>UNSEEN</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="diversity of belief" />
      
        <category term="language" />
      
        <category term="why seen" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">As a 47-year-old woman, it’s not surprising that I’m heartened by the increasing visibility and normalisation of menopause – whether I like it or not, that train is pulling into the station some time soon. But the litany of common problems – the brain fog, the sleeplessness, the pains and sweats – that sounds like a bad cosmic joke, that each new chapter of female life must open with a new swathe of physical inconvenience. Is nature itself a misogynist? No wonder most world religions contend that women are being punished for some original sin.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">What gender critical means to me</title>
      <link href="/posts/2023-12-18-what-gender-critical-means-to-me/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What gender critical means to me" />
      <published>2023-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/what-gender-critical-means-to-me</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2023-12-18-what-gender-critical-means-to-me/">&lt;p&gt;After another week of having to explain again to managers and HR staff what gender critical beliefs are and are not, I thought it would be helpful to put together this primer in case it is of use to others. The term ‘gender critical’ covers a range of views and I don’t speak for everyone, and nor am I a spokesperson for SEEN. But I think the views I explain here are fairly representative of those I have met in SEEN.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;1-sex-and-gendergender-identity-are-different-things&quot;&gt;1. Sex and gender/gender identity are different things&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stonewall define transgender as &lt;em&gt;“An umbrella term to describe people whose gender is not the same as, or does not sit comfortably with, the sex they were assigned at birth”&lt;/em&gt;, so they are not the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;2-everyone-has-a-biological-sex&quot;&gt;2. Everyone has a biological sex&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sex, whether you are male or female, is your biology and is observable and measurable. Everyone has a biological sex that is fixed from the point of conception and recorded at birth. A small proportion of people have one of the rare medical conditions known as Differences of Sexual Development (DSD), but people with DSD’s are still male or female.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone (whether or not they believe in the concept of &lt;em&gt;gender identity&lt;/em&gt;, and whatever their gender identity is, if they have one) can experience sexism, bullying and harassment or discrimination on the basis of their sex. This may be the sexism that a woman faces due to stereotypes about her sex, or the sexism a transwoman (someone registered male at birth who considers themselves to have a female gender identity) faces because they do not follow the sex-based stereotypes associated with their sex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sex is a protected characteristic. Sex is also the basis of the protected characteristics of sexual orientation (opposite-, same- or both-sex attracted) and maternity and pregnancy (which only applies to women).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is vital that we are able to talk about sex when relevant to our employment and that our employers provide us all with the sex-based protections in place in law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;3-some-people-believe-they-have-a-gender-identity&quot;&gt;3. Some people believe they have a gender identity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gender identity is defined by Stonewall as &lt;em&gt;“A person’s innate sense of their own gender, whether male, female or something else, which may or may not correspond to the sex assigned at birth.”&lt;/em&gt; Gender identity cannot be observed or measured.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some people believe in the concept of gender identity, and some people do not. Some people that do hold this belief, consider that their gender identity does not match their sex, and they may describe themselves as transgender or non-binary, cisgender, or something else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gender reassignment is a protected characteristic. Someone with the protected characteristic of gender reassignment may hold a Gender Recognition Certificate (GRC), or they may not. Either way, no one should face bullying, harassment or discrimination because their gender identity does not match their sex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Belief in the concept of gender identity may also be a protected belief under the Equality Act. No one should face bullying, harassment or discrimination due to their belief in the concept of gender identity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, a belief in gender identity should not be assumed or imposed on employees. The civil service has a duty to remain neutral both for its staff and for those we serve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;4-some-people-have-gender-critical-beliefs&quot;&gt;4. Some people have Gender Critical beliefs&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those with gender critical beliefs do not subscribe to the concept of gender identity. They think that gender identity must not be conflated with or used to replace sex in law, policy, guidance or elsewhere. If there is a need to segregate men and women for reasons of privacy, dignity, safety or safeguarding it is sex that should be used (and which is permitted under the Equality Act), not self-identified gender identity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gender critical beliefs are a protected belief under the Equality Act. Noone should face bullying, harassment or discrimination due to their lack of belief in the concept of gender identity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I do not hold a belief in gender identity, this does not mean I do not acknowledge the existence of transgender or non-binary people. My lack of Christian faith does not mean I deny the existence of Christians. Of course Christians exist, but their existence does not prove the existence of a Christian God. Equally, my lack of belief in innate gender identity does not mean I deny the existence of transgender or non-binary colleagues. Everyone should be treated with respect. But someone’s beliefs about their own gender identity do not override the protections written into law on the basis of sex, nor my (lack of) belief.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So to me, gender critical beliefs are simply about expecting my employer to apply the sex-based protections afforded to us all in law, and not imposing a belief system on me that I do not share.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;see also &lt;a href=&quot;/myths/#myth-6-intersex-people-are-proof-that-sex-is-not-binary&quot;&gt;SEEN’s position&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>UNSEEN</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="diversity of belief" />
      
        <category term="language" />
      
        <category term="why seen" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">After another week of having to explain again to managers and HR staff what gender critical beliefs are and are not, I thought it would be helpful to put together this primer in case it is of use to others. The term ‘gender critical’ covers a range of views and I don’t speak for everyone, and nor am I a spokesperson for SEEN. But I think the views I explain here are fairly representative of those I have met in SEEN.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Violence against women and girls - language matters</title>
      <link href="/posts/2023-11-28-idevaw-language-matters/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Violence against women and girls - language matters" />
      <published>2023-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/idevaw-language-matters</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2023-11-28-idevaw-language-matters/">&lt;p&gt;Language matters when we talk about violence against women and girls. In the last 15 years we have seen the word woman not being used, replaced with the word people or non-man, or replaced with dehumanising body-part terms such as cervix havers, chestfeeders, pregnant people or menstruators.  Attempting to eradicate biological sex by not naming women as women doesn’t make all the nasty, horrible things disappear and it does not give equality to women. The violence and rapes still happen it just means it is harder to measure something that is not defined. When it comes to violence against women and girls if we cannot name those who are being violated it makes it very difficult to defend them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A couple of years ago a local campaign near me decided to drop the word woman and use the higher level term ‘gender-based violence’ to highlight violence against women and girls. (Gender-based violence covers violence against males and females.) Fantastic branded signs adorned our bus stops and public buildings but no one knew what the campaign was about. It was a waste of resources and money. By taking out the word woman the campaign had forgotten who the victims were - women and why they were victims - because of their sex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prison statistics for England and Wales show that 99% of sexual offenders are male&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and we know that 88% of those offended against in such cases are female.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;  These figures are replicated around the world.  We cannot deny the biological difference here, men are the perpetrators, females are the victims. In the UK rape can only be committed by males.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; When a man rapes a woman he does so because of her biology not because of what she is referred to as. Women are oppressed and violated on the basis of their sex and to deny they have a sex by not using the word woman is gaslighting, which is another form of abuse. A male human is capable of killing a woman with his bare hands and we know that in the UK three women a week are murdered by a man.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pornography is having a massive impact on violence against women and girls. Over 88% of pornography scenes show sexual violence towards women.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Strangulation, beating and rape are the norm in pornography. One in three children have watched ‘hardcore’ pornography by the age of 12.  We are in an era where violence against women and girls is being normalised at an early age in the palm of our children’s hands. Boys are learning that girls can be objectified, humiliated, and attacked physically and sexually. Both boys and girls are learning that it is ‘normal’ for sex to hurt and that violence during sex is ‘normal’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we want to reduce violence against women and girls we have to use sex based language. To acknowledge biological sex matters and language matters helps us name the problem and find solutions. We have to be honest with our children about the harms of pornography and have conversations with them at a much younger age. We have to give them the language to reject the use of pornography so our boys can grow into adult men who can have a functioning sex life and our girls do not live in fear of their next sexual encounter. If women and girls are to achieve equality we have to significantly reduce violence against them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is one of a series of four blogs SEEN is publishing to mark the International Day for the Elimination of Violence against Women 2023. &lt;a href=&quot;/posts/2023-11-25-ending-violence-against-women/&quot;&gt;See here&lt;/a&gt; for the others.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover photo&lt;/strong&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/unwomen/51737051738&quot;&gt;UN Women&lt;/a&gt; on Flickr (&lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.0/&quot;&gt;licence&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/government/collections/offender-management-statistics-quarterly&quot;&gt;MOJ: Offender management statistics quarterly for October 2023&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ons.gov.uk/peoplepopulationandcommunity/crimeandjustice/articles/sexualoffencesinenglandandwales/yearendingmarch2017&quot;&gt;ONS: Sexual offences in England and Wales: year ending March 2017&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2003/42/part/1/crossheading/rape&quot;&gt;Sexual Offences Act 2003&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://culturereframed.org/the-crisis/&quot;&gt;culturereframed.org: The porn crisis&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>UNSEEN</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="violence against women and girls" />
      
        <category term="language" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Language matters when we talk about violence against women and girls. In the last 15 years we have seen the word woman not being used, replaced with the word people or non-man, or replaced with dehumanising body-part terms such as cervix havers, chestfeeders, pregnant people or menstruators. Attempting to eradicate biological sex by not naming women as women doesn’t make all the nasty, horrible things disappear and it does not give equality to women. The violence and rapes still happen it just means it is harder to measure something that is not defined. When it comes to violence against women and girls if we cannot name those who are being violated it makes it very difficult to defend them.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Violence against women - A personal account</title>
      <link href="/posts/2023-11-27-idevaw-a-personal-account/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Violence against women - A personal account" />
      <published>2023-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/idevaw-a-personal-account</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2023-11-27-idevaw-a-personal-account/">&lt;p&gt;I am not a victim, but I have been hurt by men. I won’t recount every time as the pain and fear crouches within me ready to pounce at any given opportunity. I am a woman who has served at the altar of men, perpetuating the entitlement that men can do as they please, whenever they please but no more, I am saying no.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I left my abuser; I did what everyone says a good mother should do or you are hurting your children, but the abuse never stops. Fear and intimidation permeate my everyday life, I live in a constant state of flight or fight. I was told my life would be better without him, I would be happy, and I guess I don’t have to put up with walking on eggshells every day as to whether he will explode like broken glass showering everyone and anything in the vicinity with sharp and dangerous shards. I don’t have to cover my children’s ears or usher them out of the room when he was screaming or throwing things. I don’t have him towering over me whilst I cower, but happiness I fear is something I will never know whilst he is still in my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I must share my children with my abuser, who is emboldened by the courts who claim that they believe you, but children need to see their fathers. Every time they are with my abuser I sink into a depression, a dark cloud shrouds everything I do, colours are less vivid, nothing is shiny, it is all dull and I feel a weight all over me, a black dog sits in wait for me snarling his ugly teeth as I anticipate a call where he has finally snapped and hurt or killed my children. I can’t breathe until they are finally at home in the safety of my embrace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t want to hear ‘not all men’ because so many men have enabled my abuser, and his continued abuse. I don’t want to continue to read the horrific statistics that another woman has been killed at the hands of a known male. I don’t want sexist tropes doled out at the pub under the guise of ‘banter’. I don’t want strangling normalised and seen as ‘rough sex’ and if you do not consent then you are ‘vanilla’ and boring. I do not want to hear that it’s not a gendered problem. This is an epidemic of violence against women. I am lucky, I had the financial resources to leave, many women do not, due to societal expectations that women are the primary carers for children and so give up their careers or go part time and then are stuck unable to leave their abusers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am scared every day; I am losing the battle but the resources I need I am fearful to use as these are now mixed sex. I am told that I must ignore my own instincts and violate my own boundaries to be kind but where is the kindness and empathy towards me and women like me? The courts don’t care, the police don’t care, and many agencies and charities set up to support women like me no longer care. So, I will bask in my fear and in the continued abuse because what else can I do? I am kind, I am kind to everyone around me, but no one cares about my problems because I have done what everyone says a good mother should do, I left my abuser. I am saying no to male entitlement, but I am screaming into the void.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://niaendingviolence.org.uk/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;nia&lt;/strong&gt; - niaendingviolence.org.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is one of a series of four blogs SEEN is publishing to mark the International Day for the Elimination of Violence against Women 2023. &lt;a href=&quot;/posts/2023-11-25-ending-violence-against-women/&quot;&gt;See here&lt;/a&gt; for the others.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover photo&lt;/strong&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/unwomen/51737051738&quot;&gt;UN Women&lt;/a&gt; on Flickr (&lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.0/&quot;&gt;licence&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>UNSEEN</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="violence against women and girls" />
      
        <category term="personal experience" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">I am not a victim, but I have been hurt by men. I won’t recount every time as the pain and fear crouches within me ready to pounce at any given opportunity. I am a woman who has served at the altar of men, perpetuating the entitlement that men can do as they please, whenever they please but no more, I am saying no.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Violence Against Women &amp;amp; Girls – 16 days of activism</title>
      <link href="/posts/2023-11-25-idevaw-16-days-of-activism/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Violence Against Women &amp; Girls – 16 days of activism" />
      <published>2023-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/idevaw-16-days-of-activism</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2023-11-25-idevaw-16-days-of-activism/">&lt;p&gt;November 25 is the UN’s &lt;em&gt;International Day for the Elimination of Violence Against Women&lt;/em&gt; (IDEVAW).Between then and &lt;em&gt;International Human Rights Day&lt;/em&gt; on 10 December, the UN is calling for &lt;em&gt;16 days of activism&lt;/em&gt; &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; to raise awareness and seek solutions to this oldest and most pervasive of problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Violence against women, by men, is endemic, both globally and very close to home (often literally). In 2020 in the UK, 110 women were killed by men &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; – a level of femicide that has remained consistent over time. In general, a woman is killed by a man in the UK every 3 days, every single year – most commonly a man she knows, or is related to, and most often in her own or someone else’s home. Moreover, rape conviction rates in the UK are at an historic low, and ONS figures show that 73% of UK domestic abuse victims in 2020/21 were female.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don’t have to be a statistician to recognise that the fact 98% of sexual violence is committed by male people doesn’t mean that 98% of male people commit sexual violence. But if we insist that violence against women is just the sum of horrible but isolated things done to some unlucky female people by a minority of damaged male people, we can’t begin to understand the bigger question of why this violence is so overwhelmingly gendered. Gender, after all, is understood by radical-minded feminists as the means by which patriarchal societies enforce the oppression of female people – by designating women a subordinate class, and using gendered norms to maintain male hegemony.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Male violence, then, commonly functions to enforce gender conformity, ie the subordination of women and the entrenchment of masculine entitlement. Aggression against gay and transgender people, for example, is commonly rooted in the perceived threat of non-conformity. Misogyny itself is deeply entwined with a thwarted sense of male entitlement – many terrorist attackers have a history as domestic abusers, and mass shootings and incel atrocities have often started with the killing of female relatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seen as a weapon of patriarchy, it’s clear that systemic violence against women is not limited to physical abuse, rape and murder. Violence and oppression against female people are also meted out in more insidious ways that are no less effective at keeping women as a sex class disempowered and therefore subordinated. Sometimes the silencing and banishment of women is very literal, if brutal – forced veiling, guardianship and disenfranchisement, for example. But oppression also works through cultural and social mechanisms – two thirds of the world’s illiterate population is female&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, and this is linked to the prevalence of child marriage of girls. This isn’t limited to the developing world – five US states have no minimum age for marriage, with a parental or judicial waiver, and marriage to an underage girl is a defence against statutory rape in most US states. &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Bodily exploitation through prostitution or surrogacy might not be done at knifepoint, but its framing as a commercial transaction makes explicit the status of female bodies as a patriarchal resource.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A woman doesn’t have to be personally attacked or exploited to be a victim of patriarchal violence – throughout history, female people as a class have suffered from the stranglehold of gender norms, which deem brains, spirit and self-determination to be incompatible with being a woman. Some women may have famously slipped the net though a male pseudonym, an amanuensis or even a full male identity, if they could convince enough people to go along with it. But for most women, this wasn’t an option – and yet the gendered expectations placed on female people by patriarchy can be intolerable. When they are, women’s and girls’ distress has been weaponised against them – women have been institutionalised for hysteria, given lobotomies and drugged up on tranquilisers when they have failed to comply with gendered subordination. Girls’ higher rates of dysmorphia, self-harm and eating disorders point to the struggles of growing up in a patriarchal society where a female body can feel like a prison – who wouldn’t want to escape?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So to eliminate violence against women, it isn’t enough to find and stop the minority of individual men who beat, rape and kill. Violence against women describes the systematic oppression and subordination of female people as a class, though its presentation takes many forms. By recognising this, we are better able to challenge it by changing the shape of our societies, rather than tackling one bad man at a time, and wondering why this keeps happening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/posts/2023-11-25-ending-violence-against-women/&quot;&gt;See here&lt;/a&gt; for our other posts for IDEVAW 2023.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover photo&lt;/strong&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/unwomen/51737051738&quot;&gt;UN Women&lt;/a&gt; on Flickr (&lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.0/&quot;&gt;licence&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.unwomen.org/en/what-we-do/ending-violence-against-women/unite/16-days-of-activism&quot;&gt;UN Women: 16 days of activism&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;femicidecensus.org&quot;&gt;femicidecensus.org&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://uis.unesco.org/sites/default/files/documents/fs32-adult-and-youth-literacy-2015-en_0.pdf&quot;&gt;UNESCO: Adult and Youth Literacy Factsheet 2015&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.unchainedatlast.org/united-states-child-marriage-problem-study-findings-april-2021/&quot;&gt;unchainedatlast.org&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>UNSEEN</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="violence against women and girls" />
      
        <category term="sex discrimination" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">November 25 is the UN’s International Day for the Elimination of Violence Against Women (IDEVAW).Between then and International Human Rights Day on 10 December, the UN is calling for 16 days of activism 1 to raise awareness and seek solutions to this oldest and most pervasive of problems. UN Women: 16 days of activism &amp;#8617;</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
