<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/bethany/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2025-08-26T22:05:27+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/bethany/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">SEEN | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Sex Equality and Equity Network</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Gluck</title>
      <link href="/posts/2023-02-26-gluck/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Gluck" />
      <published>2023-02-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-02-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/gluck</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2023-02-26-gluck/">&lt;p&gt;Another forgotten hero for LGBT history month, another lesser known artist from the 20th Century, this time a woman.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gluck&lt;/strong&gt; (born Hannah Gluckstein on 13 August 1895) was a British painter and lesbian who refused to conform to expectations: about her art, how she presented or who she loved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Hannah_Gluckstein_SAAM-1970.70_2.jpg&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; aria-label=&quot;this link opens in a new window&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/0/0b/Hannah_Gluckstein_SAAM-1970.70_2.jpg&quot; width=&quot;300&quot; alt=&quot;A portrait of Gluck by the artist Romaine Brooks&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;figcaption style=&quot;text-align: center; font-size:.8em;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A portrait of Gluck by the artist Romaine Brooks (1923-1924)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She was the daughter of Joseph Gluckstein (brother to the founders of J. Lyons and Co., the coffee house and catering empire) and had a privileged London upbringing, after which she attended St John’s Wood School of Art (1913-1916).  However, from here her life was to take anything but a conventional path.  Instead of settling into London society to marry and paint watercolours, she ran away with her fellow art student and lover, E M Craig (known by her surname, ‘Craig’).  Their destination was the Cornish artists community of Lamorna.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once there, Gluck was finally free to be herself.  She smoked a pipe and rejected the prefixes that would automatically identify a woman as married or single (Miss or Mrs).  In common with some of her lesbian friends, she sometimes used a male name (in her case the names Peter and Hig).  However, she always refused the label ‘Mr’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just like her life, no labels could contain Gluck’s art.  As &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/artanddesign/gallery/2017/feb/08/gluck-painter-fine-art-society&quot;&gt;The Guardian&lt;/a&gt; described: &lt;em&gt;“In keeping with her personality, however, she refused to identify with any particular school or painting movement”&lt;/em&gt;.  Despite this, Gluck’s first solo exhibition in 1924, sold all fifty seven paintings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gluck wore her hair short and dressed in tailored menswear, a style popular with lesbians at the time.  This was an era before women-only dating sites, magazines or bars and to be an open lesbian was a matter of social shame and exclusion, so lesbians in the 1920’s and 1930’s had to rely on such codes to identify one another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gluck was to go on to have a passionate romance with civil servant, food writer and florist &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Constance_Spry&quot;&gt;Constance Spry&lt;/a&gt;, who is likely to have been the inspiration for many of Gluck’s floral paintings in the 1930’s.  One particularly striking painting from 1936 depicts a plant known as &lt;em&gt;‘Lords and Ladies’&lt;/em&gt;.  This curious plant is in fact carnivorous.  Insects fall into the lily like tubes and drown and are dissolved in the pool of liquid in the base.  A fiercely unconventional choice of bouquet for a lady.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although Gluck successfully exhibited and sold her work throughout the 1920’s and 1930’s, it was her portrait known as &lt;em&gt;‘Medallion’&lt;/em&gt; (1937), perhaps her most famous, which was to cement her legacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/gandalfsgallery/51121322455&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; aria-label=&quot;this link opens in a new window&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51121322455_b332f19d77_w.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Medallion by Gluck&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;figcaption style=&quot;text-align: center; font-size:.8em;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A portrait of Gluck by the artist Romaine Brooks (1923-1924)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    &lt;figcaption style=&quot;text-align: center; font-size:.8em;&quot;&gt;Creative commons from gandalfsgallery on flickr.com (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/gandalfsgallery/51121322455&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; aria-label=&quot;this link opens in a new window&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/2.0/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; aria-label=&quot;this link opens in a new window&quot;&gt;licence&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This portrait emerged from Gluck’s relationship with Nesta Obermer, which began with a visit in May 1936 to Obermer’s family home in East Sussex.  Following this meeting Gluck concluded her relationship with Spry (and, in a very gentlemanly gesture, apparently burning Spry’s love letters on a bonfire shortly afterwards).  The relationship with Orbermer that followed was one of the most important of her life and the inspiration for &lt;em&gt;Medallion&lt;/em&gt;.  This dual portrait of Gluck and Obermer, was apparently inspired by a night out together attending Mozart’s Don Giovanni.  Described in &lt;a href=&quot;https://dianasouhami.com/book/gluck/&quot;&gt;Diana Souhami’s biography to Gluck&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;“They sat together in the third row and felt the intensity of the music fused them both into one person and matched their love.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Medallion&lt;/em&gt; has become an iconic statement of lesbian love and identity, such that it was chosen as the 1982 cover of Radclyffe Hall’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/129223.The_Well_of_Loneliness&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;‘The Well of Loneliness’&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gluck’s love affairs were multiple and passionate.  However like many famous historical lesbians (such as both Radclyffe Hall and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anne_Lister&quot;&gt;Anne Lister&lt;/a&gt;) those she loved were not always prepared to defy the conventions of their times.  Obermer never left her husband for her ‘wife’ Gluck.  That said, it’s probably fair to add that Gluck was not overly restrained by expectations of monogamy.  She also lived with another female lover during her relationship with Obermer.  This was the journalist Edith Shackleton Heald, who she met in 1943 and who was also lover to WB Yeats.  It was all very exciting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, after the success of Gluck’s early career, by the interwar period she was falling out of fashion.  After her relationship with Obermer ended, so too did Gluck’s art.  Although she continued her relationship with Shackleton Heald and the two moved to Sussex, she painted nothing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would be the 1960’s before Gluck’s inspiration returned, with new paintings and a well-received solo show.  Gluck’s last major work (completed 1973) was a painting of a fish head entitled &lt;em&gt;‘Rage, Rage against the Dying of the Light’&lt;/em&gt; (a possible reference to the Dylan Thomas poem &lt;a href=&quot;https://poets.org/poem/do-not-go-gentle-good-night&quot;&gt;‘Do Not Go Gentle into that good night’&lt;/a&gt;).  Until the end, a woman of unconventionality, fire and defiance.  Shacklton Heald died in 1976, followed two years later by Gluck in 1978, at the age of 82.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m grateful for the following articles, which I drew upon when researching Gluck, and which provide further insights into her life and images of her work:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Guardian&lt;/em&gt; 2021 article in collaboration with &lt;em&gt;Art UK&lt;/em&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/artanddesign/2021/feb/02/the-great-british-art-tour-national-portait-gallery-london-gluck&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Great British Art Tour: Gluck shapes herself with gender defiance&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;museumcrush.org&lt;/em&gt; | &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://museumcrush.org/the-enigma-of-gluck-discovering-the-artist-behind-the-lesbian-icon/&quot;&gt;The enigma of Gluck: Discovering the artist behind the lesbian icon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;See also &lt;em&gt;AfterEllen.com&lt;/em&gt; | &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://afterellen.com/gluck-the-lesbian-artist-who-rejected-gender-and-genre/&quot;&gt;Gluck: The Artist Who Rejected Gender and Genre&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Bethany</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="lesbian gay and bisexual" />
      
        <category term="sexual orientation" />
      
        <category term="biography" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Another forgotten hero for LGBT history month, another lesser known artist from the 20th Century, this time a woman.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Willem Arondeus</title>
      <link href="/posts/2023-02-21-willem-arondeus/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Willem Arondeus" />
      <published>2023-02-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-02-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/willem-arondeus</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2023-02-21-willem-arondeus/">&lt;p&gt;This LGBT History Month we would like to invite a celebration of some lesser known heroes who don’t always feature on the mainstream narrative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Willem Arondeus&lt;/strong&gt; (22 August 1894 – 1 July 1943) was a Dutch artist and author and hero of the Dutch anti-Nazi resistance movement during World War II.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/f/f3/Willem_Arondeus.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A portrait photograph of Willem Arondeus&quot; title=&quot;Willem Arondeus (1894-1943) Dutch writer, painter and partisan&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arondeus is worth celebrating as a talented artist and writer in his own right. However it is his incredible bravery which was to create his finest legacy. Not only was he openly gay at a time when homosexuality was stigmatised, but during the war he was active in the Dutch resistance, a decision that would ultimately lead to his murder by the Nazis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1942, Arondeus began an underground periodical called the &lt;em&gt;Brandarisbrief&lt;/em&gt; in which he called on artists to resist the occupying Nazi army. He later became more directly involved in the resistance, joining an underground organisation known as the ‘CKC’, creating forged documents along with a lesbian resistant Frieda Belinfante. This was important work, however the success of these forgeries was hampered by the Municipal Office for Population Registration, which checked documents and could expose their work as fakes. It was for this reason that Arondeus and others developed a daring plan to go one step further and destroy the whole Municipal office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this is what they did. On 27th March 1943, the building was blown up, destroying 800,000 identity cards (15% of the records), hindering Gestapo efforts to identify Dutch Jews and others wanted by the Nazis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, an unknown betrayer led the Gestapo to Arondeus, who was arrested five days later on 1st April. Brave, even under interrogation (and likely torture), Arondeus refused to betray the other resistance fighters involved. Sadly his notebook was found, and eventually the majority of the group were arrested.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nearly three months later, on 18 June 1943, Arondeus was tried and sentenced to death, along with 13 other men who participated in the attack. Almost all were executed on 1 July 1943, save for two young doctors who received prison sentences. One possible reason for this was because Arondeus took full responsibility for the attack. Frieda Belifante was the only other member of the resistance group to survive, which she did by disguising herself as a man and going undercover. (She eventually escaped to Switzerland and then emigrating to the United States, where she became a founding artistic director and conductor of the Orange County Philharmonic, a story itself worthy of a blog.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was, however, no escape for Arondeus. In a final act of defiance and bravery, before his execution, Arondeus made sure it was known that he and two of the other men in the group (Bakker and Brouwer) were gay. His last words before his execution were: &lt;em&gt;“Tell the people that homosexuals can be brave!”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1945, after the liberation of the Netherlands, Arondeus’s family was awarded a posthumous medal by the Dutch government in his honour. In 1984, he was awarded the Resistance Memorial Cross. Yad Vashem recognised Arondeus as Righteous Among the Nations on 19th June 1986.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He is certainly an inspirational hero who deserves to be better known for his bravery and also for his beautiful art.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/8/8b/Willem_Arondeus_-_Bloesems_belofte_wordt_nu_in_oogsten_vervuld%2C_september_-_Rijksmuseum_Amsterdam_-_RP-T-1930-87.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A 1930-31 calendar design for September, by Willem Arondeus&quot; title=&quot;Calendar design for September, drawing, 1930–31&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For anyone who is interested in amplifying his legacy, high quality images of his work can be downloaded for free from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rijksmuseum.nl/en/search?q=&amp;quot;Willem Arondéus&amp;quot;&quot;&gt;Rijksmuseum&lt;/a&gt;, Amsterdam and make beautiful prints.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m grateful to the contributors towards this Wikipedia article which I’ve drawn on in the above biography: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Willem_Arondeus&quot;&gt;Willem Arondeus - Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Bethany</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="lesbian gay and bisexual" />
      
        <category term="sexual orientation" />
      
        <category term="biography" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">This LGBT History Month we would like to invite a celebration of some lesser known heroes who don’t always feature on the mainstream narrative.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
