<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/sexual-orientation/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2025-08-26T22:05:27+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/sexual-orientation/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">SEEN | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Sex Equality and Equity Network</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Why SEEN is important to me (viii)</title>
      <link href="/posts/2023-09-17-why-is-seen-important-to-me-viii/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why SEEN is important to me (viii)" />
      <published>2023-09-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-09-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/why-is-seen-important-to-me-viii</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2023-09-17-why-is-seen-important-to-me-viii/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;To Celebrate Bisexuality Week, we wanted to share this post from a civil servant. This post shares an individual’s personal experience, which includes frank references to his negative experiences in another civil service network.  Many staff networks will have members and interests in common, but we also serve differing needs and as this post makes clear, these are sometimes incompatible.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;We hope that sharing these experiences will allow a better understanding of this, and this in turn will help act as a first step to allow us to work together to reach a place where all staff networks can complement and support one another.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Our network, as ever, welcomes collaborative dialogue between networks and across government departments.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;︵‿︵‿︵‿︵‿︵&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted to share some thoughts on why, as a bisexual man, SEEN is important to me, and why I haven’t found a home in the existing LGBT+ networks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The popular cliché is that a bisexual is some young, frivolous person with blue, green or purple hair and probably various facial and other piercings and a devil-may-care attitude to societal norms and who believes that gender is fluid.  But it also includes people like me, a 50 something ex-policeman, in the Civil Service, divorced with kids and who is attracted to both sexes: appreciating the masculinity in men and the femininity in women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Early on I accepted that my bisexuality was purely one manifestation of the continuum of human sexuality and I was relatively content in that knowledge. In spite of my own acceptance, I have always wanted to protect those around me from the knowledge or, where I had told them, at least the stigma of being the parent, sibling, wife, child or friend of someone who is bisexual. I believed this was the least I could do to show my gratitude and love.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In recent years, I had become very isolated and alone, in part because I had moved around quite a lot geographically, but also because I lacked contact with people with whom I could be myself, and who shared some of my life experiences. I knew intuitively that there were others in a similar predicament, but I didn’t know where I could find them. I had read that bisexuals are at risk of poor mental health and I did feel that I was suffering, so I looked first to the LGBT network for support, and in particular the Bi+ Inclusion Group. It wasn’t something that came easy to me and I was sceptical about whether I would fit in. However, I had hoped to find a friendly welcoming group where I could discuss my feelings and find other bisexual people with similar life experiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The people on the calls were friendly enough and we all conducted ourselves respectfully, but unfortunately it was apparent that the “+” was more important than the “bi” in the title of the group, even though often the “+” was omitted, as if it were a given that we all accept that there are many genders rather than two sexes. Stonewall came up in conversation once and I questioned why there seemed to be such an obsession with the view of one organisation, when there were other organisations such as the LGB Alliance with differing views. I was told that the LGB Alliance was a fascist and anti-trans organisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sadly, after several months of attending I was approached privately and it was made clear that having gender critical views was not welcome. It felt like the ultimate bi erasure as a bi man not being welcome in a Bi(+) group. However, looking back at my experience of the group I recognised that I had never found what I wanted there; a place to relax and speak openly. It seemed that rather than being allowed to speak about our own feelings and experiences, we were required to submit to a political ideology whether or not we agreed with it. There were also very few men who regularly dialled into the calls, so again it was difficult to find people with a similar life experience to my own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having gone back into my shell somewhat, it was a revelation to later happen across SEEN where different perspectives are tolerated, diverse voices welcome and same sex attraction is recognised as a unique category of experience.  I hope others will also find a welcome here too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover image&lt;/strong&gt;:  “Bisexuality symbol (bold, color)” by Kwamikagami is licensed under CC BY-SA 4.0. To view a copy of this license, visit https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/?ref=openverse.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>UNSEEN</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sexual orientation" />
      
        <category term="lesbian gay and bisexual" />
      
        <category term="why seen" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">To Celebrate Bisexuality Week, we wanted to share this post from a civil servant. This post shares an individual’s personal experience, which includes frank references to his negative experiences in another civil service network. Many staff networks will have members and interests in common, but we also serve differing needs and as this post makes clear, these are sometimes incompatible.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Rural lesbians and a safer world</title>
      <link href="/posts/2023-06-29-rural-lesbians-and-a-safer-world/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rural lesbians and a safer world" />
      <published>2023-06-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-06-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/rural-lesbians-and-a-safer-world</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2023-06-29-rural-lesbians-and-a-safer-world/">&lt;p&gt;I grew up in the rural idyll of Herefordshire &amp;amp; Worcestershire, having known most of my life that I was attracted to my own sex. There was little chance of my ever “coming out”, even though I went to an all-girls school, because at that time there was still huge stigma attached to being lesbian. It would have been social death at school, and I really didn’t want to cope with being ostracised while trying to complete my O-levels. The successful gaining of O-levels was directly linked to my gaining a motorbike and I wanted that nearly as much as I wanted a set of drums.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peer pressure and hormones encouraged me to have boyfriends and although I knew it wasn’t for me, I persevered in the hope Mr Right might rock up. He almost did, but when I met the woman of my dreams all that faded into dust. She was an old school friend who’d moved to the USA and done her coming out while playing in a rock band. I had all the savvy of vegetarianism and an interest in surviving the nuclear threat, so she was impossibly cool and desirable in comparison.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We went out to Birmingham, to find signs of life. It was an eye opener for me but ennui for her. After a brief but intense fling where I finally gained escape velocity from heterosexuality, she went back to America and I went off to the feminist peace protest at Greenham Common.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, I now needed a girlfriend to cement my fledgling lesbian status and fortunately one appeared. We had very similar backgrounds and interests, and we were both seeking our first female partner. I struggled to find my feet in this new world and my parents’ aspirations for me evaporated. After some tense battles - &lt;em&gt;“It’s like you’re going through puberty again!”&lt;/em&gt; - I was kicked out and this is how I ended up in a 25 year relationship complete with cats and eventually a civil partnership. With hindsight, I should have slowed down, but the miniscule size of my lesbian dating pool added pressure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If only there’d been somewhere to go for advice and support… At the time there was London Gay Switchboard, or Lesbian Line (one night a week). It was impossible to get through on either number. And what could they have advised me, anyway? Go to the big city like Jimmy Somerville? Move to Greenham and hope for the best?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the late 1980s, the HIV/AIDS crisis had arrived and was changing the complexion of gay life forever. Bizarrely, it was this situation that pushed many of us into action. With my gay male friends, we women had been talking about setting something up to help our community, and we decided we needed our own lifeline. Hereford &amp;amp; Worcester Lesbian &amp;amp; Gay Switchboard was born. As is often the case, we had more men than women in the group, but we did our best to train ourselves and learn to handle calls of all kinds and from either sex. I absolutely know what a vertical learning curve feels like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We set up a monthly fundraiser at a local nightclub, and swiftly gained support from the local sexual health team who were desperate to promote safer sex. This was the battleground era of Section 28 (a law which that prohibited the “promotion of homosexuality” by local authorities) and AIDS scaremongering, so looking back I realise quite how brave and determined we were. The head of the county education authority wanted our Switchboard’s service office closed down because we were in a building with many other charities and there were “vulnerable young people in wheelchairs”. The venom and gross prejudice was palpable but we held our ground and triumphed over adversity for over ten years. Our mission for the Switchboard was that we would not need to exist: we hoped the world would catch up and become a more welcoming place for us. When the calls slowed to a trickle, we knew things had changed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We organised the first gathering of UK lesbian and gay switchboards over a weekend in Worcester and even the mighty London Switchboard turned up! A mix of rural and urban organisations were represented. I delivered a presentation on sexual health and safer sex for lesbians, which at the time was either overlooked or subject to bad advice. For example, lesbians were told we didn’t need to take tests for cervical cancer. I made the plea for better understanding of lesbian health needs as well as those of our gay brothers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those years hold bittersweet memories of struggle, insight, joy, fellowship and loss. They helped form the person I am today and drive me to want that perspective in my working life. SEEN offers the chance for us to recreate the best of that shared history for lesbians and gay men in the civil service, and I look forward to welcoming colleagues as we grow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover image&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/photos/nAizdTpHUTM&quot;&gt;Peter Musk&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/license&quot;&gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Jan</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="lesbian gay and bisexual" />
      
        <category term="sexual orientation" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">I grew up in the rural idyll of Herefordshire &amp;amp; Worcestershire, having known most of my life that I was attracted to my own sex. There was little chance of my ever “coming out”, even though I went to an all-girls school, because at that time there was still huge stigma attached to being lesbian. It would have been social death at school, and I really didn’t want to cope with being ostracised while trying to complete my O-levels. The successful gaining of O-levels was directly linked to my gaining a motorbike and I wanted that nearly as much as I wanted a set of drums.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Celebrating Lesbian Visibility Day 2023</title>
      <link href="/posts/2023-04-26-lesbian-visibility-day/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Celebrating Lesbian Visibility Day 2023" />
      <published>2023-04-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-04-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/lesbian-visibility-day</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2023-04-26-lesbian-visibility-day/">&lt;p&gt;Lesbians in history have tended to be largely invisible (try naming five famous lesbians… or try naming five famous lesbians without mentioning Martina). Despite a heyday in the 1990s, we are once again disappearing - hence Lesbian Visibility Day.  Let’s prepare for our day of celebration and visibility by looking at a selection of historical highlights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lesbian mythology includes gems like this: Ministers bringing legislation outlawing homosexuality to Queen Victoria for royal assent were too nervous to explain the intent to include women. Some say Victoria was told, but reacted with such disbelief that ladies would behave that way, that only men were outlawed! So in recent history, lesbians remained legally undescribed. This was handy if you didn’t want to be imprisoned, but unhelpful in terms of being understood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patriarchy was largely unbothered by lesbianism, unless there was any threat to male superiority. But there were economic reasons why women struggled to live independently from men. Love whom you like, so long as you can afford it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Women living apart from men have always been treated with suspicion and had fewer life choices, for both economic and social reasons: wife, witch or nun, basically. Whether the concept of lesbianism as we know it today would have been understood prior to the 20th century is debatable, but it’s likely there have always been women desperate to avoid “traditional” gender roles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most famous lesbian, Sappho, lived on the Greek island of Lesbos around 630- 570 BC. This is how here we get the term “lesbian”. Sappho was a revered lyric poet, but most of her works are lost so we rely only on remaining fragments. Sappho was possibly the Melissa Etheridge of her day, writing songs that told of love between women - but like the C90 cassette compilation of my favourite songs, they are lost to us now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arabian writings about lesbianism from the medieval era include perhaps the first (written) lesbian love story, in a 10th century treatise called “The Encyclopaedia of Pleasure”. The Medieval Europeans were far more draconian in their views on homosexuality, with severe punishment (including torturous death) for men and banishment for women. By the time of the Spanish Inquisition, only the pure escaped punishment. Lesbians were therefore overly represented amongst witches and in female-only institutions like convents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later famous lesbians include the Ladies of Llangollen and Anne Lister. Thanks to her diaries and the recent successful TV drama, the legendary Anne Lister is well known for her love of the “fairer sex”, as well as the financial independence which enabled her to indulge it. She visited the Ladies in Llangollen, which begs the question of how they organised this in days of very slow media. I live in the super-speedy online world of the 21st century and it’s like herding cats getting a group of lesbians together in the same space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Salon culture of Paris and other European cities during the early 20th century was tailored to the rich, famous, or rising stars, but also provided previously unavailable social opportunities for lesbians. The Second World War provided untold chances for lesbians, as women worked beyond the home. Lesbian culture developed a strong underground vibe, hidden away from salacious eyes. Watch the film “The Killing of Sister George”, revealing the (literally underground) Gateways club in the 1960s. There were similar hideaways still available in 1980s Brighton!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Treatment for male homosexuality largely depended on class/ money, but there is little research or data regarding lesbians. Many lesbians ended up in mental hospitals, and some of them never left. Attempts to “cure” homosexuality are notoriously unsuccessful and mercifully some psychiatrists realised this. A lesbian treated by a female psychiatrist at the Tavistock clinic following a suicide attempt was told: “You must remember it is natural for you… People who are left-handed and who are forced to write with their right hand usually develop a stutter…and you are sexually left handed” (Sarah Carr &amp;amp; Helen Spandler, The Lancet April 2019).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The USA’s influential Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders listed homosexuality as a mental disorder from 1968 until 1973, when it became a “sexual orientation disturbance”. But homosexuality only left the publication in 1987 – two years after I “came out” as lesbian.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Lesbian” is falling out of fashion for some, in favour words like “queer” or “gay”, or sometimes replaced with the terms “bisexual” or “pansexual”. Theories for this suggest the word lesbian is considered to be old-fashioned or embarrassing.  However, many of us remain happy and proud to call ourselves lesbians, as it is a distinctive and defining word for us as female homosexuals, separate from men’s words. Interestingly, male homosexuals are far less likely to have their terminology and culture challenged!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know that women and girls throughout history (and still today in some parts of the world) have disguised themselves as males to get work, be educated, travel alone, escape marriage, or simply to try to keep safe from sexual attack. Some women will have done this to be free to have relationships with other women, but it’s hard to be sure because clear evidence like Anne Lister’s diaries is scarce. Women have always pursued close relationships with each other and lived together for many reasons, which won’t always have been romantic or sexual. Women’s solidarity and closeness is an historical constant, whether we are lesbian or not, and we should celebrate whatever form that takes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you do meet a lesbian in the wild today, rejoice, for we are in small numbers and often camouflaged, except that one day of the year when we celebrate…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover image:&lt;/strong&gt; Manuscripts and Archives Division, The New York Public Library. &lt;em&gt;Lavender Menace members hold signs reading “The women’s movement is a lesbian plot”&lt;/em&gt; The New York Public Library Digital Collections. 1970. https://digitalcollections.nypl.org/items/ac5276a0-9f43-0137-d597-233b6d9ef0dd&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Jan</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="lesbian gay and bisexual" />
      
        <category term="sexual orientation" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Lesbians in history have tended to be largely invisible (try naming five famous lesbians… or try naming five famous lesbians without mentioning Martina). Despite a heyday in the 1990s, we are once again disappearing - hence Lesbian Visibility Day. Let’s prepare for our day of celebration and visibility by looking at a selection of historical highlights.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Gluck</title>
      <link href="/posts/2023-02-26-gluck/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Gluck" />
      <published>2023-02-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-02-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/gluck</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2023-02-26-gluck/">&lt;p&gt;Another forgotten hero for LGBT history month, another lesser known artist from the 20th Century, this time a woman.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gluck&lt;/strong&gt; (born Hannah Gluckstein on 13 August 1895) was a British painter and lesbian who refused to conform to expectations: about her art, how she presented or who she loved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Hannah_Gluckstein_SAAM-1970.70_2.jpg&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; aria-label=&quot;this link opens in a new window&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/0/0b/Hannah_Gluckstein_SAAM-1970.70_2.jpg&quot; width=&quot;300&quot; alt=&quot;A portrait of Gluck by the artist Romaine Brooks&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;figcaption style=&quot;text-align: center; font-size:.8em;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A portrait of Gluck by the artist Romaine Brooks (1923-1924)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She was the daughter of Joseph Gluckstein (brother to the founders of J. Lyons and Co., the coffee house and catering empire) and had a privileged London upbringing, after which she attended St John’s Wood School of Art (1913-1916).  However, from here her life was to take anything but a conventional path.  Instead of settling into London society to marry and paint watercolours, she ran away with her fellow art student and lover, E M Craig (known by her surname, ‘Craig’).  Their destination was the Cornish artists community of Lamorna.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once there, Gluck was finally free to be herself.  She smoked a pipe and rejected the prefixes that would automatically identify a woman as married or single (Miss or Mrs).  In common with some of her lesbian friends, she sometimes used a male name (in her case the names Peter and Hig).  However, she always refused the label ‘Mr’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just like her life, no labels could contain Gluck’s art.  As &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/artanddesign/gallery/2017/feb/08/gluck-painter-fine-art-society&quot;&gt;The Guardian&lt;/a&gt; described: &lt;em&gt;“In keeping with her personality, however, she refused to identify with any particular school or painting movement”&lt;/em&gt;.  Despite this, Gluck’s first solo exhibition in 1924, sold all fifty seven paintings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gluck wore her hair short and dressed in tailored menswear, a style popular with lesbians at the time.  This was an era before women-only dating sites, magazines or bars and to be an open lesbian was a matter of social shame and exclusion, so lesbians in the 1920’s and 1930’s had to rely on such codes to identify one another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gluck was to go on to have a passionate romance with civil servant, food writer and florist &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Constance_Spry&quot;&gt;Constance Spry&lt;/a&gt;, who is likely to have been the inspiration for many of Gluck’s floral paintings in the 1930’s.  One particularly striking painting from 1936 depicts a plant known as &lt;em&gt;‘Lords and Ladies’&lt;/em&gt;.  This curious plant is in fact carnivorous.  Insects fall into the lily like tubes and drown and are dissolved in the pool of liquid in the base.  A fiercely unconventional choice of bouquet for a lady.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although Gluck successfully exhibited and sold her work throughout the 1920’s and 1930’s, it was her portrait known as &lt;em&gt;‘Medallion’&lt;/em&gt; (1937), perhaps her most famous, which was to cement her legacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/gandalfsgallery/51121322455&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; aria-label=&quot;this link opens in a new window&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51121322455_b332f19d77_w.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Medallion by Gluck&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;figcaption style=&quot;text-align: center; font-size:.8em;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A portrait of Gluck by the artist Romaine Brooks (1923-1924)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    &lt;figcaption style=&quot;text-align: center; font-size:.8em;&quot;&gt;Creative commons from gandalfsgallery on flickr.com (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/gandalfsgallery/51121322455&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; aria-label=&quot;this link opens in a new window&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/2.0/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; aria-label=&quot;this link opens in a new window&quot;&gt;licence&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This portrait emerged from Gluck’s relationship with Nesta Obermer, which began with a visit in May 1936 to Obermer’s family home in East Sussex.  Following this meeting Gluck concluded her relationship with Spry (and, in a very gentlemanly gesture, apparently burning Spry’s love letters on a bonfire shortly afterwards).  The relationship with Orbermer that followed was one of the most important of her life and the inspiration for &lt;em&gt;Medallion&lt;/em&gt;.  This dual portrait of Gluck and Obermer, was apparently inspired by a night out together attending Mozart’s Don Giovanni.  Described in &lt;a href=&quot;https://dianasouhami.com/book/gluck/&quot;&gt;Diana Souhami’s biography to Gluck&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;“They sat together in the third row and felt the intensity of the music fused them both into one person and matched their love.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Medallion&lt;/em&gt; has become an iconic statement of lesbian love and identity, such that it was chosen as the 1982 cover of Radclyffe Hall’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/129223.The_Well_of_Loneliness&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;‘The Well of Loneliness’&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gluck’s love affairs were multiple and passionate.  However like many famous historical lesbians (such as both Radclyffe Hall and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anne_Lister&quot;&gt;Anne Lister&lt;/a&gt;) those she loved were not always prepared to defy the conventions of their times.  Obermer never left her husband for her ‘wife’ Gluck.  That said, it’s probably fair to add that Gluck was not overly restrained by expectations of monogamy.  She also lived with another female lover during her relationship with Obermer.  This was the journalist Edith Shackleton Heald, who she met in 1943 and who was also lover to WB Yeats.  It was all very exciting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, after the success of Gluck’s early career, by the interwar period she was falling out of fashion.  After her relationship with Obermer ended, so too did Gluck’s art.  Although she continued her relationship with Shackleton Heald and the two moved to Sussex, she painted nothing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would be the 1960’s before Gluck’s inspiration returned, with new paintings and a well-received solo show.  Gluck’s last major work (completed 1973) was a painting of a fish head entitled &lt;em&gt;‘Rage, Rage against the Dying of the Light’&lt;/em&gt; (a possible reference to the Dylan Thomas poem &lt;a href=&quot;https://poets.org/poem/do-not-go-gentle-good-night&quot;&gt;‘Do Not Go Gentle into that good night’&lt;/a&gt;).  Until the end, a woman of unconventionality, fire and defiance.  Shacklton Heald died in 1976, followed two years later by Gluck in 1978, at the age of 82.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m grateful for the following articles, which I drew upon when researching Gluck, and which provide further insights into her life and images of her work:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Guardian&lt;/em&gt; 2021 article in collaboration with &lt;em&gt;Art UK&lt;/em&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/artanddesign/2021/feb/02/the-great-british-art-tour-national-portait-gallery-london-gluck&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Great British Art Tour: Gluck shapes herself with gender defiance&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;museumcrush.org&lt;/em&gt; | &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://museumcrush.org/the-enigma-of-gluck-discovering-the-artist-behind-the-lesbian-icon/&quot;&gt;The enigma of Gluck: Discovering the artist behind the lesbian icon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;See also &lt;em&gt;AfterEllen.com&lt;/em&gt; | &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://afterellen.com/gluck-the-lesbian-artist-who-rejected-gender-and-genre/&quot;&gt;Gluck: The Artist Who Rejected Gender and Genre&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Bethany</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="lesbian gay and bisexual" />
      
        <category term="sexual orientation" />
      
        <category term="biography" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Another forgotten hero for LGBT history month, another lesser known artist from the 20th Century, this time a woman.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Willem Arondeus</title>
      <link href="/posts/2023-02-21-willem-arondeus/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Willem Arondeus" />
      <published>2023-02-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-02-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/willem-arondeus</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2023-02-21-willem-arondeus/">&lt;p&gt;This LGBT History Month we would like to invite a celebration of some lesser known heroes who don’t always feature on the mainstream narrative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Willem Arondeus&lt;/strong&gt; (22 August 1894 – 1 July 1943) was a Dutch artist and author and hero of the Dutch anti-Nazi resistance movement during World War II.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/f/f3/Willem_Arondeus.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A portrait photograph of Willem Arondeus&quot; title=&quot;Willem Arondeus (1894-1943) Dutch writer, painter and partisan&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arondeus is worth celebrating as a talented artist and writer in his own right. However it is his incredible bravery which was to create his finest legacy. Not only was he openly gay at a time when homosexuality was stigmatised, but during the war he was active in the Dutch resistance, a decision that would ultimately lead to his murder by the Nazis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1942, Arondeus began an underground periodical called the &lt;em&gt;Brandarisbrief&lt;/em&gt; in which he called on artists to resist the occupying Nazi army. He later became more directly involved in the resistance, joining an underground organisation known as the ‘CKC’, creating forged documents along with a lesbian resistant Frieda Belinfante. This was important work, however the success of these forgeries was hampered by the Municipal Office for Population Registration, which checked documents and could expose their work as fakes. It was for this reason that Arondeus and others developed a daring plan to go one step further and destroy the whole Municipal office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this is what they did. On 27th March 1943, the building was blown up, destroying 800,000 identity cards (15% of the records), hindering Gestapo efforts to identify Dutch Jews and others wanted by the Nazis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, an unknown betrayer led the Gestapo to Arondeus, who was arrested five days later on 1st April. Brave, even under interrogation (and likely torture), Arondeus refused to betray the other resistance fighters involved. Sadly his notebook was found, and eventually the majority of the group were arrested.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nearly three months later, on 18 June 1943, Arondeus was tried and sentenced to death, along with 13 other men who participated in the attack. Almost all were executed on 1 July 1943, save for two young doctors who received prison sentences. One possible reason for this was because Arondeus took full responsibility for the attack. Frieda Belifante was the only other member of the resistance group to survive, which she did by disguising herself as a man and going undercover. (She eventually escaped to Switzerland and then emigrating to the United States, where she became a founding artistic director and conductor of the Orange County Philharmonic, a story itself worthy of a blog.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was, however, no escape for Arondeus. In a final act of defiance and bravery, before his execution, Arondeus made sure it was known that he and two of the other men in the group (Bakker and Brouwer) were gay. His last words before his execution were: &lt;em&gt;“Tell the people that homosexuals can be brave!”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1945, after the liberation of the Netherlands, Arondeus’s family was awarded a posthumous medal by the Dutch government in his honour. In 1984, he was awarded the Resistance Memorial Cross. Yad Vashem recognised Arondeus as Righteous Among the Nations on 19th June 1986.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He is certainly an inspirational hero who deserves to be better known for his bravery and also for his beautiful art.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/8/8b/Willem_Arondeus_-_Bloesems_belofte_wordt_nu_in_oogsten_vervuld%2C_september_-_Rijksmuseum_Amsterdam_-_RP-T-1930-87.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A 1930-31 calendar design for September, by Willem Arondeus&quot; title=&quot;Calendar design for September, drawing, 1930–31&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For anyone who is interested in amplifying his legacy, high quality images of his work can be downloaded for free from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rijksmuseum.nl/en/search?q=&amp;quot;Willem Arondéus&amp;quot;&quot;&gt;Rijksmuseum&lt;/a&gt;, Amsterdam and make beautiful prints.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m grateful to the contributors towards this Wikipedia article which I’ve drawn on in the above biography: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Willem_Arondeus&quot;&gt;Willem Arondeus - Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Bethany</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="lesbian gay and bisexual" />
      
        <category term="sexual orientation" />
      
        <category term="biography" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">This LGBT History Month we would like to invite a celebration of some lesser known heroes who don’t always feature on the mainstream narrative.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Gay in the UK</title>
      <link href="/posts/2023-02-14-gay-in-the-uk/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Gay in the UK" />
      <published>2023-02-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-02-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/gay-in-the-uk</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2023-02-14-gay-in-the-uk/">&lt;p&gt;I have been delighted to write this blog for SEEN, for LGB(T) History Month.. This blog particularly focuses on a potted history of gay rights in the UK as they relate to gay men, but later in the month a ‘sister’ piece will be released focusing on lesbian history. The blog covers 500 years worth of history, and shows how the rights for gay men to live and love freely are an incredibly recent occurrence within the history of the UK, still very much in living memory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;from-tudor-times-to-the-victorian-era&quot;&gt;From Tudor Times to the Victorian Era&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Male homosexuality was explicitly outlawed in Britain (well, actually the Kingdom of England at the time) in 1533 by King Henry VIII, in the charmingly titled Buggery Act.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Under the Buggery Act, men having sexual relationships with other men faced the possibility of being sentenced to death, and prosecutions were often brought in circumstances where men showed any affection to each other - even if there was no evidence of sexual relations between them. The law was extended to Wales in 1543, and Ireland in 1634.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Records of Scotland’s legal history prior to the union with England are more hazy, but we do know in Scotland the first prosecution for ‘sodomy’ that led to the execution of two men was in 1570, when John Litster and John Swann were strangled and then burnt at the stake.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In England, in the first 100 years of the Buggery Act’s enforcement, only one man was executed, Walter Hungerford, and as he was already on trial for treason and heresy the charge of buggery was added to ‘humiliate’ him more prior to his execution. Prosecutions for buggery where the death penalty was handed down remained rare until 1700, and only became more common after the year 1800. In the period between 1806 and 1861, there were 8921 prosecutions for buggery in England and Wales and 404 death sentences were issued, though only 56 men were executed. The last two men executed for homosexual acts in England and Wales were John Smith and James Pratt, in 1835.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ramping up of prosecutions for ‘buggery’ coincided with a growing subculture of homosexual men, particularly in larger cities and specifically in London. ‘Molly Houses’ were both secret bars and taverns for homosexual men to meet, and frequently were also brothels where men could buy sex from other men. Contemporary accounts of Molly Houses and their goings on often relied on the oft-quoted cliché that homosexual men are not real men, and the language used would today be seen as both homophobic and misogynistic. The 18&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; century journalist Ned Ward stated,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“the men rather fancy themselves as women, imitated all the little vanities that custom has reconciled to the female sex, affecting to speak, walk, tattle, curtsy, cry, scold, and mimic all manner of effeminacy.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite this, men of all types were known to frequent the establishments - traditionally masculine men as well as effeminate men - and men from all walks of life and social standing. While usually a safe haven, many of the prosecutions of men during the 18&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; century for buggery were the result of raids on Molly Houses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1861, the Offences Against the Person Act&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; combined a number of existing laws for England, Wales and Ireland, including the Buggery Act, and the death penalty was removed as a possible punishment&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, ‘reduced’ to a maximum punishment of between ten years and life imprisonment. The 1885 Labouchere Amendment&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:6&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; explicitly made all homosexual acts between men illegal, not just ‘buggery’, and introduced the concept of ‘gross indecency’. In 1895 it was ‘gross indecency’ rather than ‘buggery’ for which Oscar Wilde was convicted, following his sexual relationships with other men (primarily Lord Alfred Douglas) and Wilde served two years hard labour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-early-20th-century&quot;&gt;The early 20&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; century&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the early 20&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; century, male homosexuality seemed to become more ‘tolerated’ but only in certain parts of society. Homosexual men of the upper classes that were able to live a life of relative luxury were often left to their own devices if they kept their proclivities behind closed doors. The first ‘gay bar’ as we would consider it today opened in 1912 - ‘The Cave of the Golden Calf’ - but it was open only to the wealthy and the aristocratic. The bar only lasted two years but gained a notorious reputation in that short time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the First World War, other gay bars started slowly opening up.. This coincided with the growing metropolitan elite in the media arena. Radio remained a hugely popular form of entertainment, and BBC Television launched in earnest in 1936. Playwrights, actors and musicians effectively became the new aristocracy, and it was an open secret amongst the upper echelons of society that men like Noel Coward ‘preferred the company of other men’, even if the general public remained blissfully unaware.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, for every step forward, there were two steps back. Following the Second World War, arrests and prosecutions for homosexual acts between men started to increase significantly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alan Turing is now well known. He built the first model of a computer, and was hugely influential in the history of computer science. He should always have been a national hero for his work on the Enigma code, and how that helped shape the fortunes of the allied forces in WW2, but for a long time his involvement was a highly classified state secret. This was because, in 1952, Turing was convicted of ‘gross indecency’ for having a sexual relationship with another man. Given the option of imprisonment or chemical castration, he chose the latter. The chemical castration was done via the use of a synthetic oestrogen analogue, which left Turing impotent and caused him to grow breast tissue. Turing had his security clearance revoked and was barred from continuing to work with GCHQ. Following this horrific treatment, in 1954, aged just 41, Turing killed himself with a fatal dose of cyanide.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:7&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:7&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;decriminalisation-and-immediate-aftermath&quot;&gt;Decriminalisation and immediate aftermath&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the increase of prosecutions for male homosexuality post-WW2, and the high profile cases of Alan Turing and other prominent figures in the early 1950s, many senior politicians became concerned. In 1954, Winston Churchill’s Conservative government set up a committee headed by Sir John Wolfenden to look into homosexuality and other sexual offences. In 1957 the committee published a report - The Report of the Departmental Committee on Homosexual Offences and Prostitution - often referred to simply as ‘The Wolfenden Report’.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:8&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:8&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Wolfenden Report recommended that homosexual acts between men should be decriminalised, and saw this as a civil liberties issue. The report stated: “It is not, in our view, the function of the law to intervene in the private life of citizens, or to seek to enforce any particular pattern of behaviour.” It also refused to classify homosexuality as a mental illness, which is notable as it was not until 1974 that the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders (an American publication but with broad international recognition) removed homosexuality as a mental illness, the World Health Organisation (WHO) did not do so until 1992!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It took a long time for the report’s recommendations on decriminalising homosexuality to be implemented. There was furious opposition to the report’s recommendations, especially from religious leaders and certain sections of the press. It was 1967 when the ‘Sexual Offences Act’ passed&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:9&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:9&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, a whole decade after the report was published. This Act (applicable only to England and Wales) decriminalised sex between two men, aged 21 or over, in private, and was a true watershed moment in the history of gay rights in the UK - even if there was still a long way to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to our saturation in American culture and media, the 1969 ‘Stonewall Riots’ in New York are often overstated in their relevance to gay rights in the UK. The riots were two years after the decriminalisation of male homosexual acts in England and Wales, and at best are a footnote to gay rights in the UK. But the influence of the USA’s Gay Liberation Movement (GLF) inspired a similar group in the UK (and much later the UK organisation ‘Stonewall’ took its name from the bar where the New York riots occurred).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK GLF launched in 1970, and while it officially shut down in 1973, other organisations sprung up in its wake. The 1970s remained a hostile time for most gay men, and gay men in the media, even the most flamboyant, remained ‘in the closet’ to the general public, just as in the 1930s. Activist groups also sprang up to oppose not just gay rights groups but what they saw as society becoming corrupted by post-1960s sexual liberties. Mary Whitehouse was famously opposed to gay men having any rights or visibility in society, and the GLF disrupted her ‘Festival of Light’ in 1971. Whitehouse remained a formidable figure for the rest of her life, and in 1976 she brought a private blasphemy case against the publication ‘Gay News’&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:10&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:10&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; (the first notable gay periodical in the UK, launched in 1972) for printing a poem that depicted a Roman Centurion having a sexual relationship with Jesus Christ.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout the 1970s, male homosexual acts remained a criminal activity in Scotland, and were only decriminalised in 1980, following the passing of the Criminal Justice (Scotland) Act 1980 (Section 80).&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:11&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:11&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;aids-and-thatchers-britain&quot;&gt;AIDS and Thatcher’s Britain&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The culture in the 1980s saw a seismic shift in the visibility of gay men, and some men challenged traditional sexist norms of how they should act, dress and behave. While many high profile media figures who would come out later in life remained ‘in the closet’, men like Jimmy Sommerville and Pete Burns were flamboyantly and openly gay and bisexual at a time when it was still very dangerous for them to do so. But the early 1980s saw the emergence of a catastrophe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AIDS was first noted in 1981 as a mysterious disease in the USA, primarily affecting gay men. By 1983, there had been 14 known cases of AIDS in the UK - mainly men - and thereafter, diagnoses skyrocketed. An AIDS diagnosis was a death sentence. Many men died very soon after diagnosis. It was in 1984 when the virus that caused AIDS - HIV - was identified. As the 1980s grew on, more and more people were diagnosed as HIV+ or with AIDS, the overwhelming majority being gay and bisexual men. AIDS completely decimated gay communities throughout the country, and the media became overtaken with a frenzied, homophobic hysteria that targeted gay men and what was often called ‘the gay plague’. Tabloid headlines became increasingly more overtly hostile, The Sun famously running a headline stating &lt;em&gt;‘If my son gets AIDS I’ll shoot him’&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:12&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:12&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In 1986 a huge AIDS awareness campaign was launched in the UK, with actor John Hurt as the public face of it. The simple and chilling message was ‘AIDS: Don’t Die of Ignorance’.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:13&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:13&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The AIDS epidemic was one of the many factors that led to Mrs Thatcher’s growing concerns about homosexuality and the influence it could have on children. In 1988, her government passed Section 28 of the Local Government Act.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:14&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:14&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Section 28 stated that local authorities &lt;em&gt;“shall not intentionally promote homosexuality or publish material with the intention of promoting homosexuality”&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;“promote the teaching in any maintained school of the acceptability of homosexuality as a pretended family relationship”&lt;/em&gt;. The law effectively gagged school teachers from talking about homosexuality or gay relationships at all, even to older teenagers. This also effectively acted as a neat way from stopping teachers addressing often horrific homophobic bullying that was being carried out in secondary schools across the country. In 1989, gay and lesbian activists formed Stonewall UK, at the time an organisation looking to progress gay and lesbian rights in the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;john-major-to-new-labour&quot;&gt;John Major to New Labour&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout the 1990s, AIDS was still a massive concern, especially for gay men, even if there was less public hysteria over the illness - though the tabloid press and much of the mainstream media still remained openly hostile and homophobic for much of the decade. In 1991 one of the most high profile deaths from AIDS happened when Freddie Mercury passed away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gay men’s lifestyle magazines such as ‘Gay Times’ and ‘Attitude’ had their heyday. While the former focused on more serious news items than the latter, both were heavily filled with fashion, scene issues, and a large amount of advocacy for safe sex. Condoms and safe sex pretty much defined gay male culture in the 1990s.Although advances in medicine were starting to make the HIV virus more manageable, in many cases it was still a death sentence. Most life insurance companies refused to cover any men who were or had been in a sexual relationship with another man.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1994, Conservative MP Edwina Currie tabled an amendment to the Sexual Offences Act to equalise the age of consent to 16 for male homosexual sex, as it was for opposite-sex partners.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:15&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:15&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; She was unsuccessful in this venture, but instead the age of consent was lowered to 18 from 21. More on this later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1997 saw radical change in the UK when Tony Blair’s New Labour took power to the sound of ‘Things Can Only Get Better’. More advances in gay rights came at the turn of the new millennium. While Edwina Curry had been unsuccessful in her efforts at equalising age of consent laws, Blair’s Labour government did so with the Sexual Offences (Amendment) Act 2000, with Jack Straw playing a very key part in this move.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘Section 28’ was repealed in the year 2000 in Scotland and in 2003 in England and Wales, while the ban on gay men, lesbians and bisexual people serving in the military was lifted in 2000. While in recent years, the organisation ‘Stonewall’ has become hugely controversial as its core mission has significantly changed, it is undeniable that at the time they were hugely instrumental in the military ban being overturned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2002, Blair’s government passed the Adoption and Children Act which made it legal for same-sex couples to adopt children, and in 2004 Civil Partnerships were introduced, allowing same-sex couples to have their relationship legally recognised and provide almost all the benefits of marriage. Blair was cautious about introducing full blown ‘gay marriage’ and at the time Civil Partnerships were seen by many as an acceptable compromise. Stonewall UK famously felt Civil Partnerships were adequate and for many years following refused to support calls for same-sex marriage. Of course, gay and lesbian people are not a monolith, and some supported gay marriage while others were opposed.. From conservatives at one end who felt, despite the fact they were gay, marriage should only be for a man and woman - to radicals at the other end who felt LGB people (gay men in particular) should not ‘ape’ heteronormativity at all or even have monogamous relationships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also from the late ’90s, more and more gay representation started being seen on our TV screens, and gay characters became less ‘sexless’ and more sexually active. The hugely controversial ‘Queer as Folk’ hit Channel 4 in 1999, depicting graphic scenes of sex between men, and the cult BBC Sitcom ‘Gimme Gimme Gimme’ gave comedy fans a bitchy, narcissistic and promiscuous gay man as one of the two central characters. In 2001, Big Brother winner Brian Dowling became the first openly gay man to host a children’s television show, when he landed a job on SMTV Live.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;2010---present&quot;&gt;2010 - Present&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many could have been forgiven for believing homophobia was a thing of the past and gay rights were now a sorted issue, especially following the legalisation of same-sex marriage in early 2014, by David Cameron’s coalition government. HIV treatment is more effective than ever, and many people on effective retro-virals are able to live long, happy lives. HIV is no longer a death sentence, but the importance of regular testing cannot be overstated. The slogan is now ‘undetectable is untransmissible’, as effective retro-virals that leave the virus undetectable means there is almost zero chance of transmitting the virus, and now there are many HIV+ men in long term relationships with partners who are HIV-. The development of PrEP (Pre-Exposure Prophylaxis) also means men with a particularly high risk sex life are able to further protect themselves from becoming HIV+, as if the medicine is used correctly then there is again almost no chance of being infected with the virus even if exposed to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But for those of us outside of metropolitan bubbles, it is far from the case that homophobia is now ‘sorted’. In many parts of the country, casual homophobia is still a huge problem, and many same-sex couples are still too fearful to hold hands with their partner in public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those that attended my speech at the SEEN launch event, or who have read the transcript&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:16&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:16&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, you will know my personal experience. In addition to the traditional homophobia we have always faced, we now see a new rise of homophobia from ‘within our own communities’ with many organisations and groups which are ostensibly for gay rights now fundamentally ideologically opposed to the very nature of homosexuality and exclusive same sex attraction. We have come a long way from the Molly Houses of the 18&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; and 19&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; centuries, but places for gay men are once again moving underground and becoming more secretive. What will the future hold? Only time will tell…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;further-reading&quot;&gt;Further Reading&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.historyhit.com/the-wolfenden-report-a-turning-point-for-gay-rights-in-britain/&quot;&gt;The Wolfenden Report: A Turning Point for Gay Rights in Britain (History Hit)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-england-london-55983269&quot;&gt;‘Life was a party before Aids arrived in London’ (BBC News)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.historyextra.com/period/20th-century/aids-hiv-epidemic-changed-britain-how/&quot;&gt;Aids: History Of The Epidemic That Changed Britain (History Extra)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.nationalarchives.gov.uk/equality-of-sexuality-the-age-of-consent/&quot;&gt;Equality of sexuality: The age of consent (The National Archives blog)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://news.sky.com/story/military-marks-20-years-since-homosexuality-ban-was-lifted-11906701&quot;&gt;Military marks 20 years since homosexuality ban was lifted (Sky News)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-scotland-40731733&quot;&gt;Illegal to be gay - Scotland’s history (BBC News)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;15 Feb 2023: corrected Section 28 Sentence repeal year for England and Wales, and added Scotland repeal year.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover inage:&lt;/strong&gt; “Gay History Timeline” by mikecogh is licensed under CC BY-SA 2.0. To view a copy of this license, visit https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0/?ref=openverse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bl.uk/collection-items/the-buggery-act-1533&quot;&gt;https://www.bl.uk/collection-items/the-buggery-act-1533&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://universityofglasgowlibrary.wordpress.com/2017/02/15/lgbti-history-month-a-scottish-reading-list/&quot;&gt;https://universityofglasgowlibrary.wordpress.com/2017/02/15/lgbti-history-month-a-scottish-reading-list/&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://rictornorton.co.uk/eighteen/nedward.htm&quot;&gt;http://rictornorton.co.uk/eighteen/nedward.htm&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/Vict/24-25/100/contents&quot;&gt;https://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/Vict/24-25/100/contents&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://voicesandvisibility.org.uk/timeline/legal-timeline/&quot;&gt;http://voicesandvisibility.org.uk/timeline/legal-timeline/&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.parliament.uk/about/living-heritage/transformingsociety/private-lives/relationships/collections1/sexual-offences-act-1967/1885-labouchere-amendment/&quot;&gt;https://www.parliament.uk/about/living-heritage/transformingsociety/private-lives/relationships/collections1/sexual-offences-act-1967/1885-labouchere-amendment/&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:6&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:7&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2019/06/05/obituaries/alan-turing-overlooked.html&quot;&gt;https://www.nytimes.com/2019/06/05/obituaries/alan-turing-overlooked.html&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:7&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:8&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.parliament.uk/about/living-heritage/transformingsociety/private-lives/relationships/collections1/sexual-offences-act-1967/wolfenden-report-/&quot;&gt;https://www.parliament.uk/about/living-heritage/transformingsociety/private-lives/relationships/collections1/sexual-offences-act-1967/wolfenden-report-/&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:8&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:9&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.parliament.uk/about/living-heritage/transformingsociety/private-lives/relationships/collections1/sexual-offences-act-1967/sexual-offences-act-1967/&quot;&gt;https://www.parliament.uk/about/living-heritage/transformingsociety/private-lives/relationships/collections1/sexual-offences-act-1967/sexual-offences-act-1967/&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:9&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:10&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.historytoday.com/miscellanies/blasphemy-trial&quot;&gt;https://www.historytoday.com/miscellanies/blasphemy-trial&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:10&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:11&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Criminal_Justice_(Scotland)_Act_1980&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Criminal_Justice_Scotland_Act_1980&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:11&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:12&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://images.app.goo.gl/CEYkpzX3YdV9nVyG7&quot;&gt;https://images.app.goo.gl/CEYkpzX3YdV9nVyG7&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:12&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:13&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=iroty5zwOVw&quot;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=iroty5zwOVw&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:13&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:14&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/1988/9/section/28/enacted&quot;&gt;https://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/1988/9/section/28/enacted&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:14&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:15&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm199394/cmhansrd/1994-02-21/Debate-12.html&quot;&gt;https://publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm199394/cmhansrd/1994-02-21/Debate-12.html&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:15&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:16&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/posts/2023-01-04-why-is-seen-important-to-me/&quot;&gt;https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-01-04-why-is-seen-important-to-me/&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:16&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Jimmy</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="lesbian gay and bisexual" />
      
        <category term="sexual orientation" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">I have been delighted to write this blog for SEEN, for LGB(T) History Month.. This blog particularly focuses on a potted history of gay rights in the UK as they relate to gay men, but later in the month a ‘sister’ piece will be released focusing on lesbian history. The blog covers 500 years worth of history, and shows how the rights for gay men to live and love freely are an incredibly recent occurrence within the history of the UK, still very much in living memory.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Why SEEN is important to me (i)</title>
      <link href="/posts/2023-01-04-why-is-seen-important-to-me/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why SEEN is important to me (i)" />
      <published>2023-01-04T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-01-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/why-is-seen-important-to-me</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2023-01-04-why-is-seen-important-to-me/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[This post is the first of &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/launch-speeches/&quot;&gt;four speeches by SEEN members&lt;/a&gt; from our launch event in October.]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is SEEN important to me? To explain this, I need to go back in time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m now 38 years old, and I’ve known I was gay since my early teens. I was ‘out’ since I was 16 years old. Which, at the time, was pretty unusual especially living in the Welsh valleys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s incredibly embarrassing to have to say this, but when I was 16, my best female friend romantically propositioned me. I thought I could maybe give it a go as I misconstrued my strong friendship feelings for her as potentially something else, and maybe I wasn’t 100% gay after all. As it turned out, it wasn’t her hairstyle, make-up, clothes, or feminine style that turned me off – it was the reality of her female body. It seems bizarre to have to say this now, even little over 5 years ago if I said I was gay, everyone would have understood this to mean I am exclusively homosexual, an adult human male only attracted to other adult human males. Now to say I am gay apparently means something else, it means I am attracted to someone’s internal sense of masculine ‘identity’. Well this is not so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;there-arent-many-homosexuals-around&quot;&gt;There aren’t many homosexuals around!&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Homosexual people are actually quite a small minority, regardless of what people may assume otherwise.
According to the ONS’s 2020 estimates, 2.5% of men in the UK are exclusively homosexual, and 1.1% of women are.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; However, it’s not uncommon to see a much larger figure quoted, with suggestions that as many as 1 in 10 people are part of the ‘LGBTQIA+ community’.  The large number is in part due to the fact that the definition given of what it means to be ‘queer’ can be extremely broad, even extending to anyone who feels ‘outside the norms of society’.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I’m here because I want to talk specifically about homosexuality, and factoring in men and women, the amount of actual homosexual people in the population is about 1 in 56. There are also, of course, bisexual people. 1.6% of women in the UK are bisexual, and 0.9% of men are. So that means an estimated 3.1% of the population of the UK are Lesbian, Gay or Bisexual by 2020 ONS estimates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, because so many other people now identify as ‘queer’ or another identity, homosexual men and lesbian women are now a minority within this rapidly expanding community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;homosexual-people-are-same-sex-attracted-and-it-is-not-offensive-to-say-so&quot;&gt;Homosexual people are same-sex attracted, and it is not offensive to say so&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Homosexual people are oppressed on the basis of sex. Gay men are oppressed because we are exclusively attracted to men, of the same sex. Lesbians are doubly oppressed because they are oppressed as women, their sex, and because of their attraction to other women, their same-sex attraction.  To understand this oppression, you have to understand the reality of sex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sex matters. As JK Rowling said – ‘if sex isn’t real, there’s no same-sex attraction’.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; I am not gay because I have a particular political or philosophical belief, but only because I am exclusively same-sex attracted. No more, no less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another problem I have with the blanket term ‘queer’ is that it masks this important distinction.  This isn’t the only issue with ‘queer’.  Furthermore, for many homosexuals such as myself even the use of the word ‘queer’ is uncomfortable. For many of us ‘queer’ is a horrific slur that has been used predominantly against gay men. Noting in 2018 the website ‘Back2Stonewall’ ran a poll on the word queer, 93% of gay men who responded said they do not accept this word and still regard it as a slur.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;homosexual-people-do-not-all-have-the-same-beliefs-and-opinions-regardless-of-what-people-may-tell-you-otherwise&quot;&gt;Homosexual people do not all have the same beliefs and opinions, regardless of what people may tell you otherwise&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Along with demographic shifts in what it means to be part of the community that was once LGB, there has also been a trend towards increasing conformity in what this community thinks, politically.  My own experience of  ‘gay groups’ and organisations, and sadly, most LGBT networks I’ve encountered in the Civil Service, is that there is an increased expectation that I won’t talk about the fact I’m homosexual.  This is because the phrases ‘homosexual’ and ‘same-sex attraction’ are sometimes considered ‘dog-whistles’ for bigotry.  Gay men and lesbians may be told we have to be inclusive of people who are not gay and lesbian in our groups, organisations, meetings and safe spaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My experience of other staff networks has told me I have to listen to ‘allies’ who speak for me and spread the word that all gay people think and feel the same, and have the same political and philosophical beliefs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not true, as I said earlier, all we have in common is our sexual orientation. Nothing more, nothing less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I need to stress that these networks are perfectly entitled to exist, and I am sure many staff feel they represent them, but I needed to make the point how I do not feel they represent me, and that I am not even welcome in them, as to why SEEN is important to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;homosexuals-need-their-own-spaces&quot;&gt;Homosexuals need their own spaces&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of the broadening of what it means to be ‘queer’ groups and spaces for actual gay men, lesbians and bisexual people, are underground in a way not seen since at least the 1980s. Secret code words, handshakes, locked doors, moving in the shadows.  I know many now fear describing ourselves as homosexual lest we are ejected from the very organisations that were once set up to protect us and further our rights, because we do not necessarily share the politics of these groups&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For many lesbians and homosexuals, there is a growing need for a community that understands the particular concerns and oppressions of being a gay man or a lesbian woman.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Homosexual people must be able to protect our hard-won right to associate exclusively on the basis of our sexual orientation if we so wish, and have the right to exclude people who aren’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;why-seen-matters-to-me&quot;&gt;Why SEEN matters to me&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My experience of other staff networks has sadly been that I do not always have a voice, and I am not always made to feel welcome to talk about how I am homosexual, or to talk about the fact that sex is relevant to my orientation, or to not talk about homophobia in work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And SEEN allows me to express this most basic fact. And that is why SEEN is of such importance to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This network is important to me because &lt;strong&gt;no other network I have found in the Civil Service allows me to discuss or describe my lived experience or talk about any of the above points.&lt;/strong&gt;  I look to SEEN to give me a voice as a homosexual man, same sex attracted who believes in the reality of sex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover image:&lt;/strong&gt;   “Deep in Thought” by kreg.steppe is licensed under CC BY-SA 2.0. To view a copy of this license, visit https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0/?ref=openverse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ons.gov.uk/peoplepopulationandcommunity/culturalidentity/sexuality/datasets/sexualidentityuk&quot;&gt;https://www.ons.gov.uk/peoplepopulationandcommunity/culturalidentity/sexuality/datasets/sexualidentityuk&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.healthline.com/health/am-i-queer-enough&quot;&gt;https://www.healthline.com/health/am-i-queer-enough&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jk_rowling/status/1269389298664701952&quot;&gt;https://twitter.com/jk_rowling/status/1269389298664701952&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.back2stonewall.com/2018/05/lgbt-website-survey-finds-that-93-of-gay-men-polled-dont-want-to-be-labeled-queer.html&quot;&gt;http://www.back2stonewall.com/2018/05/lgbt-website-survey-finds-that-93-of-gay-men-polled-dont-want-to-be-labeled-queer.html&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Jimmy</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="personal experience" />
      
        <category term="lesbian gay and bisexual" />
      
        <category term="sexual orientation" />
      
        <category term="coming of age" />
      
        <category term="launch speeches" />
      
        <category term="why seen" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">[This post is the first of four speeches by SEEN members from our launch event in October.]</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
