<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/jan/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2025-08-26T22:05:27+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/jan/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">SEEN | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Sex Equality and Equity Network</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Rural lesbians and a safer world</title>
      <link href="/posts/2023-06-29-rural-lesbians-and-a-safer-world/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rural lesbians and a safer world" />
      <published>2023-06-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-06-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/rural-lesbians-and-a-safer-world</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2023-06-29-rural-lesbians-and-a-safer-world/">&lt;p&gt;I grew up in the rural idyll of Herefordshire &amp;amp; Worcestershire, having known most of my life that I was attracted to my own sex. There was little chance of my ever “coming out”, even though I went to an all-girls school, because at that time there was still huge stigma attached to being lesbian. It would have been social death at school, and I really didn’t want to cope with being ostracised while trying to complete my O-levels. The successful gaining of O-levels was directly linked to my gaining a motorbike and I wanted that nearly as much as I wanted a set of drums.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peer pressure and hormones encouraged me to have boyfriends and although I knew it wasn’t for me, I persevered in the hope Mr Right might rock up. He almost did, but when I met the woman of my dreams all that faded into dust. She was an old school friend who’d moved to the USA and done her coming out while playing in a rock band. I had all the savvy of vegetarianism and an interest in surviving the nuclear threat, so she was impossibly cool and desirable in comparison.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We went out to Birmingham, to find signs of life. It was an eye opener for me but ennui for her. After a brief but intense fling where I finally gained escape velocity from heterosexuality, she went back to America and I went off to the feminist peace protest at Greenham Common.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, I now needed a girlfriend to cement my fledgling lesbian status and fortunately one appeared. We had very similar backgrounds and interests, and we were both seeking our first female partner. I struggled to find my feet in this new world and my parents’ aspirations for me evaporated. After some tense battles - &lt;em&gt;“It’s like you’re going through puberty again!”&lt;/em&gt; - I was kicked out and this is how I ended up in a 25 year relationship complete with cats and eventually a civil partnership. With hindsight, I should have slowed down, but the miniscule size of my lesbian dating pool added pressure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If only there’d been somewhere to go for advice and support… At the time there was London Gay Switchboard, or Lesbian Line (one night a week). It was impossible to get through on either number. And what could they have advised me, anyway? Go to the big city like Jimmy Somerville? Move to Greenham and hope for the best?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the late 1980s, the HIV/AIDS crisis had arrived and was changing the complexion of gay life forever. Bizarrely, it was this situation that pushed many of us into action. With my gay male friends, we women had been talking about setting something up to help our community, and we decided we needed our own lifeline. Hereford &amp;amp; Worcester Lesbian &amp;amp; Gay Switchboard was born. As is often the case, we had more men than women in the group, but we did our best to train ourselves and learn to handle calls of all kinds and from either sex. I absolutely know what a vertical learning curve feels like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We set up a monthly fundraiser at a local nightclub, and swiftly gained support from the local sexual health team who were desperate to promote safer sex. This was the battleground era of Section 28 (a law which that prohibited the “promotion of homosexuality” by local authorities) and AIDS scaremongering, so looking back I realise quite how brave and determined we were. The head of the county education authority wanted our Switchboard’s service office closed down because we were in a building with many other charities and there were “vulnerable young people in wheelchairs”. The venom and gross prejudice was palpable but we held our ground and triumphed over adversity for over ten years. Our mission for the Switchboard was that we would not need to exist: we hoped the world would catch up and become a more welcoming place for us. When the calls slowed to a trickle, we knew things had changed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We organised the first gathering of UK lesbian and gay switchboards over a weekend in Worcester and even the mighty London Switchboard turned up! A mix of rural and urban organisations were represented. I delivered a presentation on sexual health and safer sex for lesbians, which at the time was either overlooked or subject to bad advice. For example, lesbians were told we didn’t need to take tests for cervical cancer. I made the plea for better understanding of lesbian health needs as well as those of our gay brothers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those years hold bittersweet memories of struggle, insight, joy, fellowship and loss. They helped form the person I am today and drive me to want that perspective in my working life. SEEN offers the chance for us to recreate the best of that shared history for lesbians and gay men in the civil service, and I look forward to welcoming colleagues as we grow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover image&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/photos/nAizdTpHUTM&quot;&gt;Peter Musk&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/license&quot;&gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Jan</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="lesbian gay and bisexual" />
      
        <category term="sexual orientation" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">I grew up in the rural idyll of Herefordshire &amp;amp; Worcestershire, having known most of my life that I was attracted to my own sex. There was little chance of my ever “coming out”, even though I went to an all-girls school, because at that time there was still huge stigma attached to being lesbian. It would have been social death at school, and I really didn’t want to cope with being ostracised while trying to complete my O-levels. The successful gaining of O-levels was directly linked to my gaining a motorbike and I wanted that nearly as much as I wanted a set of drums.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Celebrating Lesbian Visibility Day 2023</title>
      <link href="/posts/2023-04-26-lesbian-visibility-day/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Celebrating Lesbian Visibility Day 2023" />
      <published>2023-04-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-04-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/lesbian-visibility-day</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2023-04-26-lesbian-visibility-day/">&lt;p&gt;Lesbians in history have tended to be largely invisible (try naming five famous lesbians… or try naming five famous lesbians without mentioning Martina). Despite a heyday in the 1990s, we are once again disappearing - hence Lesbian Visibility Day.  Let’s prepare for our day of celebration and visibility by looking at a selection of historical highlights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lesbian mythology includes gems like this: Ministers bringing legislation outlawing homosexuality to Queen Victoria for royal assent were too nervous to explain the intent to include women. Some say Victoria was told, but reacted with such disbelief that ladies would behave that way, that only men were outlawed! So in recent history, lesbians remained legally undescribed. This was handy if you didn’t want to be imprisoned, but unhelpful in terms of being understood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patriarchy was largely unbothered by lesbianism, unless there was any threat to male superiority. But there were economic reasons why women struggled to live independently from men. Love whom you like, so long as you can afford it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Women living apart from men have always been treated with suspicion and had fewer life choices, for both economic and social reasons: wife, witch or nun, basically. Whether the concept of lesbianism as we know it today would have been understood prior to the 20th century is debatable, but it’s likely there have always been women desperate to avoid “traditional” gender roles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most famous lesbian, Sappho, lived on the Greek island of Lesbos around 630- 570 BC. This is how here we get the term “lesbian”. Sappho was a revered lyric poet, but most of her works are lost so we rely only on remaining fragments. Sappho was possibly the Melissa Etheridge of her day, writing songs that told of love between women - but like the C90 cassette compilation of my favourite songs, they are lost to us now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arabian writings about lesbianism from the medieval era include perhaps the first (written) lesbian love story, in a 10th century treatise called “The Encyclopaedia of Pleasure”. The Medieval Europeans were far more draconian in their views on homosexuality, with severe punishment (including torturous death) for men and banishment for women. By the time of the Spanish Inquisition, only the pure escaped punishment. Lesbians were therefore overly represented amongst witches and in female-only institutions like convents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later famous lesbians include the Ladies of Llangollen and Anne Lister. Thanks to her diaries and the recent successful TV drama, the legendary Anne Lister is well known for her love of the “fairer sex”, as well as the financial independence which enabled her to indulge it. She visited the Ladies in Llangollen, which begs the question of how they organised this in days of very slow media. I live in the super-speedy online world of the 21st century and it’s like herding cats getting a group of lesbians together in the same space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Salon culture of Paris and other European cities during the early 20th century was tailored to the rich, famous, or rising stars, but also provided previously unavailable social opportunities for lesbians. The Second World War provided untold chances for lesbians, as women worked beyond the home. Lesbian culture developed a strong underground vibe, hidden away from salacious eyes. Watch the film “The Killing of Sister George”, revealing the (literally underground) Gateways club in the 1960s. There were similar hideaways still available in 1980s Brighton!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Treatment for male homosexuality largely depended on class/ money, but there is little research or data regarding lesbians. Many lesbians ended up in mental hospitals, and some of them never left. Attempts to “cure” homosexuality are notoriously unsuccessful and mercifully some psychiatrists realised this. A lesbian treated by a female psychiatrist at the Tavistock clinic following a suicide attempt was told: “You must remember it is natural for you… People who are left-handed and who are forced to write with their right hand usually develop a stutter…and you are sexually left handed” (Sarah Carr &amp;amp; Helen Spandler, The Lancet April 2019).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The USA’s influential Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders listed homosexuality as a mental disorder from 1968 until 1973, when it became a “sexual orientation disturbance”. But homosexuality only left the publication in 1987 – two years after I “came out” as lesbian.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Lesbian” is falling out of fashion for some, in favour words like “queer” or “gay”, or sometimes replaced with the terms “bisexual” or “pansexual”. Theories for this suggest the word lesbian is considered to be old-fashioned or embarrassing.  However, many of us remain happy and proud to call ourselves lesbians, as it is a distinctive and defining word for us as female homosexuals, separate from men’s words. Interestingly, male homosexuals are far less likely to have their terminology and culture challenged!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know that women and girls throughout history (and still today in some parts of the world) have disguised themselves as males to get work, be educated, travel alone, escape marriage, or simply to try to keep safe from sexual attack. Some women will have done this to be free to have relationships with other women, but it’s hard to be sure because clear evidence like Anne Lister’s diaries is scarce. Women have always pursued close relationships with each other and lived together for many reasons, which won’t always have been romantic or sexual. Women’s solidarity and closeness is an historical constant, whether we are lesbian or not, and we should celebrate whatever form that takes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you do meet a lesbian in the wild today, rejoice, for we are in small numbers and often camouflaged, except that one day of the year when we celebrate…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover image:&lt;/strong&gt; Manuscripts and Archives Division, The New York Public Library. &lt;em&gt;Lavender Menace members hold signs reading “The women’s movement is a lesbian plot”&lt;/em&gt; The New York Public Library Digital Collections. 1970. https://digitalcollections.nypl.org/items/ac5276a0-9f43-0137-d597-233b6d9ef0dd&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Jan</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="lesbian gay and bisexual" />
      
        <category term="sexual orientation" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Lesbians in history have tended to be largely invisible (try naming five famous lesbians… or try naming five famous lesbians without mentioning Martina). Despite a heyday in the 1990s, we are once again disappearing - hence Lesbian Visibility Day. Let’s prepare for our day of celebration and visibility by looking at a selection of historical highlights.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
