<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/equality/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2025-08-26T22:05:27+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/equality/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">SEEN | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Sex Equality and Equity Network</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Women in the Olympic Games: From Paris 1900 to Paris 2024</title>
      <link href="/posts/2024-07-26-olympics/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Women in the Olympic Games: From Paris 1900 to Paris 2024" />
      <published>2024-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2024-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/olympics</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2024-07-26-olympics/">&lt;p&gt;The Olympic Games have long been a symbol of human excellence, unity, and the relentless pursuit of athletic achievement. However, the journey to equality between men and women within this prestigious event has been a winding path, filled with significant milestones and pioneering figures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Women were excluded from the first modern Olympic Games in 1896 because its founder thought that their participation would be inappropriate. And in the Ancient Olympic Games, women were barred from competing and married women were barred altogether or thrown off a mountain as punishment for illegal attendance.Women in Ancient Greece started their own Olympics, called the Heraean Games, which honoured the Greek goddess Hera.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the first inclusion of female athletes in Paris 1900 to the equal numbers achieved in Paris 2024, the evolution of female participation in the Olympics is a testament to progress and perseverance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;paris-1900-a-historic-beginning&quot;&gt;Paris 1900: A Historic Beginning&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 1900 Paris Olympic Games marked a pivotal moment in the history of sports, as it was the first time women were allowed to compete. This inclusion was not a straightforward triumph but rather a nuanced and often overlooked part of the Games. Out of the 997 athletes who participated, only 22 were women, competing in just five sports: tennis, sailing, croquet, equestrianism, and golf.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most notable figures from these Games was Hélène de Pourtalès, a Swiss sailor. On 22nd of May 1900, de Pourtaès boarded the yacht Lerina as part of the Swiss crew that won the first of two 1-2 ton class regattas that would take place at the Paris 1900 Games. She then became the first ever woman to participate at the Olympics and the first woman to win a medal at the Olympics. Her crew returned in silver medal position the following day in the second 1-2 ton regatta, making her also the first female multiple medallist in history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-evolution-of-female-participation&quot;&gt;The Evolution of Female Participation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The years following 1900 saw a gradual but steady increase in female participation in the Olympic Games. Each successive Games witnessed more women competing in a broader range of sports. The introduction of women’s swimming events in Stockholm 1912 and then women’s athletics and gymnastics in Amsterdam 1928 were significant steps forwards. By the mid-20th Century, the momentum for equality between the sexes in the Olympics was undeniable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The late 20th and early 21st centuries saw the International Olympic Committee (IOC) making more concerted efforts to promote the inclusion of women. Initiatives were introduced to increase the number of sports and events available to female athletes. The 2012 London Olympics were particularly notable, as they were the first Games where women competed in all the sports on the Olympic program. Additionally, the number of female athletes reached 44% of the total participants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;paris-2024-a-milestone&quot;&gt;Paris 2024: A Milestone&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2024 Paris Olympic Games are set to be a historic event, as they will feature an equal number of male and female athletes for the first time in Olympic history. This milestone represents a culmination of over a century of efforts to achieve equality between women and men in sport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paris 2024 will see approximately 10,500 athletes, with an equal split between men and women. This achievement is not just a numerical triumph but a profound statement on the importance of equality and equity in sports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-road-ahead&quot;&gt;The Road Ahead&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While reaching equality in male and female athlete numbers is a significant achievement, the journey towards true equality in sports continues. Efforts must persist to ensure equal representation in coaching, leadership, and decision-making positions within the Olympics and the wider sporting communities. In particular, significant action is required to address the inequality in senior decision making positions in international sport organisations. For example, only 30% of the world’s largest sports federations were chaired by women in 2023. Addressing disparities in media coverage, sponsorship, and funding between male and female athletes remains a critical area for progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most pressing barriers for women in sport today is the persistent problem of sexual harassment and abuse, which not only undermines the dignity and safety of female athletes, but impedes their progress and participation. Creating a safe and respectful environment for all athletes is critical to achieve true equality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The journey is far from over, but with each step, we move closer to a future where every athlete, regardless of their sex, can pursue their Olympic dreams on equal terms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many thanks to the following articles which I used in the research for this piece:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;UNESCO Report&lt;/em&gt; | &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.unesco.org/en/articles/unesco-report-women-and-girls-access-sport-still-lagging-far-behind&quot;&gt;UNESCO Report: Women and girls access to sport still lagging far behind&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Atlas Obscura&lt;/em&gt; | &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.atlasobscura.com/articles/when-ancient-greece-barred-women-from-even-watching-the-games-they-started-their-own-olympics&quot;&gt;When Ancient Greece Banned Women From Olympics, They Started Their Own&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;UN Women&lt;/em&gt; | &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.unwomen.org/en/paris-2024-olympics-new-era-for-women-in-sport&quot;&gt;Paris 2024 Olympics: A new era for women in sport&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Olympics.com&lt;/em&gt; | &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://olympics.com/en/news/five-historic-firsts-for-female-olympians&quot;&gt;International Women’s Day: Five historic firsts for female Olympians&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover photo&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Prospero_Piatti_-_Giochi_Erei_(1901).jpg&quot;&gt;Wikipedia Public Domain&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>UNSEEN</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sport" />
      
        <category term="equality" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The Olympic Games have long been a symbol of human excellence, unity, and the relentless pursuit of athletic achievement. However, the journey to equality between men and women within this prestigious event has been a winding path, filled with significant milestones and pioneering figures.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Protected Characteristics</title>
      <link href="/posts/2023-07-04-the-protected-characteristics-a-reminder/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Protected Characteristics" />
      <published>2023-07-04T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-07-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/the-protected-characteristics-a-reminder</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2023-07-04-the-protected-characteristics-a-reminder/">&lt;p&gt;We often come across training and guidance that makes reference to the protected characteristics, and it’s really important that this is presented correctly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following is a list of all the characteristics defined as ‘protected characteristics’ by the Equality Act 2010:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;age&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;disability&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;gender reassignment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;marriage and civil partnership&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;pregnancy and maternity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;race&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;religion or belief&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;sex (being male or female)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;sexual orientation (being attracted to people of the opposite sex, the same sex or both)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is against the law to discriminate against someone in the workplace because of a protected characteristic, so it is very important to be clear as to which characteristics are protected and to understand what they cover.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of us will be protected by at least four, maybe more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did you know that the protected characteristic of &lt;em&gt;‘religion or belief’&lt;/em&gt; also covers lack of belief (e.g. our colleagues who are Humanist or atheist)?  For example, you cannot be compelled to demonstrate your adherence or support for a belief system you do not share.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Religion or belief&lt;/em&gt; also not only covers religious beliefs (such as those held by our colleagues who are Christian, Muslim, or another faith), it also covers philosophical and non-religious ethical positions (such as following a vegan diet and lifestyle, or being gender critical).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Religion or belief&lt;/em&gt; may also cover beliefs about gender and gender identity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Equality Act, a person has the protected characteristic of &lt;em&gt;gender reassignment&lt;/em&gt; if the person is proposing to undergo, is undergoing or has undergone a process (or part of a process) for the purpose of reassigning the person’s sex by changing physiological or other attributes of sex.  This may also cover some issues relating to gender or gender identity.  It is described in more detail on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.equalityhumanrights.com/en/advice-and-guidance/gender-reassignment-discrimination&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Equality and Human Rights Commission&lt;/em&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, we have also seen internal training which incorrectly states the protected characteristics also include one or more of the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;gender&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;gender expression&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;gender identity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None of these are listed as protected characteristics, which are the nine listed at the start of this post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you come across any training or advice which gets this wrong, please do &lt;a href=&quot;/contact/&quot;&gt;let us know&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover image&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Books-book-pages-read-literature-159866.jpg&quot;&gt;Creative Commons&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>SEEN Network</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="equality act 2010" />
      
        <category term="equality" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">We often come across training and guidance that makes reference to the protected characteristics, and it’s really important that this is presented correctly.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Why SEEN is important to me (vi)</title>
      <link href="/posts/2023-04-24-why-is-seen-important-to-me-vi/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why SEEN is important to me (vi)" />
      <published>2023-04-24T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-04-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/why-is-seen-important-to-me-vi</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2023-04-24-why-is-seen-important-to-me-vi/">&lt;p&gt;In this time of strikes by the public service professions dominated by women, I’ve been reflecting on the often-overlooked history of women in the UK trade union movement and parallels to today, where many women still struggle to have their needs met for appropriate pay and suitable health and safety conditions, including to protect them during pregnancy and maternity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new film &lt;em&gt;Enola Holmes 2&lt;/em&gt; features (spoiler alert) the story of young women and girls working in a match factory, and striking for better pay and conditions. Whilst romanticised elements were added, the story is grounded in fact. 1888 was the start of action by an unlikely group of heroic young women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Girls and women in the Bryant and May match factory in Bow, now a block of luxury flats, were treated appallingly. They worked 12-hour shifts, standing up, dipping wooden matches into a mixture of chemicals which included the highly dangerous white phosphorus, and packing them into boxes. The chemical caused toothaches which worsened into abscesses and necrosis of the jaw – a condition known as “phossy jaw”. As depicted in &lt;em&gt;Enola Holmes 2&lt;/em&gt;, the managers often dismissed the girls and women affected. The pay for this work was very meagre, and halved for girls under the age of 18, even though they were doing the same work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/3/32/Matchgirl_strikers.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of matchgirls participating in a strike against Bryant &amp;amp; May, London 1888&quot; title=&quot;Photo of matchgirls participating in a strike against Bryant &amp;amp; May, London 1888&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The socialist activist and author Annie Besant took up the cause. She interviewed a number of workers, and wrote a shocking and damning article for her own magazine, &lt;em&gt;The Link&lt;/em&gt;, which she entitled &lt;em&gt;“White Slavery in London”&lt;/em&gt;. In it, she described the factory as being like a “prison-house” and the match girls as “undersized, helpless and oppressed”, with one child living on “only bread-and-butter and tea, alike for breakfast and dinner”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Annie Besant’s article enraged the factory owners, who threatened to sue her, and put pressure on their employees to deny the truth of it. The employees wrote to Annie:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Dear lady, they are trying to get the poor girls to say that it is all lies that has been printed and sign papers to say it is lies. Dear lady, we will not sign them.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When one of the women was sacked on suspicion of being the author, on 5th July 1888, all 1,400 women and girls went on strike: “One girl began, and the rest said ‘yes’ so out we all went.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Annie Besant supported the matchmakers to set up a union, led by eight of the matchmakers, including Sarah Chapman, who features in &lt;em&gt;Enola Holmes 2&lt;/em&gt;. They were supported by Annie’s colleagues in the Fabian Society, by Toynbee Hall (an enterprise for social change in the East End, which supported the strike fund) and by newspapers including the widely read &lt;em&gt;Pall Mall Gazette&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;The Times&lt;/em&gt;. Annie took a group of 56 strikers to Parliament, and MPs raised questions about their treatment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within a fortnight of the strike starting, the Bryant and May directors, horrified by the negative publicity, caved completely and met all of the strikers’ demands. Sarah Chapman became the first Matchmakers’ Union delegate, and first woman, to attend the Trades Union Congress, where a resolution was passed stating that men and women should be paid at the same rate for equal work. The match girls’ strike inspired the men of the East End to undertake the dockers’ strike a few weeks later, which closed the Thames for a month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;125 years after the match girls’ strike, I named my own daughter Annie, after Annie Besant – and at 10 she shows every sign of being a similarly fierce feminist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it wasn’t until over a century later,that the Equal Pay Act 1970 was passed, led by Barbara Castle, and it was 1976 before the Act came into force. This followed a 1970 strike by women workers at the Ford factory in Dagenham (also depicted in a film, &lt;em&gt;Made in Dagenham&lt;/em&gt;) because they were paid 15% less than men for the same work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even now, UK legislation only covers disparities between men and women working for the same employer. Government statistics for the UK for 2022 indicate that there remains a median pay gap between men and women of 9.71%. This is attributed to women being more likely to work part-time due to caring responsibilities, with part-time working commanding less pay bargaining power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are also lower rates of pay for professions in which women are or become the majority, a phenomenon known as “workforce feminisation”, whereby female dominated occupations or workplaces are paid less than those which are male-dominated, even if they were previously male-dominated. As the European Commission states: &lt;em&gt;“Highly feminised jobs tend to be systematically undervalued.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pay disparity for women increases with pregnancy, childbirth and care of infants, and again as women reach their 40s, with many reducing their hours to care both for their children and elderly relatives, while often suffering from stress and fatigue. The pay gap is also significantly larger for women from some ethnic groups and for women with disabilities and health challenges, who are likely to suffer particularly from further social and economic barriers to obtaining well-paid work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The workforce “feminisation problem” may also be an issue in some parts of the civil service, and we know there remain other barriers to women thriving in the civil service. This is why it’s so important that SEEN highlights discrimination that is connected to sex and reminds employers to collect and keep sex-disaggregated data. When it comes to equal pay and to health and safety at work, sex really matters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;sources-and-further-reading&quot;&gt;Sources and further reading:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.matchgirls1888.org/the-story-of-the-strike&quot;&gt;https://www.matchgirls1888.org/the-story-of-the-strike&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matchgirls%27_strike&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matchgirls%27_strike&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/dit-gender-pay-gap-report-and-data-2021-to-2022/dit-gender-pay-gap-report-2021-to-2022#:~:text=or%20a%20woman.-,The%20gender%20pay%20gap,to%20%C2%A32.68%20in%202021&quot;&gt;https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/dit-gender-pay-gap-report-and-data-2021-to-2022/dit-gender-pay-gap-report-2021-to-2022#:~:text=or%20a%20woman.-,The%20gender%20pay%20gap,to%20%C2%A32.68%20in%202021&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://commission.europa.eu/strategy-and-policy/policies/justice-and-fundamental-rights/gender-equality/equal-pay/gender-pay-gap-situation-eu_en&quot;&gt;https://commission.europa.eu/strategy-and-policy/policies/justice-and-fundamental-rights/gender-equality/equal-pay/gender-pay-gap-situation-eu_en&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2016/03/20/upshot/as-women-take-over-a-male-dominated-field-the-pay-drops.html&quot;&gt;https://www.nytimes.com/2016/03/20/upshot/as-women-take-over-a-male-dominated-field-the-pay-drops.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://human-resources-health.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12960-019-0406-0&quot;&gt;https://human-resources-health.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12960-019-0406-0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover image:&lt;/strong&gt; “Matchgirl strikers”, Unknown author. Wikimedia Commons https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Matchgirl_strikers.PNG&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Liz</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="biography" />
      
        <category term="sex based rights" />
      
        <category term="equality" />
      
        <category term="why seen" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In this time of strikes by the public service professions dominated by women, I’ve been reflecting on the often-overlooked history of women in the UK trade union movement and parallels to today, where many women still struggle to have their needs met for appropriate pay and suitable health and safety conditions, including to protect them during pregnancy and maternity.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">International Women’s Day 2023</title>
      <link href="/posts/2023-03-08-international-womens-day/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="International Women’s Day 2023" />
      <published>2023-03-08T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-03-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/international-womens-day</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2023-03-08-international-womens-day/">&lt;p&gt;At my mixed-sex primary school, our playground consisted simply of one big rectangle made of concrete. The playground didn’t have any lines marked on it, and it had no goal posts. And yet every playtime and lunchtime, it became a football pitch for the boys, the goals marked by their grubby jumpers. God help you if you were a boy who didn’t like football, but that’s another story. We girls gathered around the edges, chatting, skipping, cartwheeling, or playing endless games of catch. If we strayed onto the football pitch, the boys met us with shouts and shoves. When the football got kicked out, we were expected to toss it back to the boys in the right direction.  Occasionally a particularly bolshy girl (future feminists of the UK? You know who you are, ladies) would boot the football away into the car-park and then all hell would break loose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We girls grumbled to each other, but it never occurred to us to complain to the teachers. That was just the way it was. Anyway, what would we say? Our child’s sense of fairness couldn’t explain in words what intuitively angered us. There was no school rule that girls weren’t allowed to play anywhere on the playground. There was no school rule against us joining the boys to play football (although I never saw a girl dare, even those of us who enjoyed football outside school). It was just natural that the boys should be entitled to use all the playground, because they needed it to play football. The rules were the same for everyone and so it was fair.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These days we might call our playground rules &lt;em&gt;‘gender blind’&lt;/em&gt;, or that coy phrase, &lt;em&gt;‘gender neutral’&lt;/em&gt;. ‘Gender neutral’ must be good because it means we treat males and females the same and thereby ensure there is no sexism and therefore equality… right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was thinking about our school playground while reflecting on this year’s civil service theme for International Women’s Day: &lt;em&gt;‘equity’&lt;/em&gt;. Equity is our middle name here at SEEN and a key value for us, so we think a lot about what equity means and what needs to be done to achieve it. Equality and equity are complementary concepts of fairness, appropriate to different circumstances. Ensuring equity at work and in wider society sometimes requires treating women and men differently, according to our different rights and needs. The rules might be applied equally but there may still be unfairness, so how do we deal with this?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grown-up life has often seemed to me very like our school playground. Yes, women are allowed to walk around town just like men do, but some men still decide to shout at us and shove us for taking up space. Yes, women are allowed to be in the digital town square of Twitter just like men are, but we’d better be prepared to cope with rape threats, death threats and cyber stalking. Yes, women are allowed to get good jobs, but we still end up being a minority in many of the best-paid professions and getting paid less in almost every profession.  This is especially so if and when we take on that extra job for which there can never be ‘gender neutrality’: pregnancy and motherhood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are no rules specifying any of this inequity, and actually in the UK we now have laws against much of it. But women and girls still continue to be treated unfairly because of our sex. Our reality is not ‘gender neutral’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;True equity means that all of us, women and men, need to work to change our culture in all the small and big ways which will enable women and girls to take up space and thrive in the same way that we allow to men and boys. Until then, true equality remains an illusion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please &lt;a href=&quot;/contact/&quot;&gt;write to us&lt;/a&gt; at SEEN and let us know your experiences of barriers to women in your public service workplace, and what you think can be done to improve equity for women staff. We hope later to publish some of your experiences, with your agreement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally… please join us in taking 3 minutes right now to celebrate International Women’s Day with us and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZrVLL7soS1U&quot;&gt;the wonderful Helen Reddy singing &lt;em&gt;“I am Woman, Hear me Roar”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. We send love and solidarity to all our SEEN members and supporters. Please roar along!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/ZrVLL7soS1U&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Related SEEN articles you may have missed&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Teenage girls and neurodiversity - &lt;a href=&quot;/posts/2023-02-27-why-is-seen-important-to-me-iv/&quot;&gt;https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-02-27-why-is-seen-important-to-me-iv/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Being a woman - &lt;a href=&quot;/posts/2023-01-25-why-is-seen-important-to-me-iii/&quot;&gt;https://seen-network.uk/posts/2023-01-25-why-is-seen-important-to-me-iii/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Violence against women - &lt;a href=&quot;/posts/2022-11-25-ending-violence-against-women/&quot;&gt;https://seen-network.uk/posts/2022-11-25-ending-violence-against-women/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover image:&lt;/strong&gt; “Students take a break from school on the playground” by World Bank Photo Collection is licensed under CC BY-NC-ND 2.0. To view a copy of this license, visit https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd-nc/2.0/jp/?ref=openverse.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>UNSEEN</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="personal experience" />
      
        <category term="equality" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">At my mixed-sex primary school, our playground consisted simply of one big rectangle made of concrete. The playground didn’t have any lines marked on it, and it had no goal posts. And yet every playtime and lunchtime, it became a football pitch for the boys, the goals marked by their grubby jumpers. God help you if you were a boy who didn’t like football, but that’s another story. We girls gathered around the edges, chatting, skipping, cartwheeling, or playing endless games of catch. If we strayed onto the football pitch, the boys met us with shouts and shoves. When the football got kicked out, we were expected to toss it back to the boys in the right direction. Occasionally a particularly bolshy girl (future feminists of the UK? You know who you are, ladies) would boot the football away into the car-park and then all hell would break loose.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
