<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/biography/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2025-08-26T22:05:27+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/biography/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">SEEN | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Sex Equality and Equity Network</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">James Barry: female pioneer</title>
      <link href="/posts/2024-03-03-james-barry-female-pioneer/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="James Barry: female pioneer" />
      <published>2024-03-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2024-03-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/james-barry-female-pioneer</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2024-03-03-james-barry-female-pioneer/">&lt;p&gt;“So tell me”, my first history professor liked to start, after hearing my latest essay, “what have you left out, and how have you filled the gaps?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chose to study history at university because I loved stories. My mum would tell you I loved history from an early age, but I didn’t really, I just liked stories, and history happened to be chock full of tales: tall ones, fairy ones, and true ones alike. Undergraduate history, though, started out a little…dry. Term 1 was historiography, or “the writing of history”. How dull, I thought, how tedious. I’m here to dive into a world of stories, not to philosophise about how different types of historians tell them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was (obviously) completely wrong. My tutor expertly got us to unpick the exciting idea that in telling history, one makes choices. A list of facts is an encyclopaedia, but history weaves a picture and crucially should start a conversation: you look at the evidence, you infer, and you draw conclusions. And then you discuss, because there’s no ‘one way’, and certainly not a precisely objective way, of doing those things. The process can be unconscious – some bits of the past might particularly chime, or have meaning to you – or it can be highly political, wielding history as a weapon to shore up a particular vision of the present. How we see history reflects how we see the world, and also what we want to shape the world to be. So when we’re telling historical stories, what we leave in and out, and how we fill the inevitable gaps in evidence are choices, and not neutral ones. It is personal, and it is political. What kind of historian are you? What lens are you looking through towards the past? Or, if you prefer musicals to history, let Lin Miranda Manual be the tutor: who tells your story?&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where one starts and ends with the story of Dr James Barry is straightforward enough: a girl was born in the late 18th century, and dies in 1865. In between times, though, what do you include, and what do you leave out?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can start with the facts, so far as they are known. Margaret Bulkley was born in Cork, Ireland, around about 1790. Her mother, Mary Anne, took her to London around 1806. This was almost certainly to claim an inheritance from her brother, the artist James Barry, who had died without leaving a will. From here, Margaret disappears, but in 1809 Mary Anne travelled to Edinburgh with a previously unknown nephew, James Barry, who enrolled in Edinburgh University medical school. After graduation, Royal College of Surgeons exams, and some time in London hospitals, James was appointed as a surgeon in the British army in 1815. What followed was a glittering army medical career around different parts of the British Empire - including one of the few c-sections of the time that left both mother and baby alive, and culminating as the prestigious inspector general of hospitals for the army - a smattering of scandal, an infamous and hot-headed meeting with Florence Nightingale, and a reputation for a bad temper, a good heart, and a zealously reforming approach to public health. And then on death – despite leaving instructions to be buried without the traditional laying out and washing - a twist: the discovery that Dr James Barry had “a perfect female body”.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What are we to make of this story? An increasingly popular telling of it in recent years is that Dr James Barry was a transgender, non-binary, or queer pioneer. The Guardian, covering Historic England’s 2016 “Pride of Place” project to recognise LGBT+ history, hailed Barry as a “Secret Victorian Transgender Surgeon”.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Search for historical tours of Edinburgh, and a local tour company offers a blog to mark transgender day of visibility to “shine a light” on James, “a trans man who worked for the British army”.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; One biography of Barry argues that she may have had androgen insensitivity syndrome (a difference of sexual development, or DSD).&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The National Archives, in a resource for teachers to use as a lesson plan with children aged 11-16, rejects any debate, stating:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“He chose to exclusively live and identify as a man, having been assigned female at birth….. ‘Transgender’, meaning someone whose gender identity differs from the sex that they were assigned at birth, was not a term used in the 1800s. However, research has highlighted the significance of James Barry as a transgender man in the history of medicine as both a pioneer and reformer.” &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:6&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To take my tutor’s questions: what do these hot historical takes leave out, and how do they fill the gaps? We could start with the date. James was born around 80 years before the first women (the Edinburgh Seven) were admitted to a British medical school in 1869 (Elizabeth Garrett Anderson qualified in 1865 through private study: this route was then immediately closed to other women). Even after the Edinburgh Seven’s long fight for admission was won, the battles continued: their arrival prompted a notorious student riot, many professors refused to teach the seven women, and Edinburgh later decided the whole thing was a mistake and refused to award them the degrees they had earnt.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:7&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:7&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; No chance, then, for a girl like Margaret Bulkley to study medicine 80 years earlier in 1809 - other than by cutting off her long hair, shaving a few years off her cited age, and claiming to be male.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We could also look at her life. We could consider her prospects as a girl of limited means, in a struggling family, at a time when options for women were deeply constrained. We could look, perhaps, at the evidence and suggestion that she was raped when a young teenager, giving birth to a baby in secret who was then brought up as her sister: who experiencing that trauma might not want to identify out of womanhood into the relative safety of a man with status, doing things, going places? From what we can tell of her early life, Margaret appears to be a clever, confident girl, hemmed in by her sex and class - writing to her brother, “Were I not a girl, I would be a soldier!”.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:8&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:8&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; She left no account of herself that sets out her motivations: we can only infer from tiny slivers of evidence.. What do you make of her travelling with a trunk full of hidden women’s fashion plates from magazines? Or that the original plan might have been to study medicine in Edinburgh as a man for a few years, but then live and practise as a doctor in Venezuela, as a woman?&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:9&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:9&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frequently in the case of James Barry, the lens through which the story is currently told is firmly based in gender ideology. Even when tellings of her story try to tread a ‘neutral’ line, they end up tying themselves in knots: the University of Edinburgh’s historic alumni page posits the lengthy, fence sitting, “to give Barry the full respect they are due, and to refer to them by the correct gender, it would be useful to know if they considered themselves to be a man, or if they identified as a woman all along”.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:10&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:10&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Two of her biographers manage to state both that, “James Barry identified as a man and was indisputably transgender”, but also was “not a trans man in the full modern sense of that term”; and that Barry “enjoyed living as a man”, but “was never fully comfortable in his masculine identity”. At the end of this slightly mangled thought process, they conclude that, “had Margaret Bulkley been born in 1989…it’s likely she wouldn’t have transitioned but it’s possible that she would have lived as nonbinary”.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:11&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:11&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Right. There is no room, it seems, to examine her achievements just as one of those boring old binary women. Debate and discussion, based on evidence, is at the heart of history, but the National Archives constructs a ‘No Debate’ lesson plan, admonishing teachers and pupils that, “his biological sex became a matter of discussion…(after his death)…Such an intrusion into a person’s personal life is completely unacceptable today”.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:12&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:12&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I read different accounts of Barry’s life, it reminds me of the controversy in 2022 when the Globe theatre in London announced a production about Joan of Arc, “reimagining” her as non-binary. As Victoria Smith wrote in The Critic at the time,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“In this reading, Joan is no longer an exceptional woman; by being exceptional, she is no longer a woman at all.” &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:13&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:13&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To become a doctor more than half a century before women were formally admitted to medical schools, to have a successful career in the army 130 years before women were recognised as a permanent part of the British armed forces&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:14&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:14&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, and to carve out a life outside the confines of sexist gender roles at a point in history when women were fundamentally constrained by them, is an extraordinary achievement by any measure. The personal toll of it – not least in the difficulty in forming close relationships, but also in living the opposite of an ‘authentic life’ – must have been substantial: to maintain it undiscovered, until your death, would have required immense determination and courage. And so, naturally, it has to be taken away. Not an extraordinary woman at all, not someone proving what women were capable of in extremis: someone, instead, who opted out of womanhood altogether.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a political choice to claim James Barry as transgender or non-binary, and to use masculine or neutral pronouns for her. It is a censorious political choice to attempt to shut down historians proposing other interpretations, that focus on other motivations, or look at the context in which she forged a life for herself, over a possible interpretation of gender identity. That people so frequently do so (and present it as progress) makes me uncomfortable as a historian: as a woman and a feminist, it makes me angry. History is full of women pretending to be men, or aping male clothes and behaviour, both temporarily and permanently. They did it for reasons of safety, ambition, opportunity, money, necessity, and personal fulfilment. I don’t know whether any of them would recognise a modern concept of gender identity, and neither, of course, does any historian claiming them to be trans or non-binary. I don’t think it is, as the University of Edinburgh and the National Archives suggest, disrespectful to refer to James Barry as a woman: I think it’s far more disrespectful to co-opt her for a political movement that seeks to prioritise gender identity over sex, and erases as it does so both the achievements of women, and a long history of gender non-conformity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I said earlier that history was a conversation. My contribution to that conversation is this: we should say, loudly, and with admiration, that James Barry was a woman. We should tell our daughters: look, even in the most constrained of circumstances, look what women can do. Look what women can achieve. And how wonderful that you, 21st century girl, no longer need to opt out of womanhood to be any kind of pioneer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;•·················•·················•&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover photo&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Barry_(surgeon)#/media/File:James_Barry.jpg&quot;&gt;Wikipedia Public Domain&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ppXigfLHZog&amp;amp;t=198s&quot;&gt;“Who Lives, Who Dies, Who Tells Your Story” from HAMILTON (youtube.com)&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Dr James Barry: A Woman Ahead of Her Time, Dr Michael du Preez and Jeremy Dronfield &lt;a href=&quot;https://oneworld-publications.com/work/dr-james-barry/&quot;&gt;Dr James Barry - Oneworld (oneworld-publications.com)&lt;/a&gt;; The Secret Life of Dr James Barry, Rachel Holmes &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloomsbury.com/uk/secret-life-of-dr-james-barry-9781408891575/&quot;&gt;The Secret Life of Dr James Barry: Victorian England’s Most Eminent Surgeon: Rachel Holmes: Bloomsbury Publishing&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/society/2017/jul/25/secret-transgender-victorian-surgeon-feted-by-heritage-england&quot;&gt;Secret transgender Victorian surgeon feted by Historic England - Transgender - The Guardian&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mercattours.com/blog-post/lgbtq-history-james-barry&quot;&gt;LGBTQ+ History: The Story of James Barry (mercattours.com)&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloomsbury.com/uk/secret-life-of-dr-james-barry-9781408891575/&quot;&gt;The Secret Life of Dr James Barry: Victorian England’s Most Eminent Surgeon: Rachel Holmes: Bloomsbury Publishing&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/education/resources/dr-james-barry/&quot;&gt;Dr James Barry - The National Archives&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:6&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:7&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-scotland-edinburgh-east-fife-47814747&quot;&gt;Edinburgh seven doctors to graduate after 150 years - BBC News&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:7&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:8&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;du Preez and Dronfield, ibid &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:8&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:9&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;du Preez and Dronfield, ibid &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:9&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:10&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ed.ac.uk/medicine-vet-medicine/about/history/historic-alumni/james-barry&quot;&gt;James Barry - The University of Edinburgh&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:10&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:11&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kingshealthpartners.org/latest/3265-guest-article-dr-james-barry-and-the-united-hospitals-by-jeremy-dronfield&quot;&gt;The Bulkley-Barry-Cooper Professorship​ King’s Health Partners (kingshealthpartners.org)&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:11&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:12&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/education/resources/dr-james-barry/&quot;&gt;Dr James Barry - The National Archives&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:12&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:13&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://thecritic.co.uk/transing-joan/&quot;&gt;Transing Joan - Victoria Smith - The Critic Magazine&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:13&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:14&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nam.ac.uk/explore/timeline-women-army&quot;&gt;A timeline of women in the Army - National Army Museum (nam.ac.uk)&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:14&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>UNSEEN</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="appropriation of female achievement" />
      
        <category term="biography" />
      
        <category term="language" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“So tell me”, my first history professor liked to start, after hearing my latest essay, “what have you left out, and how have you filled the gaps?”</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Why SEEN is important to me (vi)</title>
      <link href="/posts/2023-04-24-why-is-seen-important-to-me-vi/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why SEEN is important to me (vi)" />
      <published>2023-04-24T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-04-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/why-is-seen-important-to-me-vi</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2023-04-24-why-is-seen-important-to-me-vi/">&lt;p&gt;In this time of strikes by the public service professions dominated by women, I’ve been reflecting on the often-overlooked history of women in the UK trade union movement and parallels to today, where many women still struggle to have their needs met for appropriate pay and suitable health and safety conditions, including to protect them during pregnancy and maternity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new film &lt;em&gt;Enola Holmes 2&lt;/em&gt; features (spoiler alert) the story of young women and girls working in a match factory, and striking for better pay and conditions. Whilst romanticised elements were added, the story is grounded in fact. 1888 was the start of action by an unlikely group of heroic young women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Girls and women in the Bryant and May match factory in Bow, now a block of luxury flats, were treated appallingly. They worked 12-hour shifts, standing up, dipping wooden matches into a mixture of chemicals which included the highly dangerous white phosphorus, and packing them into boxes. The chemical caused toothaches which worsened into abscesses and necrosis of the jaw – a condition known as “phossy jaw”. As depicted in &lt;em&gt;Enola Holmes 2&lt;/em&gt;, the managers often dismissed the girls and women affected. The pay for this work was very meagre, and halved for girls under the age of 18, even though they were doing the same work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/3/32/Matchgirl_strikers.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of matchgirls participating in a strike against Bryant &amp;amp; May, London 1888&quot; title=&quot;Photo of matchgirls participating in a strike against Bryant &amp;amp; May, London 1888&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The socialist activist and author Annie Besant took up the cause. She interviewed a number of workers, and wrote a shocking and damning article for her own magazine, &lt;em&gt;The Link&lt;/em&gt;, which she entitled &lt;em&gt;“White Slavery in London”&lt;/em&gt;. In it, she described the factory as being like a “prison-house” and the match girls as “undersized, helpless and oppressed”, with one child living on “only bread-and-butter and tea, alike for breakfast and dinner”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Annie Besant’s article enraged the factory owners, who threatened to sue her, and put pressure on their employees to deny the truth of it. The employees wrote to Annie:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Dear lady, they are trying to get the poor girls to say that it is all lies that has been printed and sign papers to say it is lies. Dear lady, we will not sign them.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When one of the women was sacked on suspicion of being the author, on 5th July 1888, all 1,400 women and girls went on strike: “One girl began, and the rest said ‘yes’ so out we all went.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Annie Besant supported the matchmakers to set up a union, led by eight of the matchmakers, including Sarah Chapman, who features in &lt;em&gt;Enola Holmes 2&lt;/em&gt;. They were supported by Annie’s colleagues in the Fabian Society, by Toynbee Hall (an enterprise for social change in the East End, which supported the strike fund) and by newspapers including the widely read &lt;em&gt;Pall Mall Gazette&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;The Times&lt;/em&gt;. Annie took a group of 56 strikers to Parliament, and MPs raised questions about their treatment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within a fortnight of the strike starting, the Bryant and May directors, horrified by the negative publicity, caved completely and met all of the strikers’ demands. Sarah Chapman became the first Matchmakers’ Union delegate, and first woman, to attend the Trades Union Congress, where a resolution was passed stating that men and women should be paid at the same rate for equal work. The match girls’ strike inspired the men of the East End to undertake the dockers’ strike a few weeks later, which closed the Thames for a month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;125 years after the match girls’ strike, I named my own daughter Annie, after Annie Besant – and at 10 she shows every sign of being a similarly fierce feminist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it wasn’t until over a century later,that the Equal Pay Act 1970 was passed, led by Barbara Castle, and it was 1976 before the Act came into force. This followed a 1970 strike by women workers at the Ford factory in Dagenham (also depicted in a film, &lt;em&gt;Made in Dagenham&lt;/em&gt;) because they were paid 15% less than men for the same work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even now, UK legislation only covers disparities between men and women working for the same employer. Government statistics for the UK for 2022 indicate that there remains a median pay gap between men and women of 9.71%. This is attributed to women being more likely to work part-time due to caring responsibilities, with part-time working commanding less pay bargaining power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are also lower rates of pay for professions in which women are or become the majority, a phenomenon known as “workforce feminisation”, whereby female dominated occupations or workplaces are paid less than those which are male-dominated, even if they were previously male-dominated. As the European Commission states: &lt;em&gt;“Highly feminised jobs tend to be systematically undervalued.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pay disparity for women increases with pregnancy, childbirth and care of infants, and again as women reach their 40s, with many reducing their hours to care both for their children and elderly relatives, while often suffering from stress and fatigue. The pay gap is also significantly larger for women from some ethnic groups and for women with disabilities and health challenges, who are likely to suffer particularly from further social and economic barriers to obtaining well-paid work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The workforce “feminisation problem” may also be an issue in some parts of the civil service, and we know there remain other barriers to women thriving in the civil service. This is why it’s so important that SEEN highlights discrimination that is connected to sex and reminds employers to collect and keep sex-disaggregated data. When it comes to equal pay and to health and safety at work, sex really matters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;sources-and-further-reading&quot;&gt;Sources and further reading:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.matchgirls1888.org/the-story-of-the-strike&quot;&gt;https://www.matchgirls1888.org/the-story-of-the-strike&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matchgirls%27_strike&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matchgirls%27_strike&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/dit-gender-pay-gap-report-and-data-2021-to-2022/dit-gender-pay-gap-report-2021-to-2022#:~:text=or%20a%20woman.-,The%20gender%20pay%20gap,to%20%C2%A32.68%20in%202021&quot;&gt;https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/dit-gender-pay-gap-report-and-data-2021-to-2022/dit-gender-pay-gap-report-2021-to-2022#:~:text=or%20a%20woman.-,The%20gender%20pay%20gap,to%20%C2%A32.68%20in%202021&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://commission.europa.eu/strategy-and-policy/policies/justice-and-fundamental-rights/gender-equality/equal-pay/gender-pay-gap-situation-eu_en&quot;&gt;https://commission.europa.eu/strategy-and-policy/policies/justice-and-fundamental-rights/gender-equality/equal-pay/gender-pay-gap-situation-eu_en&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2016/03/20/upshot/as-women-take-over-a-male-dominated-field-the-pay-drops.html&quot;&gt;https://www.nytimes.com/2016/03/20/upshot/as-women-take-over-a-male-dominated-field-the-pay-drops.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://human-resources-health.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12960-019-0406-0&quot;&gt;https://human-resources-health.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12960-019-0406-0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover image:&lt;/strong&gt; “Matchgirl strikers”, Unknown author. Wikimedia Commons https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Matchgirl_strikers.PNG&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Liz</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="biography" />
      
        <category term="sex based rights" />
      
        <category term="equality" />
      
        <category term="why seen" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In this time of strikes by the public service professions dominated by women, I’ve been reflecting on the often-overlooked history of women in the UK trade union movement and parallels to today, where many women still struggle to have their needs met for appropriate pay and suitable health and safety conditions, including to protect them during pregnancy and maternity.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Gluck</title>
      <link href="/posts/2023-02-26-gluck/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Gluck" />
      <published>2023-02-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-02-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/gluck</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2023-02-26-gluck/">&lt;p&gt;Another forgotten hero for LGBT history month, another lesser known artist from the 20th Century, this time a woman.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gluck&lt;/strong&gt; (born Hannah Gluckstein on 13 August 1895) was a British painter and lesbian who refused to conform to expectations: about her art, how she presented or who she loved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Hannah_Gluckstein_SAAM-1970.70_2.jpg&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; aria-label=&quot;this link opens in a new window&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/0/0b/Hannah_Gluckstein_SAAM-1970.70_2.jpg&quot; width=&quot;300&quot; alt=&quot;A portrait of Gluck by the artist Romaine Brooks&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;figcaption style=&quot;text-align: center; font-size:.8em;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A portrait of Gluck by the artist Romaine Brooks (1923-1924)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She was the daughter of Joseph Gluckstein (brother to the founders of J. Lyons and Co., the coffee house and catering empire) and had a privileged London upbringing, after which she attended St John’s Wood School of Art (1913-1916).  However, from here her life was to take anything but a conventional path.  Instead of settling into London society to marry and paint watercolours, she ran away with her fellow art student and lover, E M Craig (known by her surname, ‘Craig’).  Their destination was the Cornish artists community of Lamorna.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once there, Gluck was finally free to be herself.  She smoked a pipe and rejected the prefixes that would automatically identify a woman as married or single (Miss or Mrs).  In common with some of her lesbian friends, she sometimes used a male name (in her case the names Peter and Hig).  However, she always refused the label ‘Mr’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just like her life, no labels could contain Gluck’s art.  As &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/artanddesign/gallery/2017/feb/08/gluck-painter-fine-art-society&quot;&gt;The Guardian&lt;/a&gt; described: &lt;em&gt;“In keeping with her personality, however, she refused to identify with any particular school or painting movement”&lt;/em&gt;.  Despite this, Gluck’s first solo exhibition in 1924, sold all fifty seven paintings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gluck wore her hair short and dressed in tailored menswear, a style popular with lesbians at the time.  This was an era before women-only dating sites, magazines or bars and to be an open lesbian was a matter of social shame and exclusion, so lesbians in the 1920’s and 1930’s had to rely on such codes to identify one another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gluck was to go on to have a passionate romance with civil servant, food writer and florist &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Constance_Spry&quot;&gt;Constance Spry&lt;/a&gt;, who is likely to have been the inspiration for many of Gluck’s floral paintings in the 1930’s.  One particularly striking painting from 1936 depicts a plant known as &lt;em&gt;‘Lords and Ladies’&lt;/em&gt;.  This curious plant is in fact carnivorous.  Insects fall into the lily like tubes and drown and are dissolved in the pool of liquid in the base.  A fiercely unconventional choice of bouquet for a lady.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although Gluck successfully exhibited and sold her work throughout the 1920’s and 1930’s, it was her portrait known as &lt;em&gt;‘Medallion’&lt;/em&gt; (1937), perhaps her most famous, which was to cement her legacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/gandalfsgallery/51121322455&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; aria-label=&quot;this link opens in a new window&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51121322455_b332f19d77_w.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Medallion by Gluck&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;figcaption style=&quot;text-align: center; font-size:.8em;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A portrait of Gluck by the artist Romaine Brooks (1923-1924)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    &lt;figcaption style=&quot;text-align: center; font-size:.8em;&quot;&gt;Creative commons from gandalfsgallery on flickr.com (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/gandalfsgallery/51121322455&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; aria-label=&quot;this link opens in a new window&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/2.0/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; aria-label=&quot;this link opens in a new window&quot;&gt;licence&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This portrait emerged from Gluck’s relationship with Nesta Obermer, which began with a visit in May 1936 to Obermer’s family home in East Sussex.  Following this meeting Gluck concluded her relationship with Spry (and, in a very gentlemanly gesture, apparently burning Spry’s love letters on a bonfire shortly afterwards).  The relationship with Orbermer that followed was one of the most important of her life and the inspiration for &lt;em&gt;Medallion&lt;/em&gt;.  This dual portrait of Gluck and Obermer, was apparently inspired by a night out together attending Mozart’s Don Giovanni.  Described in &lt;a href=&quot;https://dianasouhami.com/book/gluck/&quot;&gt;Diana Souhami’s biography to Gluck&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;“They sat together in the third row and felt the intensity of the music fused them both into one person and matched their love.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Medallion&lt;/em&gt; has become an iconic statement of lesbian love and identity, such that it was chosen as the 1982 cover of Radclyffe Hall’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/129223.The_Well_of_Loneliness&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;‘The Well of Loneliness’&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gluck’s love affairs were multiple and passionate.  However like many famous historical lesbians (such as both Radclyffe Hall and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anne_Lister&quot;&gt;Anne Lister&lt;/a&gt;) those she loved were not always prepared to defy the conventions of their times.  Obermer never left her husband for her ‘wife’ Gluck.  That said, it’s probably fair to add that Gluck was not overly restrained by expectations of monogamy.  She also lived with another female lover during her relationship with Obermer.  This was the journalist Edith Shackleton Heald, who she met in 1943 and who was also lover to WB Yeats.  It was all very exciting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, after the success of Gluck’s early career, by the interwar period she was falling out of fashion.  After her relationship with Obermer ended, so too did Gluck’s art.  Although she continued her relationship with Shackleton Heald and the two moved to Sussex, she painted nothing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would be the 1960’s before Gluck’s inspiration returned, with new paintings and a well-received solo show.  Gluck’s last major work (completed 1973) was a painting of a fish head entitled &lt;em&gt;‘Rage, Rage against the Dying of the Light’&lt;/em&gt; (a possible reference to the Dylan Thomas poem &lt;a href=&quot;https://poets.org/poem/do-not-go-gentle-good-night&quot;&gt;‘Do Not Go Gentle into that good night’&lt;/a&gt;).  Until the end, a woman of unconventionality, fire and defiance.  Shacklton Heald died in 1976, followed two years later by Gluck in 1978, at the age of 82.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m grateful for the following articles, which I drew upon when researching Gluck, and which provide further insights into her life and images of her work:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Guardian&lt;/em&gt; 2021 article in collaboration with &lt;em&gt;Art UK&lt;/em&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/artanddesign/2021/feb/02/the-great-british-art-tour-national-portait-gallery-london-gluck&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Great British Art Tour: Gluck shapes herself with gender defiance&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;museumcrush.org&lt;/em&gt; | &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://museumcrush.org/the-enigma-of-gluck-discovering-the-artist-behind-the-lesbian-icon/&quot;&gt;The enigma of Gluck: Discovering the artist behind the lesbian icon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;See also &lt;em&gt;AfterEllen.com&lt;/em&gt; | &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://afterellen.com/gluck-the-lesbian-artist-who-rejected-gender-and-genre/&quot;&gt;Gluck: The Artist Who Rejected Gender and Genre&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Bethany</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="lesbian gay and bisexual" />
      
        <category term="sexual orientation" />
      
        <category term="biography" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Another forgotten hero for LGBT history month, another lesser known artist from the 20th Century, this time a woman.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Willem Arondeus</title>
      <link href="/posts/2023-02-21-willem-arondeus/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Willem Arondeus" />
      <published>2023-02-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-02-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/posts/willem-arondeus</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/posts/2023-02-21-willem-arondeus/">&lt;p&gt;This LGBT History Month we would like to invite a celebration of some lesser known heroes who don’t always feature on the mainstream narrative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Willem Arondeus&lt;/strong&gt; (22 August 1894 – 1 July 1943) was a Dutch artist and author and hero of the Dutch anti-Nazi resistance movement during World War II.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/f/f3/Willem_Arondeus.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A portrait photograph of Willem Arondeus&quot; title=&quot;Willem Arondeus (1894-1943) Dutch writer, painter and partisan&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arondeus is worth celebrating as a talented artist and writer in his own right. However it is his incredible bravery which was to create his finest legacy. Not only was he openly gay at a time when homosexuality was stigmatised, but during the war he was active in the Dutch resistance, a decision that would ultimately lead to his murder by the Nazis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1942, Arondeus began an underground periodical called the &lt;em&gt;Brandarisbrief&lt;/em&gt; in which he called on artists to resist the occupying Nazi army. He later became more directly involved in the resistance, joining an underground organisation known as the ‘CKC’, creating forged documents along with a lesbian resistant Frieda Belinfante. This was important work, however the success of these forgeries was hampered by the Municipal Office for Population Registration, which checked documents and could expose their work as fakes. It was for this reason that Arondeus and others developed a daring plan to go one step further and destroy the whole Municipal office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this is what they did. On 27th March 1943, the building was blown up, destroying 800,000 identity cards (15% of the records), hindering Gestapo efforts to identify Dutch Jews and others wanted by the Nazis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, an unknown betrayer led the Gestapo to Arondeus, who was arrested five days later on 1st April. Brave, even under interrogation (and likely torture), Arondeus refused to betray the other resistance fighters involved. Sadly his notebook was found, and eventually the majority of the group were arrested.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nearly three months later, on 18 June 1943, Arondeus was tried and sentenced to death, along with 13 other men who participated in the attack. Almost all were executed on 1 July 1943, save for two young doctors who received prison sentences. One possible reason for this was because Arondeus took full responsibility for the attack. Frieda Belifante was the only other member of the resistance group to survive, which she did by disguising herself as a man and going undercover. (She eventually escaped to Switzerland and then emigrating to the United States, where she became a founding artistic director and conductor of the Orange County Philharmonic, a story itself worthy of a blog.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was, however, no escape for Arondeus. In a final act of defiance and bravery, before his execution, Arondeus made sure it was known that he and two of the other men in the group (Bakker and Brouwer) were gay. His last words before his execution were: &lt;em&gt;“Tell the people that homosexuals can be brave!”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1945, after the liberation of the Netherlands, Arondeus’s family was awarded a posthumous medal by the Dutch government in his honour. In 1984, he was awarded the Resistance Memorial Cross. Yad Vashem recognised Arondeus as Righteous Among the Nations on 19th June 1986.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He is certainly an inspirational hero who deserves to be better known for his bravery and also for his beautiful art.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/8/8b/Willem_Arondeus_-_Bloesems_belofte_wordt_nu_in_oogsten_vervuld%2C_september_-_Rijksmuseum_Amsterdam_-_RP-T-1930-87.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A 1930-31 calendar design for September, by Willem Arondeus&quot; title=&quot;Calendar design for September, drawing, 1930–31&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For anyone who is interested in amplifying his legacy, high quality images of his work can be downloaded for free from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rijksmuseum.nl/en/search?q=&amp;quot;Willem Arondéus&amp;quot;&quot;&gt;Rijksmuseum&lt;/a&gt;, Amsterdam and make beautiful prints.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m grateful to the contributors towards this Wikipedia article which I’ve drawn on in the above biography: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Willem_Arondeus&quot;&gt;Willem Arondeus - Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Bethany</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="lesbian gay and bisexual" />
      
        <category term="sexual orientation" />
      
        <category term="biography" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">This LGBT History Month we would like to invite a celebration of some lesser known heroes who don’t always feature on the mainstream narrative.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
